<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aulicus coquinariæ or a vindication in ansvver to a pamphlet, entituled The court and character of King James. Pretended to be penned by Sir A.W. and published since his death, 1650.</title>
            <author>Sanderson, William, Sir, 1586?-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S645</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1356_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203447</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863401</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169833</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94193)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169833)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 178:E1356[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aulicus coquinariæ or a vindication in ansvver to a pamphlet, entituled The court and character of King James. Pretended to be penned by Sir A.W. and published since his death, 1650.</title>
                  <author>Sanderson, William, Sir, 1586?-1676.</author>
                  <author>Heylyn, Peter, 1660-1662, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 205, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Seile, over against St. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650 [i.e. 1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Sir William Sanderson.</note>
                  <note>A reply to the work by Sir Anthony Weldon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Aulicus coquinariæ: or the character &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Marsh 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Weldon, Anthony, --  Sir, d. 1649? --  Court and character of King James.</term>
               <term>James, --  Sir, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169833:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aulicus Coquinariae:</hi> OR A VINDICATION IN ANSWER TO A PAMPHLET, <hi>ENTITVLED The Court and Character of KING JAMES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pretended to be penned by Sir <hi>A. W.</hi> and publiſhed ſince his death, 1650.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Auribus oculiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recepta.</l>
               <l>Nemeſis à tergo.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Seile,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:169833:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 20. <hi>which</hi> read <hi>with.</hi> p. 7. l. 24. <hi>Chimſtry</hi> r. <hi>Chimiſtry.</hi> p. 11. l. 15. <hi>Turnpike.</hi> p. 36. l. 24. <hi>ſore.</hi> p. 39. l. 10. <hi>Tercera's.</hi> p. 45. l. 1. <hi>deſerve.</hi> p. 52. l. 14. <hi>Aſſaſſinations.</hi> p. 54. l. 5. <hi>to.</hi> p. 54. l. 7. <hi>Exception.</hi> p. 67. l. 15. <hi>the.</hi> p. 82. l. 2. <hi>leave.</hi> p. 97. l. 6. <hi>of.</hi> p. 105. l. 24 <hi>was.</hi> p. 120. l. 11. <hi>her.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:169833:2"/>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are ſome <hi>Men</hi> ſo <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>ſinne,</hi> who rather than be <hi>idle</hi> from doing <hi>evil,</hi> will take much pains to <hi>ſcandall</hi> the <hi>Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My fear to <hi>offend,</hi> hath <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held</hi> my hand a convenient time, leſt I ſhould <hi>fall</hi> into the like <hi>error</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> that <hi>publiſhed</hi> the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> Entituled, <hi>The Court &amp; Character of King
<pb facs="tcp:169833:3"/>James,</hi> and <hi>Father's</hi> the <hi>Brat</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sir <hi>A. VV;</hi> And if <hi>common fame</hi> miſtake not the <hi>meaning, His Parent</hi> took <hi>riſe</hi> from Q. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeths</hi> Kitchin, and left it a <hi>Legacy</hi> for preferment of his <hi>Iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Man</hi> went the ſame way, and by <hi>grace</hi> of the <hi>Court</hi> got up to the <hi>Green-cloth.</hi> Jn which place attending <hi>King James</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> he <hi>practiſed</hi> there to <hi>libell</hi> that <hi>Nation,</hi> which at his return home was found wrapt up in a <hi>Record</hi> of that <hi>Board,</hi> and by the hand being known to be <hi>his, he</hi> was deſervedly <hi>removed out,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169833:3"/>as <hi>unworthy to eat of his bread, whoſe Birth-right he had ſo vilely defamed.</hi> Yet by <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> with a piece of <hi>money</hi> in his <hi>Purſe,</hi> and <hi>a penſion</hi> to boot, to <hi>preſerve</hi> him <hi>loyall</hi> during his <hi>life,</hi> though as a bad <hi>creditor,</hi> he took this <hi>courſe</hi> to <hi>repay him</hi> to the <hi>purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I have heard, that in his <hi>life,</hi> he <hi>diſcovered</hi> a <hi>part</hi> of this <hi>Peece</hi> to his fellow <hi>Courtier,</hi> who earneſtly diſwaded him not to publiſh ſo <hi>defective</hi> and <hi>falſe</hi> a <hi>ſcandall,</hi> which as it ſeems in <hi>Conſcience</hi> he ſo <hi>declin'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore my <hi>Exception</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169833:4"/>willingly <hi>falls</hi> upon the practice of the <hi>Publiſher,</hi> who by his <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> may <hi>abuſe</hi> us with this falſe Story, which he diſcovers to the <hi>Reader</hi> in <hi>5 Remarkable Paſſages,</hi> and gives me the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſpare my <hi>cenſure</hi> on the <hi>deceaſed perſon:</hi> but to bestow my <hi>unkindneſs</hi> (which neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily <hi>intervenes</hi> in this <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)</hi> on him who yet <hi>lives,</hi> to make out his <hi>bad act</hi> with a <hi>Reply</hi> (if he pleaſe) more <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent,</hi> upon Me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:169833:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>QUeen</hi> Elizabeth pag. 1</item>
               <item>1. Remark. Gowryes <hi>Conſpiracy, of the name</hi> Ruthens, <hi>and Family, the manner of the Treaſon, and effects af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erwards</hi> 5</item>
               <item>George Sprott, <hi>Confederate with</hi> Gowry, <hi>his confeſſions, arraignment, execution, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony hereof</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>E. of</hi> Eſſex <hi>his Character, undertakings, Treaſon and execution,</hi> 36</item>
               <item>Caecils. <hi>Sir</hi> Rob. Caecil <hi>his ſervices, ſickneſſe, and death</hi> 49</item>
               <item>Hen. Howard, <hi>E. of</hi> Northampton, <hi>his character and death</hi> 64</item>
               <item>James <hi>L.</hi> Hay, <hi>E.</hi> Carliſle <hi>his character, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies, and Interest</hi> 67</item>
               <item>2. Remark. <hi>Sir</hi> Walter Raleigh <hi>his character, treaſon, tryall, and reprieve; obſervations upon him, and his former voyage to</hi> Guiana, <hi>ſentence, and execution</hi> 74</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Tho. Lake <hi>his character, riſing, &amp; ruine, with his Wife and Daughter</hi> 98</item>
               <item>3. Remark. <hi>Sir</hi> Tho. Overbury, <hi>and Sir</hi> Rob. Carr 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Nullity of</hi> Eſſex <hi>Marriage with</hi> Suffolk's <hi>daughter, with the Legall proceedings</hi> 113</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Archbiſhop</hi> Abbot 130</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:169833:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Rob. Carr, <hi>E. of</hi> Somerſet <hi>his Marriage with</hi> Eſſex's <hi>Relict</hi> 133</item>
               <item>3. Remark. <hi>Sir</hi> Tho. Overbury, <hi>his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and poyſoned</hi> 135</item>
               <item>Somerſet <hi>and his Wifes tryall, and Sir</hi> Thomas Monſon 138</item>
               <item>4. Remark. <hi>Pr.</hi> Henry <hi>his character, ſickneſs, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and death, not by poyſon</hi> 143</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Arthur Ingram <hi>his condition</hi> 158</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Lionel Cranfield, <hi>E. of</hi> Middleſex, <hi>his birth breeding, and advance</hi> 160</item>
               <item>George Villiers <hi>his diſcent and advance, a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite, and Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>occaſioning ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall narrations, &amp;c.</hi> 164</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>E. of</hi> Nottingham <hi>Admirall</hi> 169</item>
               <item>Egerton <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> 171</item>
               <item>Bacon <hi>Lord Chancellor</hi> 171</item>
               <item>Buckinghams <hi>Kinred.</hi> 174</item>
               <item>Williams <hi>Lord Keeper.</hi> 178</item>
               <item>5. Remark. Spaniſh <hi>Match, the Princes journey into</hi> Spaine, <hi>and return</hi> 179</item>
               <item>Briſtolls <hi>concern'd</hi> 180</item>
               <item>Inicoſſa, <hi>Spaniſh Ambaſſador</hi> 182</item>
               <item>Yelverton <hi>Attorney Generall</hi> 186</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>King</hi> James <hi>ſickneſſe, the playſter, and death,</hi> not by poyſon 192</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Concluſion</hi> 197</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Character</hi> 200</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169833:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Aulicus Coquinariae:</hi> OR THE CHARECTER <hi>Of Him who</hi> SATARIZ'D KING JAMES AND HIS COURT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Ueen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> died,
<note place="margin">Queen E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth.</note> 
               <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1602. having bin long <hi>ſick;</hi> and indeed <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate;</hi> which gave this <hi>State,</hi> time enough to conclude for his reception, the undoubted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169833:6"/>
               <hi>Heir</hi> to theſe <hi>Crownes; JAMES</hi> then King of <hi>Scotland;</hi> She hath been <hi>highly valued,</hi> ſince Her <hi>death;</hi> the beſt of any former <hi>Soveraigne</hi> over us. She was fitted for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes <hi>Darling,</hi> but with ſome <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,</hi> the better to mould Her, for the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of a Kingdome; and for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody of a <hi>Scepter.</hi> She ſhewed Her <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> as a <hi>Preſident</hi> to poſterity. She was a <hi>Princeſſe</hi> learned, even then, when Letters had eſtimation, and began them into <hi>faſhion;</hi> which brought forth many rare and excellent <hi>Men,</hi> both of the <hi>Gowne,</hi> and of the <hi>Sword.</hi> Some ſay, She had many <hi>Favorites,</hi> but in truth She had none. They were neer, and dear to Her, and to Her affaires, as <hi>Partners</hi> of her care; not <hi>Minions</hi> of phanſey. And yet ſuch as they were, ſhe ever <hi>maſtered,</hi> by her own <hi>Rules;</hi> not they Her, by their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169833:6"/>own <hi>Wills.</hi> And ſhe wanted not <hi>many</hi> of them at need, or pleaſure. She was <hi>Magnificent,</hi> (<hi>compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè</hi> with other <hi>Princes;</hi>) which yet ſhe diſpoſed frugally; Having alwaies <hi>much</hi> to do with <hi>little</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: for truly, thoſe either Wiſe or Gallant Men, were never cloied with her <hi>Bounty,</hi> more then in her <hi>Grace;</hi> which with her <hi>Mannage,</hi> paſſed for good <hi>payment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> affaires was to her <hi>Maligne,</hi> which drew her <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> almoſt dry; the only cauſe of diſtemper in the State, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, but with her life. At which time, ſhe left her Cofers <hi>empty,</hi> and yet her Enemies <hi>potent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pamp. 34.</note> And therefore it could be no <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in them, that afterwards <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled</hi> the <hi>Peace,</hi> but rather in ſuch who indeavoured then, and after, the re-eſtabliſhing a <hi>New War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt Her <hi>Favourites</hi> of the <hi>Sword,</hi> none could <hi>boast</hi> more of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169833:7"/>her <hi>Bounty</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſſex. Pamp. 10.</note> then the Earle of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> whoſe <hi>ingrate</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>blown</hi> beyond the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of his <hi>steere,</hi> by too much <hi>Popularity</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> coſened him into that abſolute <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt his <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many <hi>forewarnings</hi> of his neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friends, and unwilling Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his deereſt <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> his open <hi>Rebellion</hi> at laſt brought him to <hi>publique tryall,</hi> condemned and executed as the moſt <hi>ingrate</hi> that former times could produce. (Of which we ſhall take occaſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in ſome particular.) Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Sir <hi>Robert Cecill</hi> acted no more, then a dutiful <hi>Subject, Councelour</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> ought to have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and ſuch like of her time, evermore attempting by <hi>Aſſaſſination</hi> or <hi>Poyſon</hi> to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way her life. As were alſo the like attempts, by others in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (witneſſe the forewarning of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169833:7"/>Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> by expreſſe Meſſage of Sir <hi>Henry Wootton,</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> a year before his comming to theſe <hi>Kingdomes</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Her <hi>beloved</hi> and undoubted <hi>Heir;</hi> and in Them to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>The moſt remarkeable, was,
<note place="margin">Gowries Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> that of <hi>Gowries Conſpiracy,</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And I never read or hear'd (till our <hi>Pamphlet</hi>) <hi>That Sir</hi> George Hewms <hi>his gravity and Wiſdome uſhered him into the Secrets of the KING [therefore] and chiefly to make good that ſtory</hi>].
<note place="margin">Pamph. 8.</note>
               <note place="margin">The firſt paſſage of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</note> For of that <hi>Nation,</hi> both the wiſeſt and moſt honeſt, gave great <hi>Credit</hi> thereto; And the commemoration, was adviſedly ſettled, by <hi>Acts</hi> of their <hi>Parliament;</hi> which <hi>Anathematize</hi> upon <hi>Gowries</hi> Houſe and Name. And <hi>Solemnized</hi> there and here, with <hi>Narratives</hi> in print, of each particular <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> and the ground the cauſe inviting that <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169833:8"/>
            <p>And truely, the <hi>Anniverſary feaſt-day</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> was uſually ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized to God's Glory, by the moſt <hi>Reverend Preachers:</hi> witneſſe thoſe rare Divine <hi>Sermons</hi> of our Biſhop <hi>Andrew's</hi> and others, whoſe <hi>Conſciences</hi> no doubt were not ſo large, to cozen God Almighty with a <hi>fained tale.</hi> Indeed there might have been more <hi>additionall truths,</hi> annexed to the relation, which I have heard, to make it more <hi>apprehenſive</hi> to our <hi>Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leter;</hi> whoſe <hi>Speculations,</hi> in this as in other his ſtories of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> took Information (belike) but in his <hi>Office, Below-ſtaires; And which makes his</hi> faith <hi>drawe downe the effects of thoſe Sermons for the Father,
<note place="margin">Pamp. 10.</note> as a Cauſe of the ſad Events, and ſufferings of the Son, and us all to this preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Name of <hi>Ruthen</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was not notorious, until <hi>Anno</hi> 1568, when <hi>Ruthen</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169833:8"/>others, <hi>confederates,</hi> in thoſe divided times of trouble, laboured, much, for the <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning</hi> Queene <hi>Mary</hi> Mother to King <hi>James.</hi> In 1582. his ſonne <hi>William</hi> was created Earle <hi>Gowry,</hi> in the time of that <hi>King's minority.</hi> Though the father bore deadly hatred to the King's proſperity. And in 1584. himſelfe was in actuall <hi>Rebellion,</hi> in which he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered at <hi>Dondee.</hi> His eldeſt ſon <hi>John,</hi> then in travell in <hi>Italy,</hi> returns home to inherit his lands and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; But not one jot changed in diſpoſition, from the <hi>traiterous</hi> wayes of his <hi>Predeceſſors:</hi> For not long after, he falls into this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy.</hi> Which is not ſo <hi>antient,</hi> but that many then and now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving can relate, and my ſelf, have often heard the repetition.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of <hi>Gowry,</hi> were all of them, much addicted to <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry.</hi> And theſe more, to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169833:9"/>
               <hi>Practiſe;</hi> often publiſhing (as ſuch profeſſors uſually do) more <hi>rare experiments</hi> then ever could be <hi>performed;</hi> wherein the King (a general ſcholar) had little faith. But to <hi>infuſe</hi> more <hi>credit</hi> to the practiſe, <hi>Alexander Ruthen</hi> the ſecond Brother takes this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and withall <hi>conſpires</hi> with <hi>Gowry</hi> to <hi>aſſaſſinate</hi> the King; and taking <hi>opportunity</hi> in his <hi>hunting,</hi> not far from his houſe, St. <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone;</hi> invites the King, to be an eye-witneſſe, of his <hi>producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> In their way, Sir <hi>Thomas Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin</hi> (after Lord <hi>Kelly</hi>), overtakes them and others, Demanding of the Duke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> then preſent; why <hi>Alexander</hi> had <hi>ingroſſed</hi> the King's eare, to carry him from his <hi>ſports? Peace man,</hi> ſaid the Duke, <hi>Wee's all be turned into gold.</hi> Not far they rid, but that the Earle <hi>Gowry,</hi> made good by <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation</hi> his Brother's <hi>ſtory.</hi> And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169833:9"/>thus was the King brought to <hi>Gueſt.</hi> Neere the end of <hi>Dinner,</hi> at his <hi>fruit,</hi> and the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> gone to eate: <hi>Alexander</hi> begs of the King, at this opportunity, to <hi>withdraw,</hi> and to be partaker of his <hi>Production;</hi> to the <hi>view</hi> of that, which yet he could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</p>
            <p>And up he leades the King, into by-lodgings, locking each door behind them, till they came into a <hi>back-Roome:</hi> Where no ſooner entered, but that <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> claps on his <hi>Bonnet,</hi> and with <hi>ſterne Countenance</hi> faces the King; and ſaies: <hi>Now, Sir, you muſt know, I had a father, whoſe bloud calls for revenge, ſhed for your ſake.</hi> The King <hi>amazed,</hi> deales gently with his <hi>fury,</hi> excuſes the <hi>guilt</hi> of his <hi>death,</hi> by his then <hi>Infancy.</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing him, not to lay <hi>violent hands</hi> on the ſacred <hi>Perſon</hi> of his <hi>Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Soveraigne; Eſpecially, in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169833:10"/>cauſe of his <hi>Innocency.</hi> Pleading the <hi>laws</hi> of God and Man: which ſo much wrought upon him, that he ſaid: well, I will ſpeak with my <hi>Brother;</hi> And ſo put the King into a <hi>Lobby Room,</hi> next the <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> where no ſooner <hi>entered,</hi> but that there appeared a fellow, <hi>weaponed,</hi> ready for <hi>execution;</hi> to whoſe <hi>cuſtody</hi> the King is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted till his <hi>return.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> gone downe; the fellow trembles with <hi>Reverence,</hi> puts down his <hi>ſword,</hi> and craves pardon; which gave the King oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to worke upon that paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to aske him whether he reſolved to <hi>murther him?</hi> Being aſſured to the contrary, the King gets leave, to open a <hi>window,</hi> that looked into a back <hi>Court.</hi> When preſently <hi>Alexander</hi> returnes, and tells the King, that he muſt <hi>dy.</hi> But much <hi>affrighted,</hi> at the fellowes <hi>countenance,</hi> with his ſword, offers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169833:10"/>
               <hi>violence</hi> to the King. Which the <hi>fellow ſeemingly oppoſes;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them began a <hi>ſcuffle;</hi> which gave advantage to the King, to cry <hi>Treaſon,</hi> at the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> which looked into a <hi>back Court;</hi> where Sir <hi>Thomas Erskin,</hi> and one <hi>Herries,</hi> were come, In <hi>purſuite</hi> of the King, who was ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mored, to be gone out, the back way to his <hi>hunting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the cry of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and known to be the King's <hi>voice;</hi> they both haſtened up a back ſtaire, called the <hi>Turnepike;</hi> being <hi>directed</hi> by a ſervant of the houſe, who ſaw <hi>Alexander</hi> aſcend that way. And ſo forcing ſome doores, they found them above panting with the <hi>fray;</hi> And up comes alſo, at heeles of them, <hi>John Ramſey</hi> (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Earle of <hi>Holderneſſe</hi>) by them <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſoon <hi>diſpatched.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long after, came the Earle <hi>Gowry</hi> (by his double key) the <hi>first
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169833:11"/>way,</hi> with a caſe of <hi>Rapiers,</hi> his uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>weapons;</hi> and ready drawn. To whom, <hi>Erskin</hi> ſaid, as to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his <hi>purpoſe;</hi> what do you meane my Lord, the King is kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? (for the King was <hi>ſhadowed,</hi> having caſt himſelfe, upon a <hi>Bed,</hi> from his ſight: and his cloak was thrown upon the Body of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> bleeding on the ground.) At which <hi>Gowry</hi> ſtops, ſincking the points of his <hi>weapons;</hi> when ſuddainly <hi>Herries</hi> ſtrickes at him, with a hunting <hi>fawchion.</hi> And <hi>Ramſey</hi> having his Hawke on his fiſt, caſts her off, and ſteps into <hi>Gowry,</hi> and <hi>ſtabs</hi> him to the <hi>heart;</hi> and forthwith, more <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> came up.</p>
            <p>And the truth, very notorious, then, to every eye and eare-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not a few.</p>
            <p>There remained but one <hi>young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> ſonne of that Houſe, who though a <hi>childe,</hi> was from that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169833:11"/>time <hi>Impriſoned,</hi> by Act of their <hi>Parliament.</hi> And ſo continued afterwards, here in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> until that King's death; and the grace of the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> reſtored him to liberty; with a <hi>ſmall penſion, which kept him</hi> like a Gentleman, to theſe times. But now failing, he walks the ſtreets, poore, but well experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, alſo, in <hi>Chimicall Phyſick,</hi> and in other parts of Learning.</p>
            <p>Not long after this Conſpiracy, <hi>Herries</hi> dies well rewarded. <hi>John Ramſey</hi> hath the Honor of <hi>Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> with an additional bearing to his Cote of Armes, <hi>A Hand hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth a Dagger, reverſed proper, piercing a bloudy heart, The point crowned Empcriall;</hi> with this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, <hi>Haec Dextra Vindex Principis &amp; Patriae.</hi> Afterward he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Lord <hi>Haddington,</hi> and <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Holderneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> beſtowes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169833:12"/>on him this Character, <hi>A very good Gentleman by nature, but (in this Story) a Lier by practiſe:
<note place="margin">Pamp. 9.</note> for which all theſe favours were too little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Erskin</hi> was after. wards created <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Kelly, Knight</hi> of the <hi>Garter, Captain</hi> of the King's <hi>Guard,</hi> and <hi>Groome</hi> of the Stoole. And the <hi>Fellow,</hi> deſigned for the Murtherer, had a large <hi>Penſion</hi> confirm'd, by <hi>Act</hi> of their Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And all theſe men <hi>(but Herries)</hi> were living, with other witneſſes at King <hi>JAME'S</hi> journy, when he went from hence to viſit <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and met together by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at the ſame Houſe, with <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony;</hi> and all of them with a number of <hi>Courtiers,</hi> aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame <hi>Roome,</hi> the bloud yet remaining, where the King rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Story;</hi> and <hi>confirmed</hi> by them. And afterwards kneeling
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169833:12"/>down, with tears of Contrition for his <hi>Sinnes</hi> to God, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for this <hi>Mercy;</hi> uſing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pious Ejaculations, embraced all theſe <hi>Actors</hi> in the former <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy;</hi> when the poor <hi>fellow,</hi> alſo kiſt the King's hand.</p>
            <p>Theſe circumſtances gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion then, that this whole ſtory was freſhly revived, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of the whole <hi>Countrey,</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers. And in eſpeciall, unto the very Reverend Biſhop, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly borne, <hi>James Mountegue,</hi> then preſent; to whom the King ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf, in this <hi>Relation,</hi> and from whoſe <hi>Mouth,</hi> I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved theſe <hi>particulars,</hi> at his return into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much we have by word of mouth: ſomewhat I ſhall add out of writings for more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>This Treaſon was attempted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169833:13"/>the 4. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1600. And though there followed ſundry Suſpitions and Examination of ſeveral other Perſons ſuppoſed <hi>Abbetters</hi> &amp; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers;</hi> yet it lay undiſcovered, <hi>tanquamè poſtliminio</hi> untill 8. years after, by the circumſpection principally of the Earle of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar,</hi> a man of as great wiſdome as thoſe times and that Kingdome could boaſt of. Upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one <hi>George Sprot,</hi> Notary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick of <hi>Ayemouth</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi> From ſome words which at firſt he ſparingly or <hi>unawares expreſſed,</hi> and alſo by ſome papers, which were found in his Houſe; whereof being examin'd, with a little adoe he confeſſed, and was condemned and executed at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> the 12. of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Relation</hi> I conceive not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but in my hands to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and written by that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gentleman Sir <hi>William Hart,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169833:13"/>then Lord <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Principall</hi> in all the Acts of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature herein.</p>
            <p>And firſt <hi>George Sprot</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, That he knew perfectly that <hi>Robert Logane</hi> late of <hi>Reſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig,</hi> was privy and upon <hi>foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of <hi>John</hi> late Earl of <hi>Gowrie's</hi> Treaſonable Conſpiracy: That he knew, there were divers Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters interchanged betwixt them, anent their Treaſonable put poſe <hi>July</hi> 1600. which Letters <hi>James Bour,</hi> called <hi>Laird Bour, Servitor</hi> to <hi>Reſtalrig</hi> (imployed betwixt <hi>them,</hi> and privy to all that arrand) had in keeping, and ſhewed the ſame to <hi>Sprot</hi> in <hi>Fast-Caſtle.</hi> That <hi>Sprot</hi> was preſent, when <hi>Bour,</hi> after 5. daies abſence, returned with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers by letter from <hi>Gowry,</hi> and ſtaid all night with <hi>Restalrig</hi> at his houſe <hi>Gunueſgreen,</hi> &amp; rode the next morne to <hi>Lothiane,</hi> where he ſtaid ſix daies, then to <hi>Faſt-Caſtle,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169833:14"/>where he abode a ſhort ſpace.</p>
            <p>That he ſaw and heard <hi>Restal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig</hi> read theſe letters, which <hi>Bour</hi> brought back from <hi>Gowry,</hi> and all their Conference there anent. And that <hi>Bour</hi> ſaid, <hi>Sir,</hi> if you think to get <hi>Commodity</hi> by this dealing, lay your hand on your heart: and that <hi>Reſtalrig</hi> anſwered, though he ſhould loſe all in the world; yet he would paſſe through with <hi>Gowry:</hi> for that matter would as well content him as the <hi>Kingdome.</hi> To whom <hi>Bour</hi> ſaid, you may do as you pleaſe <hi>Sir;</hi> but it is not my Councell that you ſhould be ſo ſuddain in that other matter. But for the Condition of <hi>Darlton,</hi> I would like very well of it. To this <hi>Reſtalrig</hi> anſwered, content your ſelf, I am not at my <hi>wits end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Sprot</hi> himſelf entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conference with <hi>Bour,</hi> demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was to be done between
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169833:14"/>the Earle and the Laird? <hi>Bour</hi> anſwered, that he beleeved, that the Laird would get <hi>Darlton</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gold or ſilver: but he fear'd it would be deerer to him.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Sprot</hi> inquiring further, how that ſhould be <hi>done? Bour</hi> ſaid they have another pie in hand then buying and ſelling of land: But prayed <hi>Sprot</hi> for God's ſake, that he would let be, and not be troubled with the Lairds buſineſs: for he <hi>fear'd,</hi> that within few daies the Laird would be landleſſe and liveleſſe.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Sprot</hi> being demanded af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, if all theſe <hi>Confeſſions</hi> were true, as he would anſwer upon the ſalvation of his <hi>ſoul,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his death was neer approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? <hi>Sprot</hi> ſaid,</p>
            <p>That he had no deſire to live, and had care only of cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Conſcience in the truth. And that all the former points
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169833:15"/>and circumſtances were true, with the depoſitions made by him the 5. of <hi>July</hi> laſt, and the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion made by him ſince, as he hoped to be ſaved, and which he would ſeale with his bloud.</p>
            <p>And further being depoſed; where was now the letter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalrig</hi> to <hi>Gowry?</hi> He anſwered, That he had this letter amongſt other of <hi>Reſtalrig's</hi> papers which <hi>Bour</hi> had in keeping, and which <hi>Sprot</hi> copied out, and that he left the principall letter in his Cheſt amongſt his writings when he was taken and brought away, and that it is cloſed and folded in a ſheet of paper.</p>
            <p>Theſe depoſitions made by <hi>George Sprot</hi> the to of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1608. and <hi>others</hi> before (being all inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his Indictment following, to which for brevity I ſhall remit the Reader) and written by <hi>James <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rimroſe, Clerk</hi> of the King's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169833:15"/>and ſubſcribed <hi>Georgè Sprot.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Preſent</head>
               <p>Earl of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Earl <hi>Lothiane,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> Lord <hi>Schone,</hi> Lord <hi>Hallo-rod-houſe,</hi> Lord <hi>Blautire,</hi> Sir <hi>William Hart</hi> Lord Juſtice, Mr. <hi>John Hall,</hi> Mr. <hi>Patrick Gahoway,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter Hewet,</hi> Miniſters of <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> and ſubſcribed with all their hands.</p>
               <p>The next day 11. of <hi>Auguſt, Sprot</hi> was re-examined, and to him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the aſſurance of his death, and was advis'd not to abuſe his Conſcience to witneſſe untruths, and upon the Innocency of the dead or living. To which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, That being reſolved to die, and as he wiſhes to be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipant of <hi>Heaven,</hi> upon the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or damnation of his Soul, that all that he had depoſed were true in every point and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and no untruth in them.</p>
               <p>The next day being the 12. of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169833:16"/>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1608. <hi>Sprot</hi> was preſented in Judgement upon <hi>Pannell</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Talboth</hi> of <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> before <hi>Sir</hi> William Hart, <hi>Knight Lord Juſtice of</hi> Scotland <hi>aſſisted with theſe Perſons, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> Earle of <hi>Dunferling,</hi> Lord Chancelour. <hi>George, Earle</hi> of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Lord Treaſurer. <hi>John,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Glaſcoe. David,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe. Gawen,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Galloway. Andrew,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Brechine. David, Earl</hi> of <hi>Craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. Mark, Earl</hi> of <hi>Lotharine. James, Lord Abernethie</hi> of <hi>Saltonne. James, Lord</hi> of <hi>Balmerinoth Senita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie. Walter, Lord Blautire. John, Lord Burley. Sir Richard Coburn, Knight. Maſter John Preston, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector Generall. Sir John Skewe, Knight, Regiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And he was declared, accuſed and purſued by Sir <hi>Thomas Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Knight, Advocate to the King, for his Highneſſe entries of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169833:16"/>Crimes contained in his Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whereof the tenure follows <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Sprot,</hi> Notary in <hi>Aye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> You are indicted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, foraſmuch as <hi>John</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Earle of <hi>Gowry,</hi> having moſt cruelly, deteſtably and treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conſpired in the moneth of <hi>July</hi> the year of God 1600. to murther our deere and moſt gracious Soveraigne the King's moſt excellent Majeſty. And having imparted that diveliſh purpoſe to <hi>Robert Logaine</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalrig,</hi> who allowed of the ſame, and moſt willingly and readily undertook to be partaker thereof. The ſame comming to your knowledge, at the times and in the <hi>manner</hi> particularly after ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified. You moſt unnaturally, maliciouſly and treaſonably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed the ſame, and was art and part thereof in manner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169833:17"/>And firſt, In the ſaid moneth of <hi>July</hi> 1600. after you had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and known, that divers let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters &amp; meſſages had paſt betwixt the ſaid <hi>John</hi> ſomtimes Earl of <hi>Gowry</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Robert Logane</hi> of <hi>Restalrig,</hi> you being in the houſe of <hi>Faſt-Caſtle,</hi> you ſaw and read a letter written by the ſaid <hi>Reſtalrig</hi> with his own hand to the ſaid Earle of <hi>Gowry.</hi> viz.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp;c. At the receipt of your letter I am ſo confuted, that I can neither utter my joy, nor find my ſelfe ſufficiently able to requite your Lordſhip with due thanks. And perſwade your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> in that matter I ſhall be as forward for your honour as if it were my own cauſe. And I think there is no Chriſtian, that would not be content to revenge, that <hi>Machiavilian Maſſacring</hi> of our deer Friends: yea howbeit it ſhould be to venture and hazard
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169833:17"/>life, lands and all things elſe. My heart can bind me to take part in that matter, as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhall find proof thereof. But one thing would be done; namely, that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhould be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and earneſt with your <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that he be not raſh in any ſpeeches touching the purpoſe of <hi>Padua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And a <hi>certain ſpace</hi> after the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the aforeſaid <hi>Treaſon,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Robert Logane</hi> having deſired the <hi>Laird</hi> of <hi>Bour</hi> to deliver to <hi>him</hi> the ſaid <hi>letter</hi> or elſe to burn it; and <hi>Bour</hi> having given to you all tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets and letters, which he then had either concerning <hi>Reſtalrig</hi> or others to ſee the ſame, becauſe he could not reade himſelf, you abſtracted the above-written let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and retained the ſame in your own hands, and divers times read it, containing further, to wit,</p>
               <p>My <hi>Lord</hi> you may eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169833:18"/>that ſuch a purpoſe as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> intendeth, can not be done raſhly, but with delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I think for my ſelf, that it were moſt meet, to have the men your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſpake of, ready in a <hi>bote</hi> or <hi>bark,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe them as if they were taking paſtime on the Sea in ſuch faire <hi>Summer-time.</hi> And if your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> could think good, either your ſelf to come to my houſe <hi>Faſt-caſtle</hi> by ſea, or to ſend your <hi>Brother;</hi> I ſhould have the <hi>houſe</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quiet, and well provided after your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> advertiſement. And no others ſhall have acceſſe to haunt the place, during your being here. And if your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> doubt of ſafe landing, I ſhall provide all ſuch neceſſaries, as may ſerve for your arrival, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a flight-ſhot of the houſe. And perſwade your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> you ſhall be as ſure and quiet here, while
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169833:18"/>we have ſetled our <hi>Plot,</hi> as if you were in your own <hi>Chamber.</hi> For I truſt, and am aſſured, we ſhall have word within few daies from them your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> knowes of. For I have care to ſee what ſhips come home by. Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> knows, I have kept the Lord <hi>Both<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> quietly in this houſe in his greateſt extremity, in ſpite of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Councell.</hi> I hope if all things come to paſs (as I truſt they ſhall) to have both your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> &amp; his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> at a good <hi>Dinner</hi> ere I dy. <hi>Haec jocoſe.</hi> To animate your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> I doubt not but all things will be well: and I am reſolved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhall not doubt of any thing, on my part: Peril of life, lands, honor and goods; yea, the hazard of hell ſhall not affray me from that; yea, though the <hi>Scaffold</hi> were already ſet up. The ſooner the <hi>Matter</hi> were done, it were the better. For the King's
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169833:19"/>
                  <hi>Buck-hunting</hi> will be ſhortly, and I hope it will prepare ſome dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier cheer for us to live the next year. I remember well my <hi>Lord,</hi> that <hi>merry ſport</hi> which your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Brother</hi> told me, of a <hi>Noble-Man</hi> at <hi>Padua:</hi> for I think that a <hi>Paraſceve</hi> to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> think nothing that I commit the ſecret hereof to this bearer: for I dare not onely ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture my life, lands, honour, and all I have elſe on his credit; but I durſt hazard my ſoule in his keeping: I am ſo perſwaded of his fidelity. And I trow (as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> may ask <hi>him</hi> if it be <hi>true</hi>) he would go to <hi>Hell-gates</hi> for me, and he is not beguiled of my part to him. And therefore I doubt not, but this will perſwade your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> to give him truſt in this matter as to my ſelf. But I pray you direct him home again with all ſpeed poſſible; and give
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169833:19"/>him ſtrait command, that he take not a winck ſleep, till he ſee me again after he comes from you. And as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> deſireth in your letter to me, either rive or burn this letter, or ſend it back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with the bearer: for ſo is the faſhion I grant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Restalrig.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which letter writ every word with the ſaid <hi>Robert Logane</hi>'s own hand, was alſo ſo ſubſcribed with this word, <hi>Reſtalrig.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit by the contents of the aforeſaid letter, you know per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the truth of the ſaid moſt treaſonable conſpiracy, and the ſaid <hi>Logane</hi> his foreknowledge, allowance and guilt thereof, like as you were aſſured of the ſame by his receiving divers letters ſent by <hi>Gowry</hi> to him, and by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning letters to <hi>Gowry</hi> for the ſame purpoſe, and by ſundry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169833:20"/>ferences betwixt <hi>Logane</hi> and <hi>Bour,</hi> in <hi>your</hi> preſence and hearing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſaid <hi>Treaſon,</hi> as well in <hi>July</hi> preceding the attempt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as at divers other times ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereafter: as likewiſe by <hi>Bour</hi> his revealing thereof to you; who was upon the knowledge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of the <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as ordinary Meſſenger by <hi>Logane</hi> to <hi>Gowry;</hi> whereby your knowledge, concealing and guilt of the ſame was undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for further manifeſtation thereof, about <hi>July</hi> 1602. the ſaid <hi>Logane</hi> ſhewed unto you, that <hi>Bour</hi> had told him, that he had been ſomewhat raſh, to let you ſee a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which came from <hi>Gowry</hi> to <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gane,</hi> who then urged you to tell what <hi>you</hi> underſtood by the <hi>ſame.</hi> To whom you anſwered, That you took the meaning thereof to be, that he had been upon the <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:169833:20"/>and purpoſe of <hi>Gowrie's</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy: And that he anſwered you, what e're he had done, the worſt was his own: But if you would ſwear to him, that you ſhould never reveale any thing of that matter to any perſon, it ſhould be the beſt ſight that ever you ſaw. And in token of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recompence, he gave you twelve pounds of Silver. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, albeit you know per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly the whole practiſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of all the ſaid <hi>Treaſon,</hi> from the beginning to the end; as alſo by your Conference with <hi>Bour</hi> and <hi>Logane,</hi> during all the daies of their lives, who lived till the year 1606. or therabouts: and ſo by the ſpace of 6. years you concealed the ſame, and ſo you was and is art and part of the ſaid Treaſon, and of the concealing, and ſo you ought to ſuffer under the pain of <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> To the token, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169833:21"/>you have not only by your depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions ſubſcribed by you, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly made in preſence of many of the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Majestie's Privy Councell,</hi> and the Miniſters of the <hi>Borough</hi> of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> of the dates of the 5.15. and 16. daies of <hi>July</hi> laſt paſt, and 10. and 11. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> inſtant, confeſſed every head, point and article of the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboveſaid, but alſo by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other depoſitions ſubſcribed by you; you have ratifyed the ſame, and ſworn conſtantly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide thereat, and to ſeal the ſame with your bloud, Which Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being read openly, before <hi>Sprot</hi> was put to the knowledge of Inqueſt, he confeſs'd the ſame and every point to be true; And therefore the Indictment was put to the Inqueſt of the honeſt, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and diſcreet Perſons, that is to ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Trumball</hi> of <hi>Ardre. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169833:21"/>Fiſher</hi> Merchant and Burgeſſe of <hi>Edenburgh, Rob. Short</hi> there, <hi>Ed. Johnſtone</hi> Merchant Burgeſs there, <hi>Harb. Maxwel</hi> of <hi>Cavens, Ja. Tennent</hi> of <hi>Linchouſe, Wil. Trumbill</hi> Burg, of <hi>Edenburgh, Geor. Brown</hi> in <hi>Gorgy Mill, Joh. Hucheſon</hi> and <hi>John Lewes</hi> Merch. Burg. of <hi>Edenburgh, Ja. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mervill,</hi> &amp; <hi>Wil. Swinton</hi> of the ſame, <hi>John Cruniſon</hi> of <hi>Dirlton, Th. Smith</hi> &amp; <hi>John Cowtis</hi> Burg. of <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Inquest</hi> ſworn and admitted, and reading over the ſame Indictment again in his and their preſence, the ſaid <hi>George Sprot</hi> confeſſed the <hi>ſame</hi> to be <hi>true.</hi> Whereupon the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Hamilton,</hi> his Majeſties Advocate, aſked act and Inſtrument; and therefore the <hi>Inqueſt</hi> removed to the <hi>Inqueſt-Houſe,</hi> and elected <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Maxwell</hi> to be their <hi>Chancelour</hi> or <hi>Foreman.</hi> And after mature deliberation, they all re-entred againe in Court, where the ſaid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169833:22"/>
                  <hi>Foreman</hi> declared the ſaid <hi>George Sprot</hi> to be guilty, filed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Part</hi> of the ſaid Treaſon; for which cauſe the ſaid Juſtice by the mouth of the Demſter of Court, by ſentence and Doom ordained, the ſaid <hi>George Sprot</hi> to be taken to the <hi>Market. Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and there to be hanged upon a <hi>Gibbet</hi> till he be dead, and thereafter his head to be ſtricken off, and his <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> to be quartered and demeaned as a Traytor, and his head to be ſet up upon a prick of <hi>Iron</hi> upon the higheſt part of the <hi>Talboth</hi> of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> where the <hi>Traytor Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> and other <hi>Conſpiratours</hi> heads ſtand, and his lands and goods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited and eſcheat to our <hi>Soveraign Lord</hi> the <hi>King</hi>'s uſe.</p>
               <q>Extractum de Libro Actorum Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jornalis S. D. N. Regis per me D. Johannem Coburne de Ormeston Milifem, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169833:22"/>Inſtitiarii ejuſdem gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem. Sub meis ſigno &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptione manualibus.</q>
               <p>And ſo was <hi>George Sprot</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to a private houſe, remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his <hi>Meditations;</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards conferred with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, confeſſing all aforeſaid with extreame humiliation and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Afterwards ganging up the ladder, with his hands looſe and untyed, he was again put in mind of the truth of his <hi>Confeſſions.</hi> He for the greater aſſurance thereof, perform'd an act marvelous; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing by God's aſſiſtance to give them an evident <hi>Token</hi> before the yielding up of his <hi>Spirit;</hi> which was, when he had <hi>hung</hi> a very <hi>good</hi> while, he left up both his hands a good height, and clapped them together three ſeverall times, to the wonder of thouſand Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and ſo dyed.</p>
               <p>For more <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169833:23"/>afore Narration, there was preſent <hi>George Abbot,</hi> then Doctor in <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> after <hi>Arch-Riſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who was preſent both at his <hi>Examination</hi> &amp; <hi>Execution,</hi> &amp; hath made the ſame writing and obſervance even al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>verbatim,</hi> as all the afore ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Relation intends; which I can produce alſo.</p>
               <p>And more one—Dr. of <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> preſent alſo, ſaies as much; which no doubt is ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to all reaſonable Men, that there was ſuch a Conſpiracy and not fained.
<note place="margin">Earle of Eſſex his Treaſon.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And now we come to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Earl of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Love</hi> of whoſe memory, was but of ſuch whom he formerly <hi>caught,</hi> by his affected <hi>Popularity;</hi> or of others, that followed his <hi>Treaſonable</hi> practiſes, which were groſſe enough to be <hi>ſore appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended,</hi> by every faithful <hi>Subject,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169833:23"/>eſpecially, being proſecuted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſon</hi> of that glorious <hi>Sunne,</hi> his obliging <hi>Miſtreſſe,
<note place="margin">Pamp. 10</note> whom</hi> a little before, our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorates with much <hi>Paſſion,</hi> till now, that he comes to <hi>Ireaſon;</hi> a <hi>ſmall fault,</hi> belike, and <hi>pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> For he ſaith, <hi>that King</hi> James <hi>hated Sir</hi> Robert Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill: <hi>it ſeemes,</hi> for but <hi>proſecuting amongst other Councelours and Peers a Traytor's death.</hi> Intimating no doubt the King's impatient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to inherit theſe <hi>Crownes</hi> by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Treaſon.</hi> But he ſpares no <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives</hi> againſt any of worth or honor, that comes in his way.</p>
               <p>This Earle was eldeſt Sonne to <hi>Walter Devoreux,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Robert E. of Eſſex.</note> (of a <hi>Norman</hi> family) <hi>Viſcount Hereford,</hi> and <hi>Bowrchier;</hi> Lord <hi>Eerrers</hi> of <hi>Chart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley:</hi> and by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> created Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and Ewe; <hi>Anno</hi> 1572. and Knight of the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169833:24"/>
               <p>He was ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> Lord <hi>Marſhall</hi> againſt the <hi>Rebells;</hi> and as if but ſent of an <hi>arrand,</hi> he preſently falls ſick, and dies at <hi>Dublin,</hi> 1576. His body brought over, and intomb'd at <hi>Carmarthen</hi> in <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Robert</hi> ſucceeded his Father's <hi>Honours;</hi> and was looked upon in <hi>Court,</hi> by all with <hi>pitty,</hi> through the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of his Father: But by the Queen with great affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whome ſhe advanced (his fortunes being lowe), with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gifts of grace and bounty. At his <hi>Arraignment,</hi> accounted to the Lord <hi>Treaſurer Dorſet</hi> to be 300000. l. ſterling, in pure <hi>gift</hi> for his only uſe; beſides the <hi>fees</hi> of his offices and the diſpoſition of the treaſurein his <hi>Armies.</hi> Of all which he ſoon became a bold <hi>ingroſſer</hi> both of <hi>fame</hi> and <hi>favour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt in <hi>Anno</hi> 1585. he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaves Knighthood. In 1588.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169833:24"/>Knight of the <hi>Garter.</hi> In 1589. he had command in chief; in an Expedition into <hi>Portingal</hi> againſt <hi>Lisbone.</hi> In 1595. ſworn <hi>Counce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> of <hi>State.</hi> In 1596. he was ſent with a <hi>Navy</hi> to the Iſle <hi>Cadiz</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> and preſently after made Lord <hi>Marſhall</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> In 1597. he commanded in another Fleet, to the Iſlands <hi>Sercera's;</hi> his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries</hi> who ſtood in <hi>Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with him for fame, were, Sir <hi>Charles Blunt,</hi> afterwards <hi>Earle</hi> of of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and <hi>Generall Norris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Blunt late E. of Dev.</note> his neer friends; and yet whom he envied, the laſt to his ruine; <hi>Men,</hi> of greater merit and truer value. And after the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Norris;</hi> He takes upon him the <hi>Expedition</hi> into <hi>Ireland;</hi> the place of <hi>Exerciſe</hi> for the <hi>beſt</hi> of the <hi>Militia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And who durſt oppoſe <hi>him?</hi> Though the <hi>Queen</hi> had an eye of favour upon <hi>Blunt,</hi> often <hi>ſaying,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169833:25"/>That <hi>She</hi> preſaged him, the <hi>Man,</hi> to end <hi>Her</hi> cares in that <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And <hi>She</hi> was a true <hi>Propheteſſe,</hi> though not in <hi>Her</hi> time, but in <hi>Her Succeſſor, King James.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Blunt</hi> was a <hi>Gallant Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> and learned, on whom <hi>She</hi> beſtowed a <hi>Jewell</hi> for his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour at a <hi>Tilting,</hi> which he wore after, tackt with a <hi>Scarlet Riband,</hi> upon his <hi>Arme;</hi> and for no other cauſe, <hi>Eſſex</hi> muſt needs fight with him, and was runne through the <hi>Arme,</hi> for his labour.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Eſſex</hi> got <hi>Imployments</hi> from them all; offering the Service evermore, at leſſe charge of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Money,</hi> then others his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And over he goes,
<note place="margin">Deputy of Ireland and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> 
                  <hi>Deputy</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Generall</hi> of all the forces there: with <hi>Commiſſion</hi> ſtrickt enough, to <hi>imbound</hi> his <hi>Popularity</hi> with the Souldiery, and his own <hi>family,</hi> which followed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169833:25"/>him in <hi>Troops,</hi> either to devour or undo him.</p>
               <p>No ſooner landed, but ere he drew ſword on the <hi>Enemy,</hi> he dubbs <hi>Knighthood</hi> upon ſeven <hi>Gentlemen, Volunteers;</hi> which honour, he had very laviſhly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed at <hi>Cadiz;</hi> and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſoundly chidden by the <hi>Queen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now reſtrained by his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> with much a do, unleſſe to <hi>Men</hi> of known <hi>Merit,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> after <hi>Battaile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this firſt Act, the <hi>Queene ſwore</hi> he began his <hi>Rant:</hi> Of which he had preſent Intelligence from his deereſt Friend and Uncle, Sir <hi>Francis Knowls,</hi> a <hi>Councelor</hi> of <hi>State,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sr. Francis Knowles his Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</note> and <hi>Controwler</hi> of <hi>Her Houſhold,</hi> and after <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Banbury:</hi> Who ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his adviſe and Councel at all times. And between them there paſſed <hi>Intelligence,</hi> with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>diſpatch;</hi> whoſe letters and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169833:26"/>papers, <hi>Principall</hi> from <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Copies</hi> to <hi>him</hi> I have ſeen; by which there appears, even from the beginning of that <hi>Imployment,</hi> a very plaine and Intentional <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> to make himſelf <hi>Master</hi> of his own <hi>Ambition,</hi> and by this way and meanes to <hi>effect it; grounding</hi> all <hi>his diſcontents</hi> and <hi>diſlikes,</hi> that the <hi>Queens eare</hi> was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to his <hi>Enemies</hi> at Court. And therefore it behooved him, to <hi>guard</hi> himſelf; which he reſolv'd to do, by help of his <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>fate;</hi> And indeed having fallen into <hi>remarkeable offences,</hi> together with the <hi>Treaties</hi> with <hi>Tyrone</hi> the <hi>Arch-Rebell,</hi> without Order from <hi>England,</hi> and without acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> with <hi>whoſe</hi> adviſe <hi>he was</hi> limitted to act.</p>
               <p>'Tis true,
<note place="margin">Treats with Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone.</note> he advanced againſt the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and ſoon accepts an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation</hi> to a <hi>Treaty</hi> accompanied with his <hi>Councell of Warre.</hi> But
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169833:26"/>comming to the <hi>brinck</hi> of a <hi>River;</hi> the place aſſigned, he plunges his <hi>Horſe</hi> to the <hi>Midde ſtream,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; and there meets him <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone</hi> on <hi>Horſeback;</hi> where their private diſcourſe gave ſufficient <hi>Caution,</hi> to all that looked on a-loof-off, that <hi>Eſſex</hi> meant no fair play for his <hi>Miſtreſſe.</hi> For which fact, and no blow ſtroock in all this time, <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Money</hi> waſted; He was ſoundly blamed by the <hi>Councell</hi> at home; and no more letters from the <hi>Queens own hand,</hi> which he uſually received afore.</p>
               <p>In great <hi>choler,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Returns home.</note> as to <hi>Diſpute</hi> or <hi>Revenge;</hi> and without leave from hence, he leaves his <hi>Command</hi> to a <hi>Lieutenant;</hi> and comes over with a hundred <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> his beſt <hi>Confidents;</hi> haſtens to <hi>Court,</hi> ere it was known to any, but to his deer <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> he writes, <hi>Deer <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, Receiving your laſt, at my entring on Ship-board, Ireturn
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169833:27"/>the accounts thereof, at my Landing; being reſolved with all ſpeed, (and your Silence) to appear, in the face of my Enemies; not truſting afarre off to my own Innocency, or to the Queens favour, with whom they have got ſo much power &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At ſight of him, with amaze to the <hi>Queen, She</hi> ſwore, <hi>God's death</hi> my <hi>Lord,</hi> what do you here? <hi>Your</hi> preſence is moſt <hi>unwelcome,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Tyrone's head</hi> in your <hi>Portman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</hi> But he, falling more to a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> then any <hi>Excuſe: She,</hi> in <hi>diſdaine to be taught, but what She pleaſed to do: Bid him begone, his bootes ſtunck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo was he preſently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<note place="margin">is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted &amp; cenſured.</note> and <hi>committed</hi> to the <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury to Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth;</hi> where not long after, he was convented before a <hi>Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee</hi> of the <hi>Councel, and Correctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, not ad deſtructionem.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> very gracious, hoping his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169833:27"/>offences might diſcerne favour. for according to his <hi>Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then,</hi> and the <hi>merit</hi> of his <hi>cauſe.</hi> I have ſeen his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles papers, breviates,</hi> (who was one of his <hi>Judges</hi>) intended as his <hi>Cenſure, to condemnation,</hi> and ſo fitted for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tryall.</hi> But the day before, they had other <hi>direction</hi> from the <hi>Queen, ſaying, he was young enough to mend, and make amends for all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo their <hi>Cenſures,</hi> ſhew'd him his <hi>Errors,</hi> and left him to <hi>Her grace</hi> and <hi>mercy;</hi> only <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> him to his own <hi>Houſe,</hi> againſt Saint <hi>Clements.</hi> Not without dayly letters from <hi>Knowles;</hi> with advice to be rid of his <hi>ranting fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; Captaines</hi> and <hi>Sword-men</hi> of the <hi>Town flocking,</hi> and <hi>Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging</hi> him, to a <hi>Revenge</hi> on his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was not long that he could contain; <hi>Saying,
<note place="margin">His rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</note> he was engaged to go on.</hi> And on a Sunday morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169833:28"/>the <hi>Councell ſat; (which was uſuall, untill the late Arch-Biſhop Lawd in honour of the Morning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, altered that courſe, to the Afternoon.</hi> Then the firſt flame brake out.</p>
               <p>To him,
<note place="margin">Impriſons the Clerk of the Councell,</note> they ſent their <hi>Clerke</hi> of the <hi>Councell,</hi> to know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> of the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo many <hi>weaponed Men</hi> at his houſe; But the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> not returning, being kept <hi>Priſoner,</hi> the chiefeſt <hi>Councelours</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Queen,</hi> came to him; and no ſooner entered <hi>Eſſex houſe,</hi> but the <hi>Gates</hi> were clapp'd too, all their <hi>Train</hi> kept out, the <hi>Court-yard full of Gallants.</hi> Some cryed <hi>kill them; Impriſon them;
<note place="margin">and the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> To the Court; ſeiſe the Queen, and be our own Carvers. Eſſex</hi> comes down with all reverence, uſhers them up, reſolving to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them Priſoners,</hi> and <hi>pledges</hi> for his <hi>Succeſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169833:28"/>
               <p>Indeed in this hurly burly of advice he took the worſt. For leaving them in ſafety with <hi>Sir Ferdinando Gorges;</hi> He with the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Southampton,</hi> in one boat; and ſome others in other boats, took water at his <hi>Garden ſtaires;</hi> and landing neer the <hi>Bridge,</hi> went on foot, up the ſtreets, with ſuch <hi>stragling company</hi> as came in their way; To <hi>whom he proteſted, that the Queen ſhould have been murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his, and other good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors lives, in perill, by enemies of the State, that forced a power from the Queene, to the emiment deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kingdome.</hi> Theſe <hi>ſpeeches</hi> with their <hi>ſwords drawne,</hi> took little effect with the <hi>people,</hi> who came running out of the <hi>Churches,</hi> being <hi>Sermon-time;</hi> without wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, or any offenſable aſſiſtance, contrary to his <hi>expectation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on he goes to <hi>Sir Thomas Smith's,</hi> where he kept his <hi>Shreeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169833:29"/>neere <hi>Fan-church,</hi> his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding friend; by whoſe counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he hoped to worke with the <hi>Multitude.</hi> He being abſent, at <hi>Paul's Croſſe Sermon, Eſſex</hi> ſtaid no longer, then to ſhift his ſhirt; and ſo paſſed through <hi>Cheape-ſide</hi> to <hi>Paul's weſt-end;</hi> where he found his firſt <hi>oppoſition</hi> by ſome forces got together, by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the <hi>trained band.</hi> And after <hi>Proclametion,</hi> That <hi>Eſſex and Southampton were Traitors,</hi> &amp; all thoſe that followed their faction: Many dropping from the <hi>Crowd,</hi> there was little defence by his party, though ſome were killed; and <hi>himſelfe forſaken</hi> of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt. He retires back to <hi>Queen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hithe,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Eſſex-houſe</hi> by wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; where finding the <hi>Birds flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi> the <hi>Councellors</hi> releaſed, by their <hi>Keeper;</hi> who in hope of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, accompained them to the <hi>Queenes</hi> preſence; diſcovering
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169833:29"/>ſo much as he knew, concerning his <hi>Lord;</hi> who finding himſelfe too <hi>weake,</hi> to withſtand the <hi>force</hi> of a peece of <hi>Cannon,</hi> mounted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Church,</hi> to batter his <hi>Houſe; He</hi> and <hi>Southampton</hi> yeelded themſelves <hi>Priſoners</hi> to the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arraigned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</note> where being <hi>arraigned</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Southamton</hi> had <hi>repreeve,</hi> and after <hi>pardon;</hi> But <hi>Eſſex</hi> the reward of his merits, and <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in March</hi> 1601. upon the <hi>Inner Hill</hi> in the <hi>Tower;</hi> to the regret of <hi>None</hi> either wiſe or honeſt: <hi>Leaving behind him one onely Son, the laſt of his Line.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Cecill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cecils. Pamp. 10.</note> illuſtrate from the <hi>family</hi> of <hi>Cecils</hi> (who ſuffered perſecution in the times <hi>of Henry</hi> 8. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. and <hi>Queen Mary</hi>) he was knighted by <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> ſo ſoone as ſhe was ſetled in her <hi>Crowne,</hi> then <hi>Secretary</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of State.</hi> Afterwards crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Burligh.</hi> Then made
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169833:30"/>
                  <hi>Lord Treaſurer of England,</hi> and <hi>Knight</hi> of the <hi>Garter:</hi> and died <hi>Chauncellor</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Anno 1598. Intomb'd at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> leaving two <hi>Sons.</hi> The elder <hi>Thomas,</hi> was then <hi>Lord Preſident</hi> of the <hi>North;</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards created <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> by <hi>King James,</hi> and privy <hi>Councellor of State.</hi> He died Anno diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and honourable, whom the world could never tax with any taint.</p>
               <p>The other ſon <hi>Robert,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sr. Robert Cecill.</note> was the ſecond; But a true <hi>Inheriter</hi> of his <hi>Fathers wiſdome,</hi> and by <hi>him</hi> train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to future perfections, of a <hi>Judicious States-man:</hi> after his <hi>Knighthood,</hi> the firſt imployment from <hi>Court (for he was not at all bred out of it)</hi> ſent him <hi>Aſſiſtant</hi> with the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Darby Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> to the <hi>French King.</hi> At his returne, the <hi>Queen</hi> took him <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Secretary</hi> with Sir <hi>Fr. Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169833:30"/>after whoſe <hi>deceaſe,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>Paincipal,</hi> and ſo kept it to his death; <hi>Not relinquiſhing any Preferment, for the Addition of a Creater. A remarkeable Note; which few men of the Gowne can boast of.</hi> His <hi>Father</hi> liv'd to ſee him ſetled in theſe <hi>preferments,</hi> and after <hi>Master of the Wards</hi> and <hi>Liveries.</hi> Theſe he held to the <hi>Queenes death:</hi> Being in all Her time uſed amongſt the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>weight,</hi> as <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving great ſufficiencies from his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction who begat him.</hi> Thoſe <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> here in public, with perpetual Correſpondence by <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of his own into <hi>Scotland,</hi> might no doubt make him capable of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> with <hi>King James,</hi> who was to be adviſed by him, how to be received here of <hi>his people.</hi> Without any neceſſity, then, to make uſe of Sir <hi>George Hewmes or his Initiatiation afterwards, with any juggling trickes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp 13.</note> his <hi>merrits</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169833:31"/>appeared to the <hi>King,</hi> who not onely not <hi>diminiſhed</hi> his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former <hi>preferments;</hi> But often <hi>added</hi> to them, even to the day of his death.</p>
               <p>As firſt <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Eſſenden;</hi> then <hi>Viſcount Cranborne;</hi> after <hi>Earle of Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>Knight of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and laſtly <hi>Lord Treaſurer of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was a <hi>Councellor</hi> of ſingular merit. A very great <hi>diſcoverer</hi> of the late <hi>Queens</hi> enemies <hi>abroad,</hi> and of private <hi>Aſſinations</hi> at home: For which <hi>She</hi> valued him, and the <hi>Papists</hi> hated him; which they publiſhed by ſeveral <hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> (which I have ſeen,) and printed <hi>Libels;</hi> and that moſt peſtilent againſt his birth and honour, threatning to kill him, which himſelfe anſwered wiſely, learnedly and religiouſly, Extant in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Perduelles.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:169833:31"/>
               <p>Indeed, It behoved the <hi>King</hi> to beſtow upon him the waight of the <hi>Treaſurers Staffe.</hi> The <hi>Cofers</hi> then in ſome want; which the <hi>King</hi> was not likely ſoon to <hi>Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> but rather to <hi>increaſe</hi> in <hi>debt:</hi> having the addition of <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>children</hi> to boot. And being now come, with common opinion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Capacity, (by his additional Crownes</hi>) to <hi>reward his old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants;</hi> and to appear obliging unto <hi>new Ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The world wondering at the <hi>worth</hi> of this <hi>great Councellor,</hi> I know not upon what ſcore, our <hi>Pamphleter</hi> ſhould endeavour to <hi>ſcandal</hi> his <hi>memory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which he rancks into <hi>Numbers of ill Offices to his Nation;
<note place="margin">Pamp. 12.</note> as the burning of a whole cart-load of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Preſidents;</hi> which no man can be ſo <hi>ſottiſh</hi> as to <hi>beleeve,</hi> that knowes the ſtrict <hi>concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of thoſe <hi>Records</hi> by ſworne <hi>Officers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169833:32"/>
               <p>As for the <hi>Baronets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baronets.</note> It was the earneſt ſuite of two hundred prime <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of <hi>Birth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states</hi> to my knowledge; <hi>for I co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied the liſt before ever it came this Lord.</hi> And as true it is, That this <hi>Lord's Reception</hi> thereto, was in the ſame <hi>words</hi> which our <hi>Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> puts upon the <hi>King, That it would diſcontent the Gentry;</hi> to which themſelves replyed, <hi>Nay my Lord, It will rather ſatisfie them, in advance of Dignity, before others; who now, come behind thoſe Meaner Men,</hi> whom the <hi>King</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to <hi>Knight</hi> for his own honor, and ſome <hi>merits</hi> of <hi>theirs,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other <hi>Reward,</hi> or <hi>money</hi> to ſpare: and therein not much to blame, to <hi>oblige</hi> them that way.</p>
               <p>As for that <hi>ſuppoſed jugling,
<note place="margin">Pamp. 13.</note> which the Duke of Bullion ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover:</hi> As it was never known to wiſer men; So we may take it, a deviſe of his, who in theſe, as in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169833:32"/>other ſuch like, of his own, may truly merit that Character which he beſtowes before <hi>[On the good Gentleman.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I deſire pardon, if I ſpeake <hi>much</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> in the <hi>memory</hi> of this <hi>Noble Lord;</hi> being ſomewhat concerned, to ſpeak my owne knowledge.</p>
               <p>I know, that this <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Saleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> declining his health, with continuall <hi>labour</hi> for the good of this <hi>Nation,</hi> both in the former, and in this his <hi>Soveraign's Service;</hi> And am willing to give ſome <hi>light</hi> thereof, to ſuch as are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to read theſe particulars, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Account of his concernments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For firſt,
<note place="margin">Salisbury his ſervice to the State. Mannors, Lands.</note> he found the <hi>King's Mannors,</hi> and faireſt poſſeſſions, moſt <hi>unſurveyed,</hi> and uncertain, rather by <hi>report,</hi> then by <hi>Meaſure.</hi> Not more known, then by <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Rents;</hi> the <hi>Estate</hi> granted ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>by chance,</hi> then upon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169833:33"/>
               <p>The <hi>Custody-Lands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cuſtody-hands.</note> (antiently termed <hi>Crown-Lands</hi>) much <hi>char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> upon the <hi>Sheriffs;</hi> yearly <hi>diſcharged</hi> by annual <hi>penſions.</hi> A <hi>Revenue</hi> which ſeemed <hi>decayed,</hi> by deſcent of times, and worne out of all remembrance: theſe he evermore <hi>revived,</hi> by <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of <hi>Aſſerts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Woods,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Woods.</note> were more uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain then the reſt. No man knew the <hi>Copices, Number</hi> of <hi>acres, growth</hi> or <hi>value;</hi> nor of <hi>Timber-Trees,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Number</hi> or <hi>worth.</hi> So as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he might well find himſelf in a <hi>Wood,</hi> indeed. The <hi>Trees</hi> waſted without controwle, becauſe no <hi>Record</hi> kept thereof. Theſe he cauſed to be <hi>numbred, marked</hi> and <hi>valued,</hi> eaſily to be queſtioned, when thereafter <hi>miſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Copy-hold Lands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds.</note> where the arbitrary ſines ceaſed, by the diſcretion of the Stewards; and did ſeldome yeeld the Parſons
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169833:33"/>part; and that alſo vaniſh'd, in fees and charges. The State was then after like to raiſe of theſe Natures, the true values; and to receive equal benefit, with the reſt of the Subjects; if the Book had bin ſince obſerved, which <hi>he</hi> cauſed in print.</p>
               <p>And for the Copy-holders of Inheritance, who by many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, prove their fines certain; they did hereupon, offer for their freedome 20.30.40. and 50. years purchaſe, where they could ſhew probable Records, without ſine; to free themſelves. The Waſtes and Commons, were ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Titles;
<note place="margin">Waſtes &amp; Commons.</note> full of murmering and Commotion; which truly he never durſt offer to incloſe; Nor to urge the Tenants to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Suitors themſelves; with whom Commiſſioners were to be appointed, to compound for a part; and ſo he made a good Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for the reſt.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169833:34"/>
               <p>The Caſual fines,
<note place="margin">Caſual fines.</note> due to the King, out of the private poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (as other <hi>Lords</hi> have by their Courts of <hi>Leets,</hi> Court <hi>Barons</hi> and ſuch like) and out of publique of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, as the King was Parent of the Common-Wealth; unto whom belong'd <hi>&amp; praemium &amp; poena.</hi> Theſe being natures, left for the King's bounty, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended them alſo to Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, for a better Revenue, to be raiſed; being till his time ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly neglected and almoſt loſt.</p>
               <p>As for the extended Lands; where the <hi>Officers</hi> became indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Crown; and made it an Art, to have their Lands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, at eaſy rates; He cauſed the moſt of theſe to be ſurveyed; commended the Improvement to Commiſſioners, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Tenants to appear before them.</p>
               <p>The Improvements of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169833:34"/>he advanced from 86000. l. to 120000. l. and from that to 135000. l. by the year.</p>
               <p>He bargained, for the River<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water to be brought to <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">River wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> and ſo to the drieſt parts, which brought a great yearly value.</p>
               <p>He alwaies incouraged all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of <hi>Manufactures.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</note> Such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions as the Statutes admit and countenance. As home-making of <hi>Allome;</hi> Salt by the Sunne; Buſſes for fiſhing; Salt upon Salt, by new fires and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions; <hi>Copper</hi> and <hi>Coperas</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and of <hi>Steele;</hi> That the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at home, might be ſet on work; and the ſmall Treaſure of the Nation kept within.</p>
               <p>It concerned him as <hi>Secretary</hi> to have <hi>Intelligence</hi> from all parts of the World;
<note place="margin">Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with all Em baſſadours and Forreigne States; not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected at any hand; which he did
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169833:35"/>at his own coſt. So did all parts grow confident of ſuch a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celour. And ſo he kept Rules with the united Provinces whoſe Friendſhips he would ſay, much concerned this State.</p>
               <p>I may not forget his Chriſtian care,
<note place="margin">Ireland improved.</note> for poor <hi>Ireland;</hi> Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there, and tranſplantations of the Natives; to advance the Cuſtomes there, and to abate the charges of the Gariſons. And he did endeavour, and in manner did effect an univerſall courſe of Law and Juſtice, in the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and remote parts of that Nation.</p>
               <p>And now concerning the Court of Wards and Liveries;
<note place="margin">Wards &amp; Liveries.</note> By con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this State, all the lands of this Nation, are holden by two Tenures: By Soccage or by Knights Service. By the Plough to feed us; or by the Sword to defend us. And who ſo died,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169833:35"/>leaving an Heir within age, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do this ſervice, his Heir and Lands, fell both to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Soveraign. And this in antient time, was promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly carryed, in the Court of Chancery; until the middle time of <hi>Hon.</hi> the 8. when this Court of Wards, was firſt erected. Since which time the Maſters thereof, by favour of the Soveraign, did accuſtome (as a bounty of State) to grant unto Noble Men; the King's Servants and their owne followers, both the marriag of the body, and the leaſe of the Lands for a third peny, of their true worth.</p>
               <p>But in all humility, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip finding the eſtate in a Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade Conſumption, did with all obedience preſent his Patent, at the Kings feet: and ſo the whole benefit became the profit of the Crown.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:169833:36"/>
               <p>Thus, he wrought in the Mine of the State-affaires, and waſted his Carkaſſe with deſire, to have done better Service, in theſe his offices of <hi>Treaſurer, Secretary</hi> and <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>Wards:</hi> And yet theſe were ſufficient, juſt and true merits; Without Friends, Wit, or Wealth, to raiſe him ſo much, in his Maſter's eſteem: Or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ill offices done by him, to this Nation, as our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> will make us believe, in many abſurd parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p>And truly,
<note place="margin">Pam. 11.12.</note> his ſtudious labours in the State, brought him the ſooner to ſickneſſe, a Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Lungs; wherein he waſted ſome years, and at laſt, by adviſe for cure at the <hi>Bath;</hi> he took leave of the King, who came to viſit him at <hi>Salisbury-Houſe;</hi> and with tears, at his parting, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted to the Lords attending, his great loſſe of the wiſeſt <hi>Councelour</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169833:36"/>and beſt Servant, that any <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> could Paralel. Of whom one ſaies,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tu Pater &amp; Patriae Princeps, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia cujus Extulit immenſum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Populóſque Britannos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His time at the <hi>Bath</hi> was ſhort; being ſpent to extreamity, ere he came thither; and returning back by the way, he was taken out of his Litter, and put himſelf in his Coach, and died afterwards at St. <hi>Margarets,</hi> in the Houſe of that worthy Gentleman Mr. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1612. My Lord <hi>Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Cramborne,</hi> now Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Manton</hi> and many <hi>more Gentlemen</hi> of quality then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, whom I ſaw there: He was Imbalmed, and after Intomb'd, at his Princely <hi>Mannor</hi> of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 14.</note> A fairer Corps then any braſen face, that belies his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. His death was extreame
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169833:37"/>ſadneſſe to the King, and to all his friends, and others of worth and honour. For in ſpite of the <hi>Pamphleter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 14.</note> he will be valued, as he does confeſſe</p>
               <p>Never came a Better.</p>
               <p>The next we meet with is <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Henry Howard Earle of Northam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Illuſtrous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> of the <hi>Howards,</hi> were here more <hi>Eminent,</hi> then any other, that uſhered the King to his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall Crownes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Henry Howard</hi> was Brother unto <hi>Thomas Duke of Norfolke;</hi> who ſuffered <hi>for his attempt of marriage</hi> with the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Scots,</hi> whilſt ſhe was <hi>Priſoner</hi> here in <hi>England.</hi> Which might be ſome <hi>Motive</hi> to induce the <hi>King</hi> to conſider the advance of that <hi>family,</hi> though they were indued, with large <hi>poſſeſſions</hi> from their <hi>Anceſtors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> left two Sons <hi>Philip Earl of Arundell</hi> &amp; <hi>Thomas Howard
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169833:37"/>Earle of Suffolk</hi> afterwards <hi>Lord Treaſurer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry Howard</hi> their Uncle,
<note place="margin">Pamp. 15</note> was more wedded to his <hi>Book,</hi> then to the <hi>Bed:</hi> for he died a <hi>Bacheler;</hi> and <hi>ſo</hi> had the <hi>leſſe</hi> occaſion, <hi>to advance his fortune, by Court-flattery, or State-Imployment:</hi> nor indeed was he ever any <hi>Suitor</hi> for <hi>either.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was accounted both <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned;</hi> and therefore out of the Kings great affection to <hi>Letters,</hi> eſpecially when they are met in a <hi>Noble Perſon,</hi> he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, in his Creation of Baron of <hi>Marnhill</hi> and Earle of <hi>Southam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton;</hi> then <hi>Pryvy Councelor, Lord Privy Seale,</hi> and <hi>Lord Warden</hi> of the <hi>Cinque Ports,</hi> and Knight of the <hi>Garter.</hi> He had very <hi>plentifull</hi> for his ſingle life, and to ſpare for his friends.</p>
               <p>In his expence not over <hi>frugal;</hi> maintaining his <hi>Port,</hi> the moſt <hi>remarkeable (like the Ancient NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169833:38"/>MAN)</hi> in his <hi>family</hi> and <hi>Dependants;</hi> of any other <hi>Lord</hi> then, or ſince his time. He aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted his <hi>Nephew</hi> the <hi>Earl of Suffolk</hi> by his deſigning and large contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, to that excellent <hi>Fabrick Awdley-end.</hi> He built the <hi>Noble ſtructure</hi> at <hi>Charing-Croſſe,</hi> from, the Ground, <hi>Northampton Houſe</hi> and preſented it a New-years-gift to the <hi>Lord Walden, Suffolkes</hi> eld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Sonne, and now called <hi>Suffolk-Houſe:</hi> and yet left his other <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew,</hi> the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Arundell,</hi> the reſt of his eſtate; ſo to appear to the world, his <hi>equall diſtribution</hi> to ſuch <hi>even kinred.</hi> He was <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,</hi> and gave good teſtimony thereof in his life, built that <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Covent</hi> at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued it with <hi>Revenue</hi> for ever, for maintenance of decaied <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> a ſufficient number; and for <hi>women</hi> alſo conſiderable. He died in <hi>Anno</hi> 1613. full of years and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169833:38"/>
                  <hi>Honourable fame:</hi> though Our <hi>Pamphleter</hi> wil not know ſo <hi>much;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 16.</note> and yet no doubt muſt needs be <hi>Iutimate</hi> with his <hi>Perſon:</hi> for he tells us his <hi>thoughts;</hi> That he had aſſuredly promiſed to himſelf the <hi>Treaſurers ſtaff.</hi> Although we can produce this <hi>Lord's Letters,</hi> and other teſtimonies, imploying all <hi>his own</hi> and his <hi>Friends Intereſt,</hi> for that preferment, upon his <hi>Nephew Suffolke,</hi> and excuſing himſelf, of the burthen and weight of that <hi>Office,</hi> by his known <hi>Infirmity</hi> of <hi>Stone</hi> of the which he died.</p>
               <p>Indeed;
<note place="margin">James Hay Earle of Carlile. Pamp. 18.</note> It is no matter upon what <hi>Score,</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> gave his affection, to this <hi>Favorite James Hay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> were never very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, with <hi>Neighbour-Princes;</hi> what credit they had, came by the <hi>French,</hi> to keep ballance with <hi>England and them.</hi> The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning might then be hoped, when
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169833:39"/>their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with theſe <hi>Crownes,</hi> ſhould afford the meanes, to ſet them forth.</p>
               <p>And it was <hi>prudentiall</hi> in the King, to pick out one of his own to <hi>ſplendour</hi> that Nation, in our way of peace and Court-ſhip: Eſpecially when all was done at the Maſter's coſt. For <hi>Hay</hi> was poor, unleſſe what he got by his firſt Match, with the Lord <hi>Dennis heir,</hi> for by his laſt <hi>he</hi> had nothing; the great ſpirit of <hi>Pearcy</hi> Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> diſdaining the Marriage, and refuſed to afford <hi>a Groat, to a beggerly Scot, as he call'd him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now this Lord (for ſo was he ſoon made <hi>Lord Hay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His vaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> spences.</note> then <hi>Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Doncaſter,</hi> and <hi>Earl of Carlile</hi>) did moſt vainely prodigallize, what he often begg'd. And in truth, he had it granted for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe; to put down the <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh Courtier</hi> at that vanity.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169833:39"/>And which, both abroad and at home, was often paid for, by the <hi>King's Privy Purſe.</hi> As that feaſt at <hi>Eſſex-Houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 19.</note> and many his <hi>Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoes</hi> at <hi>Court</hi> (for he medled not with the <hi>Tilt-staff,</hi> as being no <hi>Sword-man</hi>) but in the other, and ſuch like, he never eſcaped, to act <hi>One part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe expences, fam'd him with little credit; how erche appears to our <hi>Pamphleters Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> who cries up,
<note place="margin">Pamp. 21.</note> the bounty of his <hi>Mind,</hi> beyond the <hi>Moon</hi> at leaſt; who in truth, was never <hi>good,</hi> to <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Embaſſies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies to Germany.</note> were not ſo <hi>weighty</hi> when he poſted ſo long through <hi>Germany,</hi> to find out the <hi>Emperor;</hi> who afforded him the <hi>Wild-Gooſe-Chaſe,</hi> as knowing his <hi>Arrand,</hi> before he came at him. Which in truth was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſo deſigned by the <hi>King;</hi> only to ſpend time, and to amuſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169833:40"/>mens <hi>expectations (who were wild after a Warre)</hi> to beget a Treaty, concerning the loſt <hi>Palatine.</hi> The effects wherof, (as the King wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propheſyed,) would produce <hi>diſtemper,</hi> through all <hi>Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> if not deſtructive to his <hi>Son in law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He went into <hi>France Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">France.</note> it was to treate with that King, in favour of the <hi>Hugenots (the Religion as they account it)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riſen to a <hi>Civill Warre,</hi> by management of the <hi>Duke d'Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hau, Count Sobeeze,</hi> and others; to a dangerous conſequence, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places, almoſt over <hi>France:</hi> which to allay, that King had raiſed a great Army; reſolving with countenance of his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to give end thereto: But <hi>King James,</hi> being invited by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral troubleſome <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> their <hi>Agents,</hi> to implore for their cauſe, and take upon him their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169833:40"/>protection, which he (a wiſe Prince in that) declined, yet not to neglect them; and the rather to ſatisfy ſome of our People, of the like <hi>Gang,</hi> medled thus farre to <hi>mediate</hi> by <hi>Embaſſy</hi> of <hi>Hay;</hi> who as in that of <hi>Germany,</hi> did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with effect, but went up to <hi>Montaban,</hi> and ſo come home again.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, he went into <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spaine.</note> with a <hi>meſſage</hi> to our Prince; with no <hi>more</hi> matter, then others that came after, to waite on him in that Courtſhip. For there as in other Kingdomes, his <hi>Scots va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> muſt alſo be blazon'd.</p>
               <p>And for his laſt <hi>Embaſſy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> about <hi>Our Match with that Daughter,</hi> and our <hi>Queen;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to France.</note> he came not into <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> till the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> was confirmed, and the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> concluded, by <hi>Embaſſy,</hi> only of the <hi>Earle of Holland;</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> put in afterwards, to <hi>dance</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:169833:41"/>out the <hi>Meaſures;</hi> His <hi>name,</hi> being uſed in the <hi>Proxie,</hi> for that <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> and at this time, the <hi>Earl of Holland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Earle of Holland.</note> had ſome colour for his <hi>expence</hi> which he <hi>laviſhed</hi> without <hi>reaſon,</hi> to the weakening of his unſettled fortunes; being forced to <hi>follow</hi> the other then, in all his <hi>faſhions.</hi> And which <hi>Infection,</hi> by after-Cuſtome, became his <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe</hi> alſo, and almoſt if not <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtering,</hi> yet <hi>over-ſhadowing</hi> his Natural, eminent parts, with which his inſide was <hi>habited,</hi> and perſpicuous to ſuch as knew him.</p>
               <p>But I am not delighted, to <hi>urge</hi> out this <hi>ſtory</hi> of the <hi>Earl of Carlile:</hi> as not willing to ſpeak ill of any; unlike our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> that <hi>ſpares</hi> none, but <hi>Him.</hi> For I ſhould know; that vertue and vice, are <hi>Inherent</hi> in <hi>Man.</hi> And as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us to tell <hi>truth,</hi> when we ſpeak their <hi>vertue:</hi> yet with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and compaſſion to <hi>diſcover</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169833:41"/>their <hi>vices:</hi> either being <hi>Examples</hi> for the future; that, to <hi>imitate; this,</hi> to <hi>ſhun.</hi> And I cannot but with <hi>Compunction</hi> remind, That the monſtrous <hi>exceſſe</hi> of the <hi>belly,</hi> and the <hi>back,</hi> by his firſt <hi>Preſident,</hi> became then the <hi>Mode</hi> of thoſe times, for <hi>great Perſons</hi> (the moſt part) to <hi>follow,</hi> and for the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People</hi> to this hour to <hi>practiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, a <hi>wiſe</hi> and a good <hi>Man,</hi> ought juſtly to have hated his <hi>condition</hi> in this without ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>malice</hi> or <hi>envy;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 21.</note> as it is ſaid <hi>Northampton</hi> did, who yet, as may be remembred, took leave of this <hi>life,</hi> ere <hi>Hay</hi> was ſetled <hi>on horsback.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that other marke of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach</hi> alſo, may without partial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be taken oft the <hi>Score</hi> from that Noble <hi>Northampton;</hi> who on my conſcience (for I knew him well) diſdained the <hi>Guilt</hi> in that frivolous <hi>ſtory</hi> of Sir <hi>Robert Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</hi> Nor is it material, to credit
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169833:42"/>the reſt of that <hi>Rant,</hi> in his <hi>Vice-Admirall voyage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Remark</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Second Remarke. Pamp. 30.</note> falls upon the <hi>Treaſon of</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Ralegh,</hi> which the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> calls <hi>an arrant trick of State; and Cecil the Imenire facias thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir Walter Ralegh</hi> was a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of good alliance,
<note place="margin">Sr. Walter Ralegh.</note> in the <hi>west</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and very <hi>well</hi> deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He began his <hi>Improvements,</hi> by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and <hi>Inns of Court;</hi> the latter was alwaies the place of eſteem with the <hi>Queen</hi> which, ſhe ſaid, fitted <hi>youth</hi> for the <hi>future.</hi> But he ſtaid not there. And as his fate would have him, of the <hi>Sword</hi> firſt; ſo his <hi>deſtinie</hi> drew him on, to have a <hi>mixt reputation,</hi> with the <hi>Gown:</hi> For he was often called to <hi>Councell</hi> but never <hi>ſworn.</hi> He was twice in <hi>Expeditions</hi> of Land-ſervice into <hi>Ireland,</hi> under <hi>Generall Norris and Grey,</hi> a Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer in either, as alſo in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:169833:42"/>and a voiage at <hi>Sea</hi> ere he was known at <hi>Court.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch waies as theſe, were his <hi>Introductions</hi> (the beſt hopes of his riſing:) ſome <hi>Naturall parts</hi> he had, a good <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>judgement;</hi> but his beſt <hi>weapon</hi> was his <hi>tongue,</hi> which gave him repute to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned then; but after he improved to a great <hi>value,</hi> in his future <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles;</hi> the beſt <hi>School</hi> to a <hi>wiſe man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He had a quarrel with <hi>Grey</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which being referred to a <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> it had like to coſt him his <hi>life:</hi> But by reference came afterwards to repetition, at home before the <hi>Lords. Grey</hi> had the better cauſe, but <hi>Ralegh</hi> the advantage in pleading; who ſo took them, eſpecially <hi>Lester,</hi> that the <hi>Queen</hi> was told the <hi>tale;</hi> and ſomewhat more of him. And no ſooner he came to be known to <hi>Her,</hi> but <hi>She</hi> took him, to <hi>grace.</hi> In whom (as in other of the like
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169833:43"/>form) their alwaies meet opoſites, Enemies of greater ranck, and they kept him under, ſometimes in, ſometimes out, which when it fell out to be ſo, he would wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decline himſelfe, out of the <hi>Court-rode.</hi> And then you found him not but by fame. In <hi>voyages</hi> to the <hi>West Indies, Gueana,</hi> New <hi>Plantations, Virginia,</hi> or in ſome <hi>Expeditions</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> Againſt whom, his and other the like ſucceſſe, of <hi>Drake, Candiſh, Forliſher, Hawkins,</hi> with other <hi>Iſland-voyages,</hi> neer home, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd <hi>Ralegh,</hi> a grand <hi>Oppoſer</hi> of the generall <hi>peace</hi> which <hi>King James brought</hi> in with him; and that <hi>brought Ralegh to his ruin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for all theſe his good <hi>parts,</hi> he roſe to no more, then <hi>Governor</hi> of <hi>Jerſey, Lord Warden</hi> of the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries</hi> in the Weſt, and <hi>Captain</hi> of the <hi>Guard</hi> to the <hi>Queens perſon;</hi> which laſt place, brought him to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169833:43"/>
                  <hi>eſteem</hi> in the <hi>Court,</hi> but not in the <hi>State</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>Yet buſie he had been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſpeak his mind, of the <hi>Generall affaires;</hi> and therein he pleaſed his late <hi>Miſtreſſe.</hi> For then his <hi>inclination</hi> went with the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> of thoſe times of <hi>War;</hi> But now, his <hi>Councell</hi> came out of <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> For at the entrance of the <hi>King;</hi> He was preſented by <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legh</hi> with a <hi>Manuſcript</hi> of his own, againſt the <hi>peace</hi> with <hi>Spain.</hi> It was alwaies his table talk, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the more eſteem, which took accordingly. And the way to make him the contrary, was the work of the <hi>Spaniſh faction.</hi> Either to <hi>buy</hi> him out of that humour, or to <hi>abuſe</hi> him into a <hi>worſe condition</hi> which was thus effected.</p>
               <p>And indeed to mould this <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> there was a medly of divers <hi>conditions;</hi> but the <hi>contrivers</hi> were two <hi>Priests, Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clarke</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169833:44"/>
                  <hi>count Arembergh, Embaſſedor Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> for the <hi>Arch-Duke,</hi> who brought in the <hi>Lord Cobham;</hi> and he, his brother <hi>George Brooke;</hi> and he, <hi>Parham;</hi> and theſe, the <hi>Lord Grey of Wilton.</hi> Then came in Sir <hi>Walter Ralegh,</hi> the wiſeſt of them all; who dallied like the <hi>flie</hi> with the <hi>flame,</hi> till it conſumed him. Willing he was (it ſeemes) to know it, and thought by his <hi>wit,</hi> to over-reach the <hi>confederates;</hi> whom he <hi>knew</hi> well enough; though none but <hi>Cobham,</hi> for a good while, <hi>dealt</hi> with him. And with him, <hi>Ralegh</hi> plaid <hi>faſt and looſe,</hi> till himſelfe was caught in the <hi>Gin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was one <hi>Mathew De Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie,</hi> here at <hi>London</hi> a <hi>Merchant</hi> of <hi>Antwerpe;</hi> with whom <hi>Cobham</hi> held <hi>Intelligence,</hi> for <hi>many years</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; &amp; for ſome <hi>reaſons</hi> of State, connived at, by the late <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>her Councel.</hi> This Man, was the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169833:44"/>
                  <hi>property,</hi> whom <hi>Arenbergh</hi> made uſe of, to <hi>Cobham;</hi> who now was much <hi>diſcontented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe 3. made the firſt ſtep to the <hi>contrivement:</hi> And it hath bin my <hi>jealouſie,</hi> that <hi>Lawrency</hi> betrayed it, to this <hi>State:</hi> for I never, could be <hi>aſſured,</hi> how it was <hi>diſcovered;</hi> though I have bin often <hi>preſent with Sir Walter,</hi> in his <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> when he pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately <hi>diſcourſed</hi> hereof.</p>
               <p>But being ripe, they were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally <hi>examined,</hi> &amp; <hi>reſirained;</hi> firſt to their <hi>owne homes,</hi> not without <hi>watchful eyes,</hi> on either of them; then to <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> and laſtly, to their <hi>Tryals</hi> at <hi>Winchester;</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Terme</hi> removed, out of this evermore <hi>Peſtilentiall City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And on the 17. <hi>November</hi> 1602.
<note place="margin">His ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment</note> the day of <hi>Arraignment</hi> for <hi>Ralegh,</hi> and the <hi>Jury</hi> called to the <hi>Bar.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> he did not <hi>except;</hi> nor could: for they were
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169833:45"/>the moſt able <hi>ſufficient,</hi> in <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, (where the fact had its ſcene.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall <hi>name</hi> them. <hi>Sir Ralphe Conisby, Sir Thomas Fowler,</hi> Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peacock,</hi> Sir <hi>William Roe, Knights. Henry Godwin, Bobert Wood, Thomas Walker, Thomas Whitley, Thomas Highgate, Robert Kempton, John Chalke</hi> and <hi>Robert Bromley Eſquries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Indictment</hi> was managed, by the <hi>King's Atturney</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cook, Serjeant Heal,</hi> and Ser. <hi>Philips;</hi> and drawne from the 9. Iun. 1603. The <hi>accuſation</hi> was <hi>double,</hi> againſt the King, and the State. The <hi>perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> had 2. <hi>parts,</hi> firſt againſt <hi>his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly</hi> to diſable his <hi>title</hi> to this <hi>Crowne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>firſt,</hi> was read <hi>Brookes confeſſion;</hi> That his <hi>Brother Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> uſed theſe ſpeeches, <hi>That it would never be well, till the King and his cubs were taken away,</hi> and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169833:45"/>ſaid, that he thought it proceeded from <hi>Ralegh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this <hi>Ralegh</hi> anſwered, That <hi>Brookes</hi> was his <hi>enemy.</hi> It was replyed, but <hi>Cobham</hi> was ever your <hi>friend;</hi> and it would ſeeme, a ſtrange <hi>malice</hi> in <hi>Brooks,</hi> to <hi>ruin</hi> his <hi>brother,</hi> to undo <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>ſecond part,</hi> there was produced a <hi>Booke,</hi> (which I have read) <hi>a defence of the Queens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, againſt</hi> Mary <hi>Queen of Scots;</hi> which <hi>Cobham</hi> confeſſed <hi>Ralegh</hi> had delivered to him, and he to <hi>Brookes,</hi> and <hi>Brookes</hi> to <hi>Gray,</hi> upon <hi>Cobhams diſcontent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ralegh</hi> acknowledged, that it contained matter of ſcandal to the <hi>Kings title.</hi> And that he had leave of Sir <hi>Robert Ceill,</hi> after his <hi>Fathers</hi> death, to ſearch his <hi>ſtudy,</hi> for <hi>Coſmographicall Manuſcripts,</hi> of the <hi>Weſts-Indies,</hi> and ſo lighted on this <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir Robert Cecill</hi> then preſent
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169833:46"/>upon the Bench acknowledged this leaſe: and ſaid, <hi>He would then as really have trusted him, as any man;
<note place="margin">Sir Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils words.</note> though ſince for ſome Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Sir Walter the bonds of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection were crackt; and yet, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his duty to the King, which may not be diſpenſed withall, in this his Masters ſervice, he ſwore by God, he loved him; and had a great conflict in himſelf, that ſo compleat a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was fallen from this State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this <hi>paſſage, needs no ſooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to excuſe <hi>Cecill</hi> either for the <hi>Father</hi> or the <hi>Son.</hi> For I have heard <hi>Sir Robert Cecil,</hi> when he was <hi>Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> ſay publickly at his own ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, That he had intercepted and kept all the conſiderable <hi>Libells,</hi> againſt the late <hi>Queen</hi> and this <hi>King.</hi> But though <hi>Juſtifiable</hi> in them as <hi>Councelours</hi> of <hi>State;</hi> yet it was a <hi>crime</hi> in <hi>Ralegh,</hi> who never was any. And this <hi>Book,</hi> as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, was of <hi>one Bragg</hi> or <hi>Stagg</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:169833:46"/>a <hi>Jeſuite.</hi> But Sir <hi>Walter</hi> excuſed it; That there was nothing acted thereby, to the <hi>Kings</hi> prejudice; for the <hi>Book</hi> was <hi>burnt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to inſiſt hereupon; <hi>Cobham</hi> had confeſſed, That <hi>Rale g</hi> had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed; That <hi>Cobham</hi> ſhould treate with <hi>Aremburgh</hi> for 600. <hi>thouſand Crownes,</hi> to the intent, to advance the title of the Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> to this <hi>Crown.</hi> That <hi>Cobham</hi> under pretence of travelling ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute this <hi>deſigne,</hi> in the <hi>Lowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countries, France</hi> and <hi>Spaine;</hi> and to carry 3. letters from her, to the <hi>Arch-Duke, Duke of Savoy,</hi> and to the <hi>King of Spaine,</hi> and to promiſe toleration of <hi>Religion,</hi> and her <hi>Marriage</hi> to be diſpoſed of, by them. That at his returne, he ſhould meete <hi>Ralegh</hi> at <hi>Jerſey</hi> the place of his <hi>command;</hi> and there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, to diſpoſe the <hi>money</hi> to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents.</hi> And <hi>Ralegh</hi> ſhould have 7. <hi>thouſand crownes</hi> from <hi>Arenberge,</hi> for himſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:169833:47"/>
               <p>And further confeſſed, that Ralegh <hi>had Inſtigated him to all theſe Treaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that <hi>Ralegh</hi> ſhould ſay; that he thought the beſt way to trouble <hi>England,</hi> was to cauſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this, onely of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he anſwered &amp; confeſſed the <hi>words;</hi> and that he had ſo thought, theſe 20. yeares. <hi>It ſeemes by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell ſince he was not in ſtaken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lawrencie</hi> confeſſed that <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Cobham</hi> and <hi>Ralegh</hi> being together, he delivered a letter to <hi>Cobhane,</hi> from <hi>Arembergh;</hi> and preſently <hi>Ralegh</hi> went with <hi>Cobham</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to conferre thereof.</p>
               <p>To all theſe <hi>confeſſions, Ralegh</hi> craved that <hi>Cobham</hi> might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, to accuſe him <hi>face to face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I may not omit one paſſage acted <hi>heretofore,</hi> which comes in properly <hi>here</hi> to be conſidered. When the <hi>confederates</hi> had ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169833:47"/>under ſome <hi>Examinations,</hi> and were <hi>reſtrained</hi> to their ſeveral houſes: And <hi>Ralegh</hi> knew well that <hi>Lawreney</hi> was then <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> but not <hi>examined;</hi> then did <hi>Ralegh</hi> diſcover in a letter to Sir <hi>Robert Cecil,</hi> where <hi>Cobham</hi> was with <hi>Lawrency;</hi> and that then was the time, to <hi>apprehend Lawrency,</hi> and ſo to intercept their <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> ere matters were ripe.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Ralegh's</hi> deſigne was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I muſt confeſſe, my conceipt is very blunt. But this uſe was made of it to <hi>Raleghs ruine.</hi> For after that <hi>Cobham,</hi> had denied much of the former <hi>ſtuffe,</hi> upon his firſt <hi>Examinations;</hi> this letter was ſhewed <hi>him,</hi> under <hi>Ralegh's</hi> hand, &amp; upon mature &amp; often delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be aſſured, that it was his hand: Then <hi>Cobham</hi> in an <hi>Extaſie,</hi> calling <hi>Ralegh Villain, Traitor;</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his poſitive <hi>Accuſation</hi> of <hi>Ralegh,</hi> as aforeſaid: and added,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169833:48"/>That <hi>Ralegh,</hi> after his firſt <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> before the <hi>Lords,</hi> had writ to <hi>Cobham, that although he had bin examined of many things, yet that he had cleered</hi> Cobham <hi>of all, when (as the Lords proteſted)</hi> he had not at all, been <hi>examined</hi> concerning <hi>Cobham.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this was inferred by the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi>) to confirm <hi>Cobham</hi> to deny all, when he ſhould be <hi>examined;</hi> Sir <hi>Walter</hi> ſaid, That <hi>Cobham</hi> had not <hi>ſigned</hi> his <hi>accuſation,</hi> and that he was at the worſt but <hi>ſingularis Teſtis.</hi> To which my Lord <hi>Chief Justice</hi> gave it for <hi>law,</hi> that it was not neceſſary, to <hi>ſigne,</hi> nor to have more then <hi>One witneſſe:</hi> after much pleading herein; and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legh</hi> alledging <hi>law and Scripture,</hi> for not admitting a <hi>ſingle witneſſe,</hi> to condemn one, yet the <hi>Court</hi> was ſatisfyed therein, by the <hi>Judges</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ralegh</hi> ſaid, Then prove it by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169833:48"/>
                  <hi>One witneſſe face to face, and I will confeſſe my ſelf guilty:</hi> but the <hi>Judges</hi> were of opinion, that it was not to be permitted by law: yet <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legh</hi> inſiſted hereupon, with many <hi>stories</hi> which took up <hi>much time:</hi> Then being asked, if he would be <hi>concluded</hi> thereby if <hi>Cobham</hi> would now juſtify his <hi>accuſation, under his</hi> hand. To this it may be obſerved that <hi>Ralegh</hi> made no anſwer at all but conſented that the <hi>Jury</hi> ſhould go together.</p>
               <p>Then was produced <hi>Cobham's</hi> letter to the Lords, writ but the day before, in effect thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Sir Walter, had writ a letter to him wrapt in an apple, and caſt in at his window ten daies ſince, in the Tower, to intreate him for God's ſake to write to him, under his own hand, that he had wronged him in his accuſatious: and odviſed him to be conſtant in denialls, rather then to appeale to the King.</hi> And now
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169833:49"/>(writes <hi>Cobham</hi>) <hi>It is no time to diſſemble; and therefore proteſted before God and his Angells, that all and every part of his accuſation, of Sir</hi> Walter Ralegh, <hi>was ſubstvntially true.</hi> And added; <hi>That</hi> Ralegh <hi>had dealt with him, ſince the King's comming to procure him a penſion from</hi> Spain, <hi>for Intelligence &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>Ralegh,</hi> rayling againſt <hi>Cobham,</hi> confeſſed this letter was in an <hi>Apple,</hi> to which <hi>Cobham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned an anſwer; which <hi>Ralegh</hi> produced, and deſired that it might be read. But the <hi>Atturney</hi> oppoſed Sir <hi>Robert Cecil's</hi> conſent thereto. To whom <hi>Cecil</hi> replied: <hi>Sir, you are more preremptory then honest, come you hither to direct us?</hi> And ſo read it. Which in effect was a <hi>confeſſion that he had wronged Sir Walter, and that he was Innocent.</hi> This bore date 10. dayes before. And here <hi>Ralegh</hi> confeſſed, That <hi>Cobham</hi> had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169833:49"/>to him a <hi>Penſion,</hi> from <hi>Spain,</hi> to the effect before confeſſed: And that he had <hi>concealed</hi> it, as loath to ruine <hi>Cobham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Jury</hi> went out, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in halfe an houre, with their <hi>Verdict; Guilty.</hi> So was <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> as in <hi>Caſe of Treaſon.</hi> And he was returned, to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and there lay upon <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve</hi> 2. yeares, and 3. years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was <hi>executed</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1618.
<note place="margin">Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Tryall.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe this <hi>Second Remarke</hi> in the Pamphleter and this <hi>Prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> ſtickes in their <hi>ſtomacks,</hi> with which they indeavour to <hi>choke</hi> the <hi>Readers;</hi> I have thereſore bin the more <hi>prolix;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pam p. 35.</note> that thereby the whole world may judge, with the <hi>Jury,</hi> of his <hi>guilt</hi> or <hi>Innocency. Vide</hi> page 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ralegh's</hi> riſe of preferment, was occaſioned upon a conteſt with the <hi>Lord Grey</hi> in the <hi>Queenes time,</hi> which they were to plead <hi>face to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169833:50"/>face:</hi> Where indeed, but not in <hi>truth,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter</hi> had the better by the <hi>tongue,</hi> telling his tale to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; which tooke the Queen, who tooke him from that inſtant into favour as before remembred. Belike he expected the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence at this time, when ſo oft he deſired to plead <hi>face to face,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 35.</note> with <hi>Cobham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How could <hi>Wade</hi> the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the <hi>Tower</hi> (as is ſurmized) <hi>tamper with</hi> Cobham, <hi>to write his name to a blanck, to which</hi> Wade <hi>framed the accuſation againſt</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legh. When it appeares, <hi>Cobham</hi> never <hi>ſigned at all,</hi> to his <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations;</hi> which therefore was ſo much inſiſted upon, at his <hi>tryall,</hi> for his advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in truth; beſides the confeſſion of</hi> Cobham, <hi>the fatal evidence was</hi> Cobham's <hi>own voluntary last letter of accuſation, or confeſſion over night, writ every whit with his own hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:169833:50"/>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> commanded (as the COURT was aſſured at the triall) that upon any <hi>examination,</hi> there ſhould none be rackt, which made Captaine <hi>Kemiſh</hi> (who was the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of meſſages and letters betweene <hi>Ralegh</hi> and <hi>Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>) often to proteſt, in my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That in truth, he was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the <hi>Rack,</hi> which was ſhewed to him, but had he taſted therof, he ſaid, that he ſhould have bin inforced, to tell an odd tale, <hi>meaning of diſcovery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sr. <hi>Walter</hi> was admitted a <hi>chair, pen, Inck</hi> and <hi>paper</hi> for his <hi>memory.</hi> And truly he rather ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the <hi>Court and Jury,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Repree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ed.</note> with <hi>Impertinences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus was Sr. <hi>Walter Ralegh</hi> reprieved to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and many years of <hi>Impriſonment</hi> in that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, till his future <hi>merits,</hi> and fame of <hi>learning,</hi> begat many to <hi>pitty</hi> his <hi>ſufferings;</hi> So that at laſt, by meanes of the <hi>French Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,</hi> with others of <hi>our own Lords,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:169833:51"/>he had freedome, to <hi>repair</hi> for his health, to his <hi>Houſe</hi> at <hi>Saint James,</hi> and after a year or two, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a Commiſſion, to make a <hi>Voyage</hi> to <hi>Gueana</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> for the return of <hi>Gold Oare or Mine.</hi> But was expreſly limitted, not to <hi>trench</hi> upon the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to the breach of <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His landing was at St. <hi>Tomaz,</hi> a <hi>Town</hi> of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> upon the opening of the <hi>Great River Oreno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> in <hi>America.</hi> Where he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many of them, and there <hi>loſt</hi> his eldeſt ſon <hi>Walter,</hi> under the <hi>Walls.</hi> Then ſends he Captain <hi>Kemiſh,</hi> his old Servant, <hi>(upon whoſe confidence it appears this voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was reſolved)</hi> up this River, to the <hi>foot</hi> of a <hi>Mountain,</hi> where here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and alſo during <hi>Ralegh's Impriſonment,</hi> he had been ſent, and returned, with wonderfull <hi>Remarks</hi> of a rich <hi>Mine,</hi> or rather <hi>Madre-del-Ore.</hi> But now comes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169833:51"/>from thence. And all the account came to no more, but that the <hi>Mountain</hi> was fled away, he could <hi>not find it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, the whole <hi>ſleet</hi> 4. or 5. ſaile, <hi>mutiny</hi> forces him home again as a <hi>Priſoner:</hi> in the return, <hi>Kemiſh</hi> kills himſelf, in his own <hi>Cabin,</hi> &amp; ſo no tales could be <hi>told.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ralegh's ſhips</hi> were firſt, caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſouth of <hi>Ireland:</hi> then they land in the Weſt of <hi>England;</hi> where warrants were ready to apprehend him <hi>Priſoner</hi> to the <hi>Tower.</hi> In the <hi>West,</hi> he is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to deal with a <hi>French Maſter</hi> of a ſhip, to ſteal <hi>away</hi> into <hi>France.</hi> Then in his journy to <hi>London,</hi> he combines, with a <hi>French Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banck,</hi> who aſſiſted him with <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients,</hi> (which he deſired) that would without danger of life, bring him to breake forth into <hi>Blanes:</hi> Purpoſely done, by this meanes to get <hi>longer time,</hi> to work
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169833:52"/>
                  <hi>opportunities</hi> to ſave <hi>his life;</hi> which he knew he had ſo <hi>deeply forfeited.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then being delivered into the <hi>hands</hi> of Sir <hi>John Stukely, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of the <hi>Tower</hi> he deales with him for a ſum of <hi>Money,</hi> part in hand being paid, to join with him in <hi>Eſcapeboth</hi> of them, into <hi>France. Stukely</hi> yields to all, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies him by water, in the way to <hi>Graveſend;</hi> where <hi>(by deſigne of Stukelie's treachery, in that, and ſo it proſpered with him, being hang'd afterwards, for clipping of Gold)</hi> they were ſeized and brought back to the <hi>Tower.</hi> From whence, very ſpeedily, <hi>Ralegh</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the King's-Bench-bar at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> before the <hi>Lord chief Juſtice Mountegue;</hi> where the <hi>Records</hi> of his former <hi>Sentence</hi> only were read; &amp; hedemanded, why <hi>Execution ſhould</hi> not be done?</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Walter</hi> acknowledged that <hi>Sentence,</hi> and the <hi>King's</hi> Mercy for
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169833:52"/>his life thus long: And that he hoped, ſeeing he had bin imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Commiſſion, with power of life and death, over the King's <hi>Lie ge People,</hi> it did make void that former ſentence.</p>
               <p>He was told to the <hi>contrary,</hi> and that his time of <hi>Execution</hi> was the next morning: and ſo the <hi>Sheriff</hi> of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> took him into cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the <hi>Gate-Houſe,</hi> and to <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> the next day, in the old <hi>Palace yard,</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> where he had the favor of the <hi>Ax.</hi> which he ſaid (ſmilingly touching it) was a ſharp <hi>Medioine,</hi> but a true <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> to cure all diſeaſes: and ſo it proved to him, at this very <hi>time</hi> in his <hi>Ague. ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At his death, himſelfe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; to <hi>cleere</hi> ſome <hi>points,</hi> (which it ſeemes our <hi>Pamphleter</hi> knew not of otherwiſe he would have done it for him.)</p>
               <p>To have had often plots with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169833:53"/>
                  <hi>France,</hi> which he denied, but confeſſed, that he had bin ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thence; and indeavoured to <hi>eſcape</hi> thither at twice. That the <hi>French Agent,</hi> came oft to him, with <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from that <hi>King</hi> to him; But he returned the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That he ſhould ſpeake diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the King: his accuſer, he ſaid, was a baſe runagate, <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and perfideous, whom he truſted; being ſworne to ſecrecie, which he betrayed; much he ſaid in theſe particulars, which he did not deny, but <hi>traverſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then there were, other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of charge, to which he was liable to a new <hi>Tryall.</hi> But the <hi>prudence</hi> of the King <hi>would</hi> not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard further proceedings, having a ſufficient upon the <hi>old ſcore.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 38.</note> And now for that additional tale of the <hi>Pamphleter</hi> concerning Sir <hi>Walters</hi> recovery of <hi>Queen Anne; for which
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169833:53"/>he begg'd the boone, viz. for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the Lord</hi> Cobham <hi>by</hi> 4. <hi>Earles and</hi> 2. <hi>Councelors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I never <hi>heard</hi> nor <hi>read</hi> thereof before, nor can beleeve it. For this I know by ſeverall <hi>relations</hi> of thoſe great <hi>Ladies</hi> of her <hi>Bedcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> and of her <hi>Chirurgians</hi> and <hi>Phyſitians</hi> now living, <hi>That She was never cured of her diſeaſe, but by death,</hi> that ends all <hi>Maladies.</hi> It followes in the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> That after he hath ranted his Stories of <hi>Manſell</hi> and <hi>Monſon,</hi> and of the peace, ratifyed and ſworne; He makes <hi>Cecill</hi> the chief <hi>Ringleader</hi> of the King by the <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to ſay truth, The King was alwaies brought up to his eaſe, though the fore-part of his <hi>Raigne</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> proved <hi>troubleſome</hi> enough to his Councell. And therefore now, he was to follow his affaires, in peace, and his own <hi>Inclination,</hi> in a <hi>Sportfull</hi> life. The
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169833:54"/>rather; <hi>He</hi> being much Subject to <hi>unwildines or weaknes</hi> in his <hi>Limbs,</hi> and which becauſe of his extream diſ-affection to <hi>Phyſick,</hi> he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to the beſt <hi>Aire,</hi> moſt <hi>agreable to the Nature of Scotland, freſh</hi> and <hi>bleak:</hi> and for that end, he choſe <hi>Royſtan,</hi> and <hi>Newmarket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Without, that Scandalous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation, <hi>of leaving his Queen, without any love or liking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are forced to fall upon <hi>One Lake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir Tho. Lake. Pamp. 54.</note> whom we find to be that learned Gentleman Sir <hi>Thomas Lake,</hi> apted in his youth with ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of the <hi>Book,</hi> to attend Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi> (that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>Secretary of State</hi> to Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizebeth</hi>) as <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> to him: And after good experience of his <hi>deſarts,</hi> he was recommended to the <hi>Queen,</hi> and read to her <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Latine.</hi> In which tongues, ſhe would ſay, that he <hi>ſurpaſſed</hi> her <hi>Secretaries,</hi> and was ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169833:54"/>to her death; for he was reading to her, when the COUNTESSE <hi>of</hi> WAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WICK <hi>told him, that the Queen was departed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But not long before;
<note place="margin">&amp; merits</note> ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him <hi>Clarke</hi> of her <hi>Signet.</hi> And he was choſen, by this State in that place to attend the <hi>King</hi> from BARWICK. And ſo ſufficient he was, that the <hi>King</hi> made uſe of his preſent <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> in ſome <hi>French affaires,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came into <hi>England.</hi> Which indeed <hi>Secretary Cecil</hi> had reaſon to reſent, as too much trenching on <hi>his Office.</hi> And therefore cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved leave of the <hi>King,</hi> that he might not attend beyond his <hi>Moneth</hi> to prejudice the other Clarks Which was excuſed, and he kept ſtill at Court.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Sufficiencies</hi> of his, enabled him in thoſe times of gaining, with much repute, and direct
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169833:55"/>honeſty, to purchaſe large <hi>poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After <hi>Ccils</hi> death, the <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Secretary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">as ſecreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> was joyned in two <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals.</hi> And not long after he was one of them, &amp; ſo continued, with <hi>Honourably esteem</hi> of all men; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til that <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> two violent <hi>paſſions,</hi> over-ruling the <hi>Weaker Sexe,</hi> concerning his <hi>wife</hi> and <hi>daughter,</hi> involved him into their <hi>quarrel,</hi> the chiefe and onely cauſe of his <hi>ruine.</hi> He had by his <hi>Wife,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with his wife and daughter.</note> ſons and daughters. His <hi>eldeſt</hi> married unto the <hi>Lord Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Roſſe</hi> (in right of a <hi>Grand-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>) the ſon of <hi>Thomas Earle of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter</hi> by a former venter. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the credit of Sir <hi>Thomas Lake,</hi> he was ſent <hi>Embaſſadour Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary into Spaine,</hi> in a very <hi>gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Equipage,</hi> with ſome hopes of his own, to continue <hi>Leiger,</hi> to ſave charges of tranſmitting any other.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169833:55"/>
               <p>In his abſence there fell out an extreame <hi>deadly</hi> fewd (tis no matter for what) betweene the <hi>Lady Lake</hi> and the <hi>Counteſſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Exeter.</note> A youthful widow ſhe had bin and <hi>vertuous;</hi> and ſo became <hi>Bedfellow</hi> to this <hi>aged, gowty, diſeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> but <hi>noble Earle.</hi> And, that <hi>preferment</hi> had made her ſubject to <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Malice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Home comes the <hi>Lord Roſſe</hi> from his Embaſſy, when being fallen into ſome neglect of his <hi>wife and his kindred;</hi> I conceive, upon refuſal of an increaſe of <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance</hi> to her <hi>ſettlement</hi> of <hi>joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which was promiſed to be compleated at his returne.</p>
               <p>Not long he ſtaies in <hi>England,</hi> but away he gets into Italy, turnes a profeſſed <hi>Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> being couſened into that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> by his publick <hi>confident, Gondamore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this his laſt abſence (<hi>never</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:169833:56"/>to <hi>returne</hi>) the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</note> accuſe the <hi>Counteſſe,</hi> of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Incontinencie</hi> with the Lord <hi>Roſſe,</hi> whilſt he was here, and that therefore, upon his <hi>wives diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> he was fled from hence, and from her <hi>Marriage. Bed,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deviſed <hi>Calumnies</hi> by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſignes and contrivements, to have <hi>poiſoned</hi> the <hi>Mother and daughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This quarrel, was ſoone bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon'd at Court, to the <hi>King's eare,</hi> who as privately as could be, ſingly, <hi>examines</hi> each party. The <hi>Counteſſe,</hi> with teares and Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, profeſſeth her <hi>Innocency,</hi> which to oppoſe the <hi>Mother Lake and her daughter,</hi> counterfeit her hand, to a whole ſheet of paper; wherein they make the <hi>Counteſſe,</hi> with much <hi>contrition,</hi> to <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> her ſelfe <hi>guilty,</hi> craves par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for <hi>attempting</hi> to <hi>poiſon</hi>them, &amp; deſires <hi>friendſlsip</hi> with them all.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169833:56"/>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> gets ſight of this, as in favour to them, and demands, the <hi>place, time,</hi> and <hi>occaſion,</hi> when this ſhould be writ. They tell him, that all the parties met, in a viſit at <hi>Wimbleton, (the houſe of the Lord of Exeter)</hi> where, in diſpute of their <hi>differences,</hi> ſhe <hi>confeſſes</hi> her guilt of attempting their poiſon. And being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of abſolution and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, (being required thereto) conſents, to ſet down all <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> therein, under her own <hi>hand,</hi> which preſently ſhe writ, at the <hi>Window,</hi> in the upper end of the great <hi>Chamber,</hi> at <hi>Whimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in preſence of the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Daughter,</hi> the <hi>Lord Roſſe,</hi> and one <hi>Diego</hi> a <hi>Spaniard</hi> his confiding <hi>Servant.</hi> But now they being gone, &amp; at <hi>Rome,</hi> the King forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſends Mr. <hi>Dendy</hi> (one of his <hi>Serjeants</hi> at <hi>Armes</hi> ſometime a domeſtick of the <hi>Earl of Exeters,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:169833:57"/>an <hi>honest</hi> and worthy <hi>Gentleman</hi>) poſt to <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſpeedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes with <hi>Roſſe,</hi> and <hi>Diego's hand,</hi> and other teſtimonialls, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That all the ſaid <hi>accuſation,</hi> and <hi>confeſſion, Suſpitions</hi> and <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> concerning the <hi>Counteſſe,</hi> were notorious <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> and confirmes it by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Hoaſt,</hi> in aſſurance of her <hi>Honour</hi> and his <hi>Innocency.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> well ſatisfyed, ſends to the <hi>Counteſſe friends and truſties,</hi> for her <hi>Jointure</hi> and <hi>Eſtate;</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring many of her <hi>letters,</hi> with this writing, do conclude it <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, <hi>He</hi> tells the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Daughter,</hi> that this writing, being denied by her, and their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies being parties, would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, with any belief. But any other <hi>Additionall Witneſſe,</hi> would give it ſufficient credit. To which they aſſure <hi>him,</hi> That one <hi>Sarah Swarton,</hi> their <hi>Chambereſſe</hi> ſtood
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169833:57"/>behind the hanging, at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the <hi>Room,</hi> and heard the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> reade over, what ſhe had <hi>writ:</hi> and her alſo they procure, to <hi>ſwear</hi> unto this, <hi>before</hi> the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make further <hi>tryal,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> in a hunting journy, at <hi>New Park</hi> neer <hi>Wimbleton,</hi> gallops thither, viewes the <hi>Room;</hi> obſerving the great diſtance of the <hi>Window,</hi> from the lower end of the Room, and placing himſelf, behind the <hi>hanging,</hi> and ſo other <hi>Lords</hi> in turn; they could not <hi>hear</hi> one <hi>ſpeak a loud,</hi> from the <hi>window.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Houſe-Keeper</hi> was call'd, who proteſted thoſe hangings had conſtantly furniſht that <hi>room,</hi> for 20. years; which the <hi>King</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, to be two foot <hi>ſhort</hi> of the <hi>ground,</hi> and might diſcover the <hi>woman,</hi> if hidden behind them. I may preſent alſo, the King ſaying, <hi>Oaths cannot confound my ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides all this, the <hi>Mother</hi> and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169833:58"/>
                  <hi>Daughter,</hi> counterfeit another writing, a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of one <hi>Luke Hutton,</hi> acknowledging for 40. l. annuity, the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> hired him to poiſon them; which <hi>Man,</hi> with wonderful providence, was <hi>found</hi> out privately; and denies it to the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus prepared, the <hi>King</hi> ſends for Sr. <hi>Thomas Lake,</hi> whom in truth he very much valued; tells him, the danger to imbark himſelf, in this quarrel; adviſing him, to leave them to the <hi>law,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now ready for the <hi>Star-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> He humbly thanked his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, <hi>but could not refuſe: to be a Father and a Husband,</hi> and ſo puts his <hi>Name</hi> with theirs,
<note place="margin">comes to Hearing in Stur; chamber.</note> in a <hi>croſſe Bill.</hi> Which at the hearing, took up 5. ſeveral daies, the <hi>King</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Judgement.</hi> But the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer teſtimonies, and ſome private <hi>confeſſions,</hi> of the <hi>Lady Roſſe,</hi> and <hi>Sarah Wharton;</hi> which the King
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169833:58"/>kept in private, from publick proceedings, made the cauſe, for ſome of the daies of triall, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doubtful to the Court, untill the <hi>King's</hi> diſcovery, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the <hi>Sentence;</hi> and was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced upon ſeverall <hi>Cenſures.</hi> Sr. <hi>Thomas Lake</hi> and his <hi>Lady</hi> fined 10000. l. <hi>to the King; five thouſand pounds to the Counteſſe;</hi> 50. l. <hi>to</hi> Hutton, Sara Wharton <hi>to be whipt, at a Carts taile, about the ſtreets, and to do penance at Saint</hi> Martin's Church; The <hi>Lady Roſſe</hi> for confeſſing the truth and plot in the midſt of the triall, was <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by the Major Voices, from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Sentence.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The King, I remember, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their <hi>crimes,</hi> to the firſt plot of the firſt <hi>ſin in Paradiſe: the Lady Lake</hi> to the <hi>Serpent,</hi> her <hi>daughter</hi> unto <hi>Eve,</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> to poor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> whom he thought in his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> that his <hi>love to</hi> his <hi>wife</hi> had
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169833:59"/>beguiled him. I am ſure, he paid for all, which as he told me, coſt him <hi>thirty thouſand pounds;</hi> and the loſſe of his <hi>Maſters</hi> favour, and offices of <hi>gaine</hi> and <hi>honour;</hi> but truly with much pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of the Court.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Pamphleter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 57. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scots.</note> enters upon the <hi>Scots,</hi> pa. 57. and would couſen us, to credit their <hi>Story,</hi> where he begins a diviſion, between the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and them at Court, &amp; goes ſmoothly on, to the middle of theſe <hi>laſt times,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 58.</note> when it ſeemes he writ this: And, as he ſaies, <hi>ſaw all our happineſſe derivative, from their favours, by their own valour, and bravery of ſpirit.</hi> Good <hi>Man!</hi> He <hi>beleeves,</hi> what he thought he <hi>ſaw;</hi> But wanting the eye of faith to forſee this great <hi>Alteration,</hi> which he lived not to <hi>find;</hi> but <hi>We,</hi> now to <hi>feele:</hi> Our late <hi>gude Presbyterian Brethren, turne falſe Loones, and become the traiterous
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169833:59"/>Rebells to that reformation, which not long ago they profeſſed, &amp; he, &amp; others beleeved, and ſo diſunited the union of all our quiet, and happines.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 60. Scandal. upon E. of Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He tells us of a trick, that the <hi>Earle of Salisbury</hi> had, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with the <hi>Scots Courtiers,</hi> for their <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Fee-farmes,</hi> which they bought at 100. l. <hi>per annum</hi> for a <hi>thouſand pound.</hi> Then would he fill up theſe <hi>bookes</hi> with prime land, worth 20. <hi>thouſand pounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A pretty trick indeed to make himſelfe Lord <hi>Para-Mount,</hi> of the beſt lands in <hi>England;</hi> but it had bin a gainful <hi>trade</hi> of our <hi>Author,</hi> to have turn'd <hi>Informer</hi> to the <hi>State,</hi> in the <hi>particulars</hi> of theſe <hi>Tricks;</hi> and ſo the <hi>return</hi> of theſe <hi>lands</hi> ſo <hi>deceitfully got, would prove</hi> now as <hi>hard a bargain to his ſon</hi> (as the <hi>Lord-like purchaſers</hi> of <hi>Deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs have done</hi> latly) &amp; to his ſon, that may ſucceed him.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:169833:60"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are come to the conſideration of the third</hi> Remark <hi>in the</hi> Preface;
<note place="margin">Remar. 3.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 61. Robert Carre and Sir Tho. Overbury.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo we fall into the</hi> Hiſtory <hi>of</hi> Rob. Car, <hi>after</hi> E. <hi>of</hi> Summerſet, <hi>and intermixed with that of Sir</hi> Thomas Overbury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ro. Car,</hi> was a <hi>Scottiſhman,</hi> of no eminent <hi>birth,</hi> but a <hi>Gent.</hi> and had bin a <hi>Page</hi> of <hi>honor,</hi> to the King in <hi>Scotland.</hi> And in <hi>truth,</hi> he became the firſt <hi>Favorite</hi> that we find; that is, <hi>one whom</hi> the <hi>Ki. fancied, meerly</hi> for his <hi>faſhion:</hi> upon no <hi>other ſcore,</hi> nor <hi>plot</hi> of <hi>deſign.</hi> His <hi>Confident,</hi> was <hi>one</hi> Sr. <hi>Tho. Overbury,</hi> a <hi>man</hi> of <hi>good parts, whom our Author,</hi> hath well <hi>characterized;</hi> and his <hi>policy,</hi> was to <hi>pleaſe</hi> the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>intertaining</hi> them his <hi>Domestiques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was <hi>amongst other perſons</hi> of <hi>honor</hi> &amp; <hi>quality</hi> in <hi>Court, a young L.</hi> of <hi>great birth and beauty, Fra.</hi> the <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Tho. Howard,</hi> then E. of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> &amp; L. <hi>Treaſurer</hi> of <hi>Eng.</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in under-<hi>age,</hi> unto the <hi>late</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> E. of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:169833:60"/>
               <p>Of him, <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fame</hi> had an <hi>opinion (grounded upon his own ſuſpition)</hi> of his <hi>inſufficiency,</hi> to <hi>content</hi> a <hi>wife.</hi> And the <hi>effects of this Narration,</hi> with the <hi>ſequell</hi> of <hi>his life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> with <hi>his ſecond wife,</hi> is ſo <hi>notorious,</hi> as <hi>might ſpare me and the Reader our ſever all labours, for any other convincing arguments.</hi> But with <hi>his first,</hi> when <hi>both were of years, to expect</hi> the <hi>event</hi> and <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of their <hi>Marriage-bed;</hi> He was <hi>alwaies obſerved, to avoid the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> of <hi>Ladies,</hi> and ſo much <hi>to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect his own,</hi> that to <hi>wiſh</hi> a <hi>Maid</hi> into a <hi>Miſchief, was</hi> to <hi>commend her to my Lord</hi> of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> Which <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed</hi> the <hi>jealouſie</hi> of ſuch <hi>Men, whoſe interests were, to obſerve him;</hi> That he <hi>preferred the occaſion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to a ſeparation.</hi> And which indeed from <hi>publique fame,</hi> begat private <hi>diſputation,</hi> amongſt <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilians</hi> of the <hi>legality</hi> thereof, wherein thoſe <hi>Lawyers are bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:169833:61"/>
               <p>This Caſe followed the <hi>heeles</hi> of a former <hi>Nullity,</hi> freſh in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, between the L. <hi>Rich,</hi> and his <hi>fair Lady,</hi> by <hi>mutual conſent.</hi> But becauſe the E. of <hi>Dev. married</hi> her, <hi>whilſt her Husband lived,</hi> the King was ſo much <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> thereat, as it broke the E. heart: for his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> told him, That he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed a <hi>fair woman with a black ſoul.</hi> And this is a known truth, That before <hi>Viſcount Rochford</hi> (for ſo was <hi>Carre</hi> lately created) had made any <hi>addreſſe</hi> to this Lady, her own <hi>friends</hi> in <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> to her <hi>birth, expoſed</hi> her to the <hi>plaint</hi> of <hi>her Husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> &amp; to the <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt triall</hi> in a <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>judicature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 'tis as true, that the King <hi>knew</hi> hereof, our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> ſaies: [<hi>A party in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>udy buſineſſe</hi>] for, what was <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> for the <hi>meaneſt Subject,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamp. 77.</note> could not in <hi>juſtice</hi> be <hi>denied</hi> unto Her: Which in fine, <hi>ſentenced them both,</hi> by <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Canon, looſe from their <hi>Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall bands.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:169833:61"/>
               <p>And, becauſe the <hi>Nullity</hi> gave freedome to either, and ſo the means to the Counteſſes after-<hi>Mariage,</hi> with the ſad occaſions of all the ſequell miſhaps, and ſuſpected ſcandalls, ſo untruly expreſſed by the <hi>Pamphlet;</hi> I have with ſome diligence, laboured out the truth, preciſely and punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as it was acted, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Commiſſion <hi>Delegative;</hi> not eaſily now otherwayes to be brought to light.</p>
               <q>Upon Petition of the Earl of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke</hi> and his Daughter <hi>Francis</hi> to the King.
<note place="margin">Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of <hi>Nullity.</hi>
                  </note>
               </q>
               <p>That Whereas his Daughter <hi>Francis,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> had been <hi>Married</hi> many years, unto <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> in hope of comfortable effects to them, which contrarywiſe, by reaſon of certaine latent, and ſecretem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169833:62"/>and impediments of the ſaid <hi>Earl,</hi> diſabling him in the rights of <hi>Marriage,</hi> and moſt unwillingly diſcovered to him by his daughter; which longer by him to conceale, without remedy of Law, and the practice of all Chriſtian policy, in like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, might prove very prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore pray the King,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To commit this cauſe of <hi>Nullity</hi> of <hi>Matrimony,</hi> which ſhe is forced to proſecute againſt the ſaid <hi>Earl,</hi> to ſome grave and worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> as is uſuall, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Which accordingly was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto foure Biſhops, two Privy Counſellers learned in the Law, and to foure other Civill Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers; with Clauſe to proceed <hi>Cum omni, qua poterint, celeritate, &amp;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169833:62"/>expeditione, Summarie, ac de plano, ſine ſtrepitu, ac figura Judicii, ſola rei &amp; facti veritate inſpecta, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra aequitate attenta.</hi> And with this Clauſe alſo, <hi>Quorum vos praefat. Reverendiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patrem Cant. Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopum, Reverendiſſmum patrem Lond. Epiſcop. &amp; Iul. Caeſar. Mil. Aut duos veſtrorum, in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda ſententia, intereſſe volumus.</hi> But for ſome exceptions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Quorum</hi> by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners in the words <hi>ſententia eſſe,</hi> not <hi>intereſſe,</hi> A ſecond Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was granted and adjoyned two Biſhops more, with this <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Quorum ex vobis praefat. Re. Pa. Georg. Cant. Archiepiſ. Ioh. Lond. Epiſc. Tho. Winton Epiſc. Launcelot Elienſ. Epiſc. Richard Covent. &amp; Lichſ. Epiſc. Ioh. Roſſ. Epiſc. Iulio Caeſare, Tho. Parry Mil. in ferenda ſententia, tres eſſe volumus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this the <hi>Lady</hi> procures
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169833:63"/>Proceſſe againſt the <hi>Earl</hi> to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer her in a cauſe of <hi>Nullity</hi> of <hi>Matrimony.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Earle</hi> appears before the Commiſsioners, by his Proctor, And She gives in her <hi>Libell, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Earl</hi> and the <hi>Lady,</hi> ſix years ſince, in <hi>Ianuary Anno Dom.</hi> 1606. were <hi>Married,</hi> her age then thirteen, and his four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, and now ſhe is 22. and he 23 years old.</p>
               <p>That for three years ſince the <hi>Marriage,</hi> and he 18. years old, they both did cohabit as <hi>Married</hi> folke, in one bed naked and alone, indeavouring to have carnall knowledge each of others Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, the <hi>Earl</hi> neither did, nor could ever know her Carnally; he being before, and ſince, poſſeſſed with perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all incurable Impediment, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169833:63"/>Impotency, at leaſt in reſpect of her.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Lady</hi> was, and is apt, &amp; fit, without any defect, &amp; is yet a Virgin, and Carnally unknown by any man.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Earl</hi> hath confeſſed often times to perſons of great credit, and his neereſt friends, that he was never able Carnally to know her, though he had often attempted, and uſed his utmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</p>
               <p>And therefore prayeth the Commiſsioners upon due proof hereof, to pronounce for the <hi>Invalidity</hi> &amp; <hi>Nullity</hi> of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Earl</hi> by his Proctor, denies the ſaid Contents, <hi>Conteſtatio Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis negativè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Anſwer is required by Oath, by ſecond Proceſs, where,
<note place="margin">His An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oath.</note> in open Court his Oath was adminiſtred, with ſo great care,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169833:64"/>and effectuall words, to minde him of all Circumſtances, as the like hath been ſeldome obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Earl</hi> confeſſeth the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Viva voce.</hi>
                  </note> and Circumſtance, (as in the Libell.) And were not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent above three moneths, the one from the other, in any of the ſaid 3. years.</p>
               <p>That, for one whole yeare of the three, He did attempt divers times, carnally to know Her. But the other two years, he lay in bed with her nightly, but found no motion to copulation with Her.</p>
               <p>That in the firſt year, She ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed willingneſs, and readineſs thereto.</p>
               <p>That he did never carnally know Her, but did not find any impediment in himſelf, but was not able to penetrat or injoy Her.</p>
               <p>And beleeveth, That before and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169833:64"/>after the <hi>Marriage,</hi> he found in himſelf ability to other Women; and hath ſometimes felt motions that way.</p>
               <p>But being asked, Whether he found in himſelf a perpetuall, &amp; incurable Impediment towards Her? He anſwered, that in 2. or 3 years laſt, He hath had no motion to Her; and beleeveth, He never ſhall, nor that She is apt as other women: And that She is <hi>Virgo integra &amp; incorrupta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And confeſſeth, That He hath often, before Perſons of credit, confeſſed thus much.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this his Oath, She produced ſundry Witneſſes of the <hi>Marriage,</hi> Time, Age, Cohabitation at Bed and at Board; as before in the <hi>Libell, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then that period of time, limited by the Civill and Canon Law, proved his Cohabitation,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169833:65"/>and Condormition, for conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
               <p>The next was, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, She remained <hi>Virgo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra, incorrupta.</hi> But, becauſe the <hi>Earl</hi> beleeved not the <hi>Lady</hi> to be fit and apt for copulation, Therefore her Councell deſired, <hi>Matronas aliquas probas &amp; hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stas, fide dignas, &amp; in ea parte peritas, per dominos aſſignari, ad inspiciendum Corpus dictae domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon it was decreed,</p>
               <p>That ſix Midwives of the beſt Note, and ten other Noble Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, fearing God, and Mothers of Children, out of which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would chooſe 2 Midwives and 3 Matrons; and out of which the Delegates did ſelect 5. <hi>ut ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tune Domini viz. Arch. Cant. London: Elienſ: Coventry &amp; Lichf: Caeſer, Parry, Dun, Bennet, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169833:65"/>habita inter eos privata de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberatione, ex numero Matronarum praedict. eligerunt,</hi> The Lady <hi>Martha Terwhite,</hi> wife of Sir <hi>Ph: Terwhite,</hi> Baronet; the Lady <hi>Alice Carew,</hi> wife of Sir <hi>Mathew,</hi> the Lady <hi>Daliſon,</hi> wife of Sir <hi>Roger. Et in ſupplimentum Caſu earum impedire.</hi> The Lady <hi>Anne Waller</hi> Widdow, <hi>&amp; ex obſtetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum numero, &amp;c. Margaretam Mercer, &amp; Chriſtianam Cheſt. Et aſſignarunt procuratorem dictae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minae Franciſ. ad ſiſtendum cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Inspectatrices, coram Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendiſſimo patre Lond. Epiſc. Iulio Caeſar, &amp; Daniele Dun, &amp;c. Inter caeteros nominat. iſlo die, inter hor as quintam &amp; ſextam poſt meridiem, juramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hac parte ſubdituras, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inspectione facta fideliter rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas; earu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> judiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> juxta earu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et experientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dictis dominis, delegatis, ſic ut praefertur, aſſignatis, quam cito fieri poſsit,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169833:66"/>ante horam quartam, poſt meridiem diei Iovis prox. alioquin, ad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parendum, hoc in loco coram Comiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariis, dicto die lovis, inter horas quartam et ſextam poſt meridiem ejuſdem dici earum Iudicium in hac parte, tunc relaturas, et inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſendum diebus, hora &amp; loco, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective praedict, ad videndum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectatrices praedictas, Iuramento in hac parte enerari. Necnon quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliis diebus, hora &amp; loco per dictos Dominos Commiſſarios nominat, dictis inspectatricibus ad referend, earum Iudicium aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly, between the hours of five and ſix in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon that day, were preſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Delegates, <hi>London, Caeſar, et Dun;</hi> the ſaid Lady <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>white,</hi> Lady <hi>Carew,</hi> Lady <hi>Anne Waller, Margare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mercer,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Cheſt</hi> Midwives, ſworn <hi>ad Inquirend. &amp; Inſpect.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:169833:66"/>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the Lady <hi>Francis</hi> were a Woman, apt and fit for carnall Copulation, without any defect that might diſable Her to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether ſhe were a Virgin, unknown carnally by any man.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, they went from the preſence of the Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, into the next room, where the <hi>Lady</hi> was, accompanied then with the Councell of both ſides; into which room was no entrance but at one dore, whereout the Councell came forth, and only the <hi>Lady</hi> left with the ſaid women, who after ſome convenient time returned their report under their hands; the Commiſsioners having firſt ſequeſtred from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the Councell of the <hi>Earle</hi> and <hi>Lady,</hi> who had been preſent in all theſe paſſages, and all other perſons except the Regiſter, that ſo the Ladies and Midwives might
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169833:67"/>more freely deliver their ſecret reaſons, &amp;c. though it was not fit to inſert them in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
               <p>And this is their ſum of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That they believed the ſaid <hi>Lady</hi> fitted with abilities to have Carnall copulation, and apt to have Children.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That ſhe is a Virgin incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
               <p>And to coroborate all this, the <hi>Lady</hi> in open Court produced 7 women of her Conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</p>
               <p>That, in as much as the truth of all was beſt known to her ſelfe, She might by vertue of Her Oath ſhould be no further regarded, than it was confirmed by the oathes of theſe her kinſwomen.</p>
               <p>The Law preſuming that ſuch kindred ſhould be beſt acquainted
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169833:67"/>with the inward ſecrets of their kinſwoman.</p>
               <p>In order hereto, the <hi>Lady Francis,</hi> in open Court, had an Oath adminiſtred to her, with all the like grave admonition, as before to the <hi>Earl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo She affirmed;</p>
               <p>That, ſince the <hi>Earl</hi> was 18-years old, for three years, He and She had divers times layn naked in bed all night; And ſundry times there, the <hi>Earl</hi> had attempted, and indevoured to conſummate <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> with her, &amp; She accordingly yielded, and willing thereto, and yet he never had Copulation with Her.</p>
               <p>And then theſe ſeven Noble Women, <hi>viz. Katherine</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Suffolke, Francis</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Kildare, Elizabeth</hi> Lady <hi>Walden, Elizabeth</hi> Lady <hi>Knevet,</hi> Lady <hi>Katherin Thinn,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Katherine Fines,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Dorothy
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169833:68"/>Neal,</hi> her Kinſwomen, being char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Court to ſpeak with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality what they beleeved as to the <hi>Ladies</hi> depoſition, they did all depoſe, that they believed the ſame to be true.</p>
               <p n="1">1 And in particular. That <hi>poſt plenam pubertatem utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> they both endeavoured Copulation.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That notwithſtanding this Cohabitation, and ability on his part <hi>per Inſpectatrices,</hi> ſhe remained a Virgin incorrupted.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That the <hi>Earl</hi> had Judicially ſworne, that he never had, nor could, nor ſhould ever know her carnally.</p>
               <p>And this the Law being, That <hi>Impotentia coeundi in viro,</hi> howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, whether by naturall defect, or accidentall means, and whether abſolute towards all, or reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to his wife alone; If it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede <hi>Matrimony,</hi> and be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, as by Law is preſumed,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169833:68"/>when by 3 yeares continuance, after the Mans age of 18 years, there having been <hi>nil ad copulam,</hi> the <hi>Marriage</hi> not conſummated. the Law allowing the ſaid proofs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was abundantly ſufficient to convince the ſaid <hi>Earle</hi> of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency.</p>
               <p>Becauſe, <hi>Canonum Statuta cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diri debent ab omnibus; &amp; nemo in actionibus, vel judiciis Eccleſiaſticis, ſuo ſenſu, ſed eorum authoritate duci debet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid Reverend, and grave Judges <hi>Delegates,</hi> gave this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence unanimouſly, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idcirco nos Epiſcopi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in dicta cauſa Iudices, Delegati, &amp; Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarii, Chriſti Nomine (primitùs) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocato, &amp; ipſum ſelum Deum, oculis noſtris praeponentes, et habentes, de<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> et cum conſilio Iuriſperitor cum quibus in hac parte communicavimus; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turéq, deliberavimus, praefatum Domi.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169833:69"/>num Comitem Eſſex, dictam dominam Franciſcam, ob aliq uod latens, &amp; incurabile impedimentum perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; praedictum contractum, &amp; ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizationem, praecedens, citra ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zationem, et contractum praedictum, nunquam carnaliter cognoviſſe, aut carnaliter eandem, cognoſcere potuiſſe, aut poſſe, et eundem dominum Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad carnale copulam, cum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem domina Franciſca, exercend omnino inhabilem, et impotentem fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe, et eſſe: Pronunciamus, decerni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus et declaramus praefatum praeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Matrimonium, ſic inter praedict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um virum Robertum Devoreaux, Comitem Eſſex, Et praedictam praenobitem faeminam, Franciſcam Howard, de facto contractum, et ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnizatum, Omniaque exinde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia, ratione praemiſſorum, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino invalidum, ac nullum, nulla fuiſſe, et eſſe, viribuſque juris caru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe, et carere debere; atque nullo et aullis; et invalido et invalidis;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:169833:69"/>ad omnem Iuris effectum, ettamque pronunciamus, decernimus et declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, dictum matrimoniumpraetenſum, omnia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex inde ſequentia, caſſamus, anullamus, &amp; irritamus; Memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamque</hi> Dominam Franciſcam Howard, <hi>ab aliquo vinculo, huiuſmodi praetenſi Matrimonii, inter</hi> Eam, <hi>&amp;</hi> dictum dominum Robertum Comitem <hi>(ut praefatur) de facto contracti, &amp; ſolemnizati,</hi> liberam, <hi>&amp;</hi> ſolutam <hi>fuiſſe, &amp; eſſe. Et ſic tam</hi> liberam, <hi>&amp;</hi> ſolutam <hi>inſuper pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciamus, decernimus &amp; declaramus. Eademque</hi> dominam Franciſcam, <hi>ab eodem</hi> domino Comite Eſſex, <hi>quoad vinculum Matrimonii prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſi praedicti, omnia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex inde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia,</hi> liberandam &amp; divortian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>fore debere, pronunciamus, &amp; ſic liberamus, &amp; divortiamus; eoſdem quo ad tranſitum ad alias nuptias, conſcientiis ſuis, in domino relinquere per hanc noſtram</hi> ſententiam deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitam, <hi>ſive hoc noſtrum</hi> finale
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169833:70"/>decretum, <hi>quam ſi ve, quod</hi> ſecimus, <hi>&amp;</hi> promulgamus <hi>in his ſcriptis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe <hi>Records</hi> extant, doe mention the proceedings (you ſee) modeſt and legall; parallell with any former of the like kind, though our <hi>Pamphleter</hi> with his baudy tale, pleaſeth himſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame thoſe <hi>Reverend Biſhops,</hi> whoſe dignities gave them place of Judges; acting no more, or otherwayes, than the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Canons in ſuch caſes preſcribe. <hi>Nemine contradicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes ſayes He <hi>[Archiſhop Abbot,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 78.</note> who was therefore excluded the Councell Table, and ſo dyed in diſgrace of that King, though in favour with the King of Kings.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is otherwiſe. For the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> (providence permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) ayming with a Croſſebow to ſtrike a <hi>Deere,</hi> kill'd his Game keeper; for which Act, having
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169833:70"/>His hand in blood, by the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> he cannot be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to officiate at the Altar; and ſo, He not being admitted to the full uſe of his ſpiritual <hi>calling;</hi> Himſelf forbore the <hi>Councell Table,</hi> as He told me in theſe words. <hi>[Since they will have it ſo, that I am uncapable of the one, I ſhall ſpare my ſelf the trouble of the other.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he enjoyed the benefit of that <hi>See,</hi> whilſt he lived, and retyred in that time (moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant) to his <hi>Palace at Lambeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Much diſpleaſed he was (as I well remember) with the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Clergy;</hi> and upon that <hi>Score.</hi> And, forſooth, to juſtifie, that his <hi>Function</hi> was not weakned, by his <hi>Miſchance,</hi> quarrelling with the <hi>Canons,</hi> he fell upon down-right <hi>Puritan Tenents;</hi> which gave occaſion to many <hi>Diſcontents</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> to viſit him
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169833:71"/>ſo frequent, that they called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Nicodemites,</hi> and his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I obſerved very often, perhaps therefore, (for I could not meet with a better reaſon) that the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> conſtantly with <hi>Candell light</hi> in his Chamber and Study, made it <hi>Midnight</hi> at <hi>Noon day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here he began to be the <hi>firſt Man</hi> of Eminency in Our <hi>Church,</hi> a <hi>Ringleader</hi> of that <hi>Faction,</hi> for I can name thoſe, then his private <hi>Diſciples,</hi> which lately appear deſperate <hi>Proſelites.</hi> And thus He lived,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> but <hi>[died not in diſpleaſure of King James]</hi> for the <hi>Phamphlet</hi> perſwades us after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to believe <hi>[him to be the Kings confeſſor]</hi> living long after in the late Kings time, from whom no evill <hi>Reſentment</hi> could paſſe in relation to this former <hi>Story;</hi> it being buried in Oblivion
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169833:71"/>to <hi>Him</hi> and all good Men, till that Our <hi>Pamphletter,</hi> rakes in the <hi>Embers,</hi> to light His owne <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, after all the former <hi>proceedings,</hi> and the <hi>Nullity</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, a <hi>Marriage</hi> was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized, with Viſcount <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> then <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, here I ſhould be unwilling to proſecute this <hi>Story;</hi> but our <hi>Pamphletters</hi> foule mouth leads me back to Maſter <hi>Copinger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mr. <hi>Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinger.</hi>
                  </note> whoſe birth, breeding and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour deſerves no leſſe of fame, than to leave him quiet in the ſilent Grave. <hi>[But He knew Him otherwiſe deſerving.]</hi> I am ſure many men now living know, that Our <hi>Author</hi> may give himſelfe <hi>Copingers Character;</hi> faces about, and in truth you have Him to a haires bredth.</p>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Copinger</hi> had been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, Maſter of a larger fortune,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169833:72"/>which yet, fell not ſo low, <hi>[as to turne Baud for want of better maintenance]</hi> Indeed he was entertained a <hi>Dependent</hi> on <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> a <hi>favourite,</hi> and <hi>Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> and ſo no diſhonour, for Him, or other Men, of better Ranke, and Birth, than Our Authors family, to be near atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo great a <hi>Perſon,</hi> as Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of his Bed Chamber; and thereby, the more proper to be truſted, with the Secrets and Civilities of his <hi>Maſters lawfull Affection,</hi> and addreſſe to ſo <hi>great a Lady;</hi> which might then, well become Him, or any other honeſt Man to <hi>advance;</hi> and I may believe, he afforded the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency <hi>[of His own houſe for their meeting and conſent of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage]</hi> which was not long after ſolemnized with much honour and magnificence.
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbury.</hi>
                  </note> And Sr. <hi>Thomas Overbury,</hi> congratulating the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169833:72"/>Ceremony, with as publique profeſſion as others in Court ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. And it concerned this great <hi>Favourite,</hi> to look upon <hi>Him</hi> with reſpect of preferment; and as he failed not the <hi>meaneſt,</hi> ſo it became Him, to advance his <hi>Confident Overbury,</hi> moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent.
<note place="margin">Pamph. 65.</note> (Whoſe <hi>Character</hi> Our <hi>Pamphletter hath more deſervedly hit upon, than any other.</hi>)</p>
               <p>And therefore, it was his own <hi>ſeeking,</hi> as beſt fitting his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent parts,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> to preſent the <hi>Kings Perſon</hi> in <hi>Embaſſie</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> which to my knowledge he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and ſeemingly prepared to advance.</p>
               <p>Conceiting, perhaps, that the power which he uſurped over <hi>Somerſet;</hi> and the <hi>Intereſts of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affection,</hi> (which <hi>Overbury</hi> knew beſt how to <hi>Maſter</hi>) could not endure <hi>abſence,</hi> without much <hi>regret,</hi> which accordingly had for
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169833:73"/>ſome time, the true <hi>effects,</hi> as <hi>Overbury</hi> intended.</p>
               <p>But when <hi>Somerſet</hi> had wiſely conſidered, that there would be no great loſs of ſo looſe a friend; Then <hi>Overbury would not goe;</hi> no, though I know his <hi>Inſtructions were drawn, and Additionalls thereto, by his own conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was a <hi>just,</hi> and true <hi>ground,</hi> for the <hi>King and Councell,</hi> to puniſh ſo great Inſolency, with <hi>Impriſonment</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> which <hi>Somerſet</hi> heartily endeavoured in due time to <hi>releaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Overbury</hi> (to ſhadow his own demerits,) deviſed the <hi>reaſon and cauſe,</hi> from his diſaffection of the former <hi>Marriage,</hi> and which he publiſhed, with much <hi>diſhonor, though not the tythe which is ſtudied in our Pamphleters Libell.</hi> For which, the <hi>Malice of Women,</hi> (as it often meets) ſought <hi>Revenge</hi> by <hi>Poyſon,</hi> to puniſh him, to the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169833:73"/>
                  <hi>death.</hi> And for which <hi>Fact, they</hi> were <hi>arraigned,</hi> and ſome ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In proſecution of which, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoved the Kings <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to be <hi>ſevere</hi> and <hi>ſerious,</hi> without [any <hi>King-craft.</hi>] And therefore needed not ſuch an additionall falſehood [<hi>as to kneel down to the Iudges]</hi> when then, as uſuall he gave them their <hi>Charge,</hi> upon their <hi>Itinerate Circuits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For then, the truth of <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buries poyſoning</hi> was but <hi>ſuſpected;</hi> And therefore it was not <hi>unnaturall</hi> nor <hi>wonderous [for the King to take his leave of his Favorite and friend, with expreſsions of great kindneſs]</hi> who yet in <hi>Iuſtice</hi> he expoſed to <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, in this much <hi>forced story</hi> of our Author, take him at his own <hi>dimenſion,</hi> an ingenious good Nature, may find out much <hi>strugling</hi> in the <hi>King,</hi> to make
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169833:74"/>
                  <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy, kiſs each other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was preſent at their <hi>Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and the <hi>[Pictures, Puppets, for Magick ſpells]</hi> were no other, but ſeverall French Babies, ſome Naked, others Clothed; which were uſuall then, and ſo are now a dayes, to teach us the faſhions, for dreſſe of Ladies <hi>tyring</hi> and <hi>apparrell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed <hi>[Foremans Book was brought forth]</hi> wherein the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanck</hi> had formerly for his own advantage and credit, ſawcily <hi>[inſerted the Counteſſes name, ſo of many others that came to ſeek For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes]</hi> which ſhe cleared by her own <hi>Protestation,</hi> and <hi>Foremans confeſsion,</hi> that ſhe was never with him.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Monſon</hi> was brought to the Bar,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
                  </note> and began his <hi>Tryall,</hi> but was remitted to the <hi>Tower,</hi> with as much <hi>Civility,</hi> as is uſuall to other <hi>Priſoners.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:169833:74"/>
               <p>And Sir <hi>Geo. More</hi> then <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of the <hi>Tower,</hi> took him from the <hi>Bar,</hi> and both together were carried in his <hi>Coach</hi> to the <hi>Tower.</hi> I ſay the truth, for I ſaw it.</p>
               <p>But I cannot pick out the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, why <hi>[ſo much pains is taken to tell out Monſons tale]</hi> was he Guilty, or No? By the ſtory, he had hard meaſure. So perhaps had ſome of the others; for <hi>He</hi> was a <hi>Creature</hi> of that <hi>Family.</hi> And yet for ſome (no doubt) pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reſpects of our <hi>Author</hi> (for he was his Companion) He is in, and out, and out, and in, and in, and out again.</p>
               <p>And now comes <hi>Somerſet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 115.</note> who he ſayes <hi>[being warned to his tryal, abſolutely refuſed, and was aſſured by the King, never to come to any]</hi> when was this aſſurance? For he tells us, <hi>[At their parting at Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, they never met after]</hi> but we muſt conceive it by <hi>Meſſage.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:169833:75"/>
               <p>And why for this, muſt <hi>[More a wiſe man be at his wits end?]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The warrant for <hi>Tryall</hi> came o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver night late; and it is ſo <hi>uſual</hi> as it never <hi>failes,</hi> that the <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Tower</hi> hath freedome of acceſſe <hi>[to waken his Soveraign]</hi> at any hour.</p>
               <p>The importance of his <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> having that conſequence annexed. And in ſpeciall to give <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>Warrants,</hi> either of <hi>Tryalls,</hi> or of <hi>Execution</hi> of <hi>Priſoners.</hi> And this, of <hi>Courſe</hi> he did. <hi>[When the King in tears, is told a tale in his Eares]</hi> that none knew, but he that was furtheſt off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>[A trick of wit brings him to the Barre, and a deſperate plot by two men placed at his Elbow, with Clokes to clap over him, made him calm at his Tryall]</hi> And thus it was, that the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> on his right, and the <hi>Gentleman Iaylor</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:169833:75"/>on his left hand, with <hi>Clokes</hi> on their backs, <hi>[but not on their armes]</hi> might colour our Authors conceipt.</p>
               <p>It had appeared a mad <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> when a <hi>Priſoner</hi> at his <hi>tryall,</hi> upon Life and Death, hath Freedome to ſpeak for himſelf, in publique Courſe of Juſtice, <hi>[to be ſnatch'd from the Bar, and from the power of the Iudge, at the pleaſure of a Iaylor.]</hi> But to make out this Monument,] <hi>the King rewards him with</hi> 1500 l.]
<note place="margin">Pamph. 119.</note> And for a truth [<hi>More tells all this to the Author, of whom</hi> (him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſes) <hi>he had no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his honesty</hi>] nor I beſeeve any body elſe.</p>
               <p>The Concluſion of all is, That due execution was done upon Sir <hi>Iervice Ellowayes,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Turner, Weston</hi> and <hi>Franklyn. Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſon</hi> cleared, the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169833:76"/>
                  <hi>Earl reprieved, [our Author and moſt men cleer him of the Poyſon, and condemn him only in the high point of friendſhip, for ſuffering his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment]</hi> which he could not releaſe, And the Counteſſe only guilty of connivance.</p>
               <p>And now comes this.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Prefacers</hi> 3. <hi>Remarke</hi> to the <hi>Iudgment Seat</hi> for ſentence. Let him pick out a greater <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> in any <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> more <hi>Remarke,</hi> than this of the King, to make good this His former <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> wherein by the way He may take leave, to be allowed, His <hi>owne</hi> even <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> both.</p>
               <p>Which no doubt, hath found acceptance at <hi>Gods Tribunall,</hi> in behalfe of <hi>Him and His, His</hi> own death being <hi>Ordinary,</hi> not forced by any <hi>Poyſon.</hi> And <hi>His poſterity in due time, by our Saviours merits, ſhall be gathered up in the myſtery of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169833:76"/>everlaſting ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by the way how ſmoothly we are told a Story of the <hi>Pittifull Palſgrave [how He Married a Kings Daughter, with much joy,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 82 <hi>Palſgrave</hi>
                     </note> and great miſfortune to all the Princes of Chriſtendom; but fayling of that, and all the rest, how He was caſt out, He and His, to beg their bread,</hi> But <hi>had His Father-in-law been half ſo wiſe,</hi> (with our Authors good Counſell to boot) and had He bought ſwords, with a quarter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of words, <hi>He had bin</hi> —] What? As his Sonne that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds him; <hi>Palſgrave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we haſten;
<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Henry.</hi>
                  </note> having much matter to meddle with, confuſedly put together in our <hi>Pamphlet;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The 4th. Remarke in the Preface.</note> which wee muſt take leave to <hi>ſeparate, for each ſingle ſtory:</hi> and Re-mind back, the death of that <hi>Heroick Prince</hi> HENRY (in the midſt of <hi>Somerſet's Greatnes) [Who had he liv'd to have bin King
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:169833:77"/>would no doubt</hi> (with our Authors leave) <hi>have been ſo gracious as to leave alive,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 85</note> one</hi> HOWARD, <hi>to piſſe againſt the Wall.</hi>] When as with reverence to His <hi>Memory,</hi> it was a notorious truth, that He made Court to the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> of <hi>Eſſex</hi> before any other <hi>Lady</hi> then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <p>But He is dead, <hi>[and poyſoned too, as we ſhall have it in his following diſcourſe]</hi> and yet ſpeaks not one word more of Him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prince Henry</hi> was borne in <hi>Scotland,</hi> at <hi>Striveling Caſtle,</hi> in <hi>February</hi> 1594. the firſt ſonne unto <hi>King</hi> JAMES and <hi>Queene</hi> ANNE.</p>
               <p>His breeding, apted his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Inclination,</hi> to all <hi>Exerciſes</hi> of <hi>Honor,</hi> and <hi>Arts</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> which gave him <hi>fame,</hi> the moſt exquiſite, hopefull <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:169833:77"/>
               <p>In the nineteenth yeare of his <hi>Age,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> appeared the firſt <hi>Symptome</hi> of <hi>change;</hi> from a full round face, and pleaſant diſpoſition, to be <hi>paler</hi> and <hi>ſharpe,</hi> more ſad and retired; often complaining of a <hi>giddy heavineſſe</hi> in his <hi>for-head.</hi> Which was ſomewhat eaſed, by <hi>bleeding</hi> at the Noſe; and that ſuddenly ſtopping, was the firſt of his <hi>diſtemper,</hi> and brought him to extraordinary qualms, which his Phyſicians recovered, with Strong waters.</p>
               <p>About this time, ſeverall <hi>Ambaſſadors Extraordinary,</hi> being diſpatched home, He retired to his Houſe at <hi>Richmond;</hi> pleaſantly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Thames River;</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited him to learn to ſwim, in the <hi>Evenings</hi> after a ful <hi>ſupper:</hi> the firſt immediate pernicious <hi>cauſe</hi> of ſtopping that gentle <hi>flux of blood,</hi> which thereby putrifying, might ingender that fatall <hi>Feaver</hi> that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:169833:78"/>accompanied Him to his Grave. His active Body, uſed violent <hi>Exerciſes;</hi> for at this time, being to meet the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Bever,</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> he rode it in two dayes, neer a hundred miles, in the extremity of heat in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. For he ſet out early, and came to Sir <hi>Oliver Cromwells</hi> neer <hi>Huntingde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> by ten a clock before Noon, neer 60 Miles, and the next day bet mes to <hi>Bever,</hi> 40 Miles.</p>
               <p>There, and at other places, all that <hi>Progreſs,</hi> He accuſtomed to <hi>Feaſting, Hunting</hi> and other <hi>sports</hi> of <hi>Balloon</hi> and <hi>Tennis,</hi> with too much <hi>violence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now returned to <hi>Richmond,</hi> in the Fall of the Leaf, He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained afreſh of His <hi>pain</hi> in the <hi>Head,</hi> with increaſe of a meager complexion, inclining to <hi>Feveriſh;</hi> And then for the rareneſs thereof called the <hi>New diſeaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:169833:78"/>
               <p>Which increaſing;
<note place="margin">Takes His Chamber,</note> the 10th of <hi>Octob.</hi> He took His Camber, and began Councel with His <hi>Phyſician</hi> Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> an honeſt and worthily learned Man. Three dayes after He fell into a looſneſs (by cold) 15 times a day.</p>
               <p>Then removes to <hi>London,</hi> to St. <hi>Iame's</hi> contrary to all adviſe. And (with a ſpirit above his Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) gives leave to His <hi>Phyſician</hi> to go to his own home.</p>
               <p>And ſo allowes Himſelfe too much liberty, in accompanying the <hi>Palſgrave,</hi> and Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> (who was come hither up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Fame</hi> to ſee him) in a great Match at <hi>Tennis</hi> in His <hi>Shirt,</hi> that winter ſeaſon, his looks then preſaging <hi>ſickneſs.</hi> And on <hi>Sunday</hi> the 25 of <hi>Octob.</hi> He heard a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> The text in <hi>Iob; Man that is born of a Woman, is of ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and is full of trouble.</hi> After that, He preſently went to <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:169833:79"/>and heard another <hi>Sermon</hi> before the King, and after dinner being ill, craves leave to retire to his own <hi>Court,</hi> where inſtantly he fell into ſudden ſicknes, faintings; and after that a ſhaking, with great heat and <hi>Head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ach,</hi> that left Him not,
<note place="margin">And His Bed.</note> whilſt He had <hi>Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſtantly He takes His <hi>Bed,</hi> continuing all that night in great <hi>drought</hi> and little reſt; The next day <hi>Head ache</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, his Body coſtive, pulſe high His water thyn and whitiſh.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Mayern</hi> preſcribes Him a <hi>Gliſter;</hi> After which he roſe, playd at Cards, that, and the next day: But looked pale, ſpake hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, dead ſunk eyes, with great drought.</p>
               <p>And therefore Mr. <hi>Naſmith</hi> ſhould have let him blood by <hi>Mayerns</hi> Counſell. But the other <hi>Phyſicians</hi> diſagreeing it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd; yet He roſe all this day,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169833:79"/>had His fit, firſt cold, then a dry greatheat.</p>
               <p>On his 4th. day comes Doctor <hi>Butler,</hi> (that famous Man of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi>) who approved what had bin miniſtred, gave hopes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and allowed of what ſhould be given Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mayern, Hammond</hi> and <hi>Butler,</hi> deſired the aſſiſtance of more <hi>Doctors;</hi> but the <hi>Prince</hi> would not, to avoid <hi>confuſion</hi> in <hi>Counſell.</hi> His Head-ache, drought, and other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents increaſed.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Evening</hi> there appeared 2. hours after Sun ſet, <hi>A Lunar Rainbow, directly croſs over the Houſe, very ominous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 6.7. increaſing His di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe.</p>
               <p>The 8th. His <hi>Phyſicians bleed the Median of his right arm,</hi> 8. <hi>ounces,</hi> thin and putride: After which He found eaſe, with great hopes; and was viſited by <hi>King, Queen,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:169833:80"/>Duke, Palſgrave,</hi> and <hi>Siſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 9th. worſe than before;
<note place="margin">His diſeaſe</note> and therefore, Doctor <hi>Atkins,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted their <hi>opinions, That his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe was, a corrupt putrid Feaver; ſeated under the Liver, in the firſt paſſage. The Malignity, by reaſon of the Putrefaction, (in the higheſt degree) was venemous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 10th. increaſing Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, greater ravings, and Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver violent. And therefore <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern</hi> adviſed more <hi>bleeding:</hi> But the reſt would not; but applyed <hi>Pigeons</hi> and <hi>Cupping glaſſes,</hi> to draw away the pain.</p>
               <p>The 11th. ſmall hopes, All accidents violently increaſing, no applications giving eaſe. His <hi>Chaplains</hi> continuing their daily <hi>Devotions</hi> by His Bed ſide. The <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Melborn,</hi> Dean of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and others, with whom He daily prayed.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:169833:80"/>
               <p>The 12. No hope. The King with exceſſive grief, removes to <hi>Kenſington Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were added Doctor <hi>Palmer,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Guifford,</hi> all imaginable helps, <hi>Cordialls, Dia. phoretick and Quinteſſentiall ſpirits;</hi> &amp; a <hi>water</hi> from Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> Priſoner in the Tower: all theſe were by <hi>Conſent adminiſtred;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut any effect.</p>
               <p>And ſo He died at 8 a Clock at night, Friday the 6.
<note place="margin">His death.</note> of <hi>November</hi> 1612.</p>
               <p>The Corps laid upon a Table,
<note place="margin">Corps laid out,</note> the faireſt, cleereſt and beſt proportioned, without any ſpot or blemiſh.</p>
               <p>The next day was ſolemnly appointed, for imbowelling the Corps, in the preſence of ſome of the <hi>Counſell,</hi> all the <hi>Phyſicians, Chirurgions, Apothecaries,</hi> and the <hi>Palſgraves Phyſician.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the true Copy of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:169833:81"/>their view,
<note place="margin">And view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſicate.</note> under their hands as followeth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Skin,</hi> as of others, <hi>Blac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Skin,</note> but no way ſpotted with <hi>Blackneſſe,</hi> or <hi>Pale</hi> marks, much leſſe purpled, like Flea bites, could ſhew any <hi>Contagion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>Peſtilenticall Venome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the place of His <hi>Kidnies,
<note place="margin">Kidnies.</note> Hipps,</hi> and behind His <hi>Thighs,</hi> full of redneſſe; and becauſe of his continuall lying upon his <hi>back,</hi> his <hi>belly</hi> ſomewhat <hi>ſwollen,</hi> and ſtretched out.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Stomach</hi> whoſe &amp; handſom,
<note place="margin">Stomach.</note> within and without; having never in all his ſickneſſe, been troubled with vomiting, lothing or yelping; or any other accidents which could ſhew any <hi>taint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Liver</hi> marked with ſmall ſpots above;
<note place="margin">Liver.</note> and in the Lower parts, with ſmall lines.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Gall Bladder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gall.</note> void of any humour; full of wind.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:169833:81"/>
               <p>The <hi>Spleen</hi> on the top,
<note place="margin">Spleen.</note> and in the lower end, blackiſh, fill'd with black heavy blood.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Kidnies</hi> without any blemiſh.
<note place="margin">Kidnies.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Midriſe,</hi> under the Filme or Membraine,
<note place="margin">Midriffe,</note> containing the <hi>Heart</hi> (wherein a little moyſture) ſpotted with black leadiſh colour by reaſon of the bruſing.
<note place="margin">Heart.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Lungs,</hi> the greateſt part black,
<note place="margin">Lungs.</note> the reſt all ſpotted with black, imbrewed and full of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſt blood, with a corrupt, and thick Serocity, which by a vent made in the <hi>Lungs,</hi> came out fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in great abundance. In which doing, and cutting a ſmall Skin, which invironeth the <hi>Heart</hi> to ſhew the ſame, the <hi>Chirurgian</hi> by chance cutting the Trunck of the great Veine, the moſt part of the blood iſſued out into the Cheſt, leaving the lower Veins empty; upon ſight whereof, they concluded an <hi>extream heat</hi> and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:169833:82"/>fullneſſe; &amp; the ſame more appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the windpipe, with the Throat &amp; Tongue,
<note place="margin">Throat.</note> were covered with thick blackneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Tongue</hi> cleft and dry in many places.
<note place="margin">Tongue.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>hinder Veins</hi> called <hi>Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mater,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Piamater.</note> in the Inmoſt Filme of the <hi>Braine,</hi> ſwolne, abundance of blood, more than naturall.</p>
               <p>The Subſtance of the <hi>Braine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Braine.</note> faire and clcere; but the ventricks thereof, full of cleere water, in great abundance, which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred by reaſon of the <hi>Feaver Maligne,</hi> divers humors being gathered together, of a long time before. He not being ſubject to any dangerous Sickneſſe by Birth.</p>
               <p>The other part,
<note place="margin">Without poyſon.</note> by reaſon of the Convulſions, reſoundings and benummings, and of the fullneſſe, choaking the naturall hear, and deſtroying the vitalls,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:169833:82"/>by their <hi>Malignity, have convayed Him to the Grave without any teken or accident of Poyſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His admirable patience, in all his ſickneſſe, might deceive the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> never dreaming dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Urines</hi> ſhewd none. And the unknown ſtate of His greateſt griefe, lay <hi>cloſely rooted in His head,</hi> which in the opening was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               <p>But the Picture of <hi>Death</hi> by a ſtrange extraordinary Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, from the beginning,
<note place="margin">And vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing him, hath been the cauſe, that ſome vainely rumored, that <hi>He was Poyſoned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But no Symptome appearing,
<note place="margin">By ſent.</note> it is ſurmiſed, that He might be <hi>Poyſoned</hi> by a <hi>Sent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But indeed, <hi>He died in the Rage of a Malicious Extraordinary Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Fever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeventh of <hi>December,</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:169833:83"/>He was Interred at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 1612.</p>
               <p>His Motto's <hi>Fax mentis, Honeſtae Gloria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juvat ire per Altum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was comely <hi>tall;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</note> five Foot eight Inches high; <hi>Strong</hi> and well made; ſomewhat <hi>broad Shoulders;</hi> a ſmall <hi>Waste, Amiable</hi> with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">and</note> His <hi>Haire</hi> Aborn colour. Long <hi>Faced,</hi> and broad <hi>For-head,</hi> a pearcing grave <hi>Eye;</hi> a gracious <hi>Smile;</hi> but with a <hi>Frowne, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Courteous</hi> and <hi>affable;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Character.</note> naturall <hi>Shamefaſt</hi> and <hi>modest. Patient</hi> and ſlow to Anger. <hi>Mercifull</hi> and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious in puniſhing offendors. <hi>Quick</hi> to conceive, yet not raſh. Very conſtant in reſolves. Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull <hi>ſecret</hi> of any <hi>truſt,</hi> even from his <hi>Youth.</hi> His <hi>Corage Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, fearleſs, noble, undaunted;</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there ſhould be nothing impoſſible to Him, that had bin
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:169833:83"/>
                  <hi>done</hi> by another. Moſt <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Proteſting His great <hi>deſire</hi> to compoſe <hi>differences</hi> in <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word; He was never heard, by any body living to <hi>ſwear</hi> an <hi>Oath,</hi> And it was remembred at his <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sermon</hi> by the Archbiſhop, that He being commended by one for not replying with paſſion in <hi>Rlay,</hi> or <hi>ſwearing</hi> to the <hi>truth;</hi> He ſhould anſwer, That He knew no <hi>Game,</hi> or <hi>Value</hi> to be won or loſt, that could be worth an <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſay no more, <hi>Such and ſo many were His Virtues, that they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are told by our Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet <hi>[that his death was foretold by Bruce,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 85</note> who was therefore baniſhed]</hi> And if ſo, he deſerved rather to be hanged.</p>
               <p>But in truth, He was not ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at all, but wiſely remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:169833:84"/>himſelf into <hi>Germany,</hi> where his Profeſſion of <hi>Propheſying</hi> gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt profit. And from whence all Chriſtendome are fill'd with ſuch <hi>lying foretellings.</hi> But in this particular he needed not much <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Devills</hi> help to ſay <hi>[That Salisburies crazy body ſhould yeeld to Nature before Prince Henry's.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this true ſtory of Prince</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 86</note> 
                  <hi>may anſwer the fourth Remarke in the Preface, that he came not to untimely death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram.</hi> Sir <hi>Lionell Cranfield.</hi>
                  </note> and Sir <hi>Lionell Cranfield,</hi> our Pamphlet couples upon the ſcore of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants;</hi> though the latter being of merit and was rank'd with the Peers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ingram</hi> was bred a <hi>Merchant,</hi> and for his wit and wealth imployed as a <hi>Cuſtomer:</hi> and afterwards came to that eſteem, as to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred <hi>Cofferer</hi> in the <hi>Kings houſe;</hi>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:169833:84"/>and with much <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> ſo to be. For the vaſt expence of the <hi>State,</hi> kept the <hi>Treaſury</hi> dry; Eſpecially, the needfull <hi>diſburſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> divided into <hi>Severalls,</hi> of <hi>King, Queen, Prince, Princeſs, and Palſgrave, and Duke.</hi> And at this time alſo of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and, who more proper to aſſiſt (the <hi>Revenue</hi> failing) but ſuch able men as theſe; who could, and honeſtly might, diſcover the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craft of the coſening <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant.</hi> And it was high time ſo to doe, or the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gros'd all the <hi>wealth</hi> of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> beſtowes on them the Characters <hi>[of evill Birds deſiling their own Neſts]</hi> what is our <hi>Anthor</hi> then?
<note place="margin">Pamph. 87</note> 
                  <hi>who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil'd the Court that gave him bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, defamed the King that gave him hread?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this I know, That the <hi>King</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:169833:85"/>moſt prudent, put this courſe in <hi>practice</hi> at <hi>Court</hi> (ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering I confeſs in the Line of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> to the <hi>Houſhold preferment,</hi> which riſes by <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</hi>)</p>
               <p>This Man Sir <hi>Arthur Ingram</hi> a <hi>ſtranger</hi> in <hi>Court,</hi> ſtept in to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the <hi>concealments</hi> of the <hi>Green Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> alſo, and when this Tyde had its Ebb, it returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to its wonted Chanell. And 'tis true, that the <hi>King</hi> ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the fault upon his <hi>Favorit. An ordinary fate, which of ten fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows them, to beare the burthen of their Maſters miſtakes.</hi> Which yet was but an <hi>Experiment,</hi> proper enough for the <hi>Lord Chamberlain</hi> to put in practice.</p>
               <p>He being layd aſide,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Lionell Cranfield.</hi>
                  </note> Sir <hi>Lionell Craufield</hi> came into publick, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch like <hi>Deſign,</hi> but in a <hi>nobler way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I find him of an antient Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:169833:85"/>in <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> as by their bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Arms in the Heralds office appears.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Gentleman,</hi> a Brother unto Sir <hi>Randall Cranfield,</hi> who inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited his fathers poſſeſsions <hi>there,</hi> and in other <hi>Counties,</hi> of good <hi>value;</hi> And in <hi>Kent;</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Our <hi>Authors habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was bred, a <hi>Merchant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and by his extraordinary qualities, and the bleſsing of God upon his <hi>indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> in that moſt commendable way of <hi>Adventure,</hi> (beſides his great underſtanding in the affairs of the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi>) became uſefull to the <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt, had the honour of <hi>Knighthood;</hi> then the <hi>Cuſtody</hi> of the Kings <hi>Wardrobes;</hi> afterwards <hi>Maſter of the Court of Wards and Liveries;</hi> and laſtly ſucceeded <hi>Suffolke,</hi> in the place of <hi>Treaſurer</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:169833:86"/>of <hi>England;</hi> and in that time, created <hi>Earle of Middleſex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all which Offices of <hi>Truſt;</hi> I never knew <hi>then,</hi> nor can find <hi>ſithence,</hi> any ſuſpicion, unleſſe in that of the <hi>Treaſury. The ground whereof is hinted unto us by our Author.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 166.</note> But in truth, in this He hath but <hi>Scumm'd the Pot,</hi> to <hi>cleere the Broth.</hi> For indeed, who more fit (for the reaſons I have ſhewed) than this man of <hi>experience,</hi> in Stating the <hi>Accompts,</hi> for the <hi>Revenues</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> which I know he improved, and not unlikely <hi>thereby,</hi> purchaſed <hi>Envy</hi> for his <hi>Eminency.</hi> And to ſay truth, according to his <hi>Place,</hi> He did indeavor to <hi>Husband</hi> the ſame <hi>to piece out with the expence,</hi> which the <hi>Princes Iourney</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> had wonderfully and unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily <hi>exhauſted;</hi> as by the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accompt</hi> thereof lately divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Parliament,</hi> doth manifeſtly
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:169833:86"/>appeare. Then which no better <hi>Evidence</hi> can be produced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> together with what the <hi>Pamphletter</hi> publiſhes as a ſuppoſed crime,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 166.</note> 
                  <hi>[His refuſall to ſupply that journey and Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams folly and prodigality;]</hi> and this <hi>[He did deny]</hi> as the duty of his Office required, and which He well underſtood, as being <hi>[of Counſell and acted as a Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in that undertaking] to My knowledg;</hi> and as indeed being then the Stateſman at the <hi>Counſell</hi> Table.</p>
               <p>But his refuſall of <hi>ſupplying Buckingham,</hi> upon that <hi>Score only,</hi> wrought him (no doubt) at his returne home, the <hi>Treaſurers</hi> great enemy.</p>
               <p>And whom He oppoſed <hi>[a ſmall accuſation might ſerve the turne, to turne any Man out of all]</hi> as He did, Him.</p>
               <p>And yet to the Honour of his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:169833:87"/>
                  <hi>Memory;</hi> though they raked into all his <hi>actions,</hi> and <hi>racked</hi> all mens <hi>diſcoveries,</hi> to the <hi>height</hi> of <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> the power of <hi>Buckingham</hi> could never produce any <hi>Crime,</hi> (though mightely attempted) againſt his <hi>exact accompts, in that boundleſſe truſt of the tempting Treaſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in ſpite of <hi>Malice,</hi> though they diveſted him of that <hi>Office,</hi> yet He lived long after in <hi>Peace, Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Houour;</hi> And died ſince theſe times of inquiry, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to his <hi>Heire, his Honors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taint; with a plentifull Eſtate to all his Children; enabling them to beare up the worthy Character of their Fathers meritts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, having digreſſed in our <hi>matter</hi> beyond our <hi>time;</hi> we returne to the firſt <hi>appearance</hi> of our <hi>new Favorite,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>George Villiers,</hi> 89 His di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent.</note> George Villiers,</hi> who was of an Ancient <hi>Family</hi> in <hi>Leiceſterſhire.</hi> His Father Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:169833:87"/>Villiers,</hi> begat him, upon a ſecond <hi>Wife, Mary Beomont,</hi> of <hi>Noble birth;</hi> whom for Her <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> He <hi>Married.</hi> He had by Her three Sonnes, <hi>Iohn Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Purbeck, George Duke of Buckingham,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Earle of Angleſey;</hi> and one <hi>Daughter, Suſan Counteſſe of Denbigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Pamphlet</hi> tells us.
<note place="margin">Page. 90.</note> 
                  <hi>[That He came over by chance, from his French Travells; and ſought his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in Mariage with any body, but mist of his match, for want of a hundred Marks Ioynture.]</hi> And ſo pieces him for the Court (like in the Story of <hi>Dametas Capari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>) borrowing of every one <hi>piecemeal,</hi> to put him forward for the <hi>Kings Favourite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth is thus, His <hi>Mother</hi> a <hi>Widdow,</hi> was lately Married unto Sir <hi>Thomas Compton,</hi> ſecond <hi>Brother</hi> to the <hi>Lord Compton;</hi> who by chance falling upon a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:169833:88"/>match (for matchleſs wealth) with <hi>Alderman Sir John Spencers</hi> Daughter and Heir.</p>
               <p>And his Father then lately dead, this <hi>Lord</hi> was <hi>Maſter</hi> of all, which was of more than credible; and ſo might be enabled bountifully to ſet up a <hi>Kinſman,</hi> without help, or alms of the <hi>Pariſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it was plotted long before, and <hi>Villiers</hi> ſent for to the ſame purpoſe. And this indeed, was done by practice of ſome <hi>Engliſh Lords.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I can tell him the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place.</hi> There was a great, but private <hi>Entertainment</hi> at Supper, at <hi>Baynards Caſtle,</hi> by the Family of <hi>Herberts, Hartford</hi> and <hi>Bedford,</hi> and <hi>ſome others;</hi> By the way in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street,</hi> hung out <hi>Somerſets picture,</hi> at a Painters Stall; which one of the <hi>Lords</hi> envying, bad his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>ſling dirt in the face;</hi> which he did: and gave me occaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:169833:88"/>to ask my Companion upon what <hi>ſcore</hi> that was done. He told me, That this meeting would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. And truly, I waited neer, and opportune, and ſo was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Deſign,</hi> to bring in <hi>Villiers.</hi> And thus backt. <hi>[Our new Favourite needed not to borrow, nor to ſeek out many Bravo'es to ſecond his Quarrels,]</hi> which at firſt, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs he met with.</p>
               <p>For, having bought the place of <hi>Cup bearer</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> his right was, to have the upper end of the <hi>Table,</hi> at the reverſion of the <hi>Kings Diet;</hi> only during his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethly wayting. But he, not ſo perfect a <hi>Courtier</hi> in the <hi>Orders</hi> of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> ſet himſelf firſt (out of his month) when it was not his due; and was told of it, and ſo removed: which was not done with over much <hi>kindneſſe;</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the <hi>Other</hi> was <hi>Somerſets Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:169833:89"/>
               <p>But not long after, this party by chance, (rather than by deſigne) ſpilt upon <hi>Villiers</hi> cloaths, as he carried meat to the <hi>Kings Table;</hi> and returning to Dinner, <hi>Villiers</hi> gave him a <hi>box</hi> on the <hi>Eare;</hi> For which the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of the <hi>Court</hi> was to have his hand cut off, and which belonged to <hi>Somerſet, as Chamberlain,</hi> to proſecute the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Favorite.</note> as he did. And here the <hi>Kings</hi> mercifull <hi>pardon,</hi> without any ſatisfaction to the party, made him appear a <hi>Budding Favorite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now we are fallen upon a ſtory <hi>[of fooling and fidling]</hi> ſometime uſed for <hi>Courtlike recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations</hi> I confeſſe;
<note place="margin">Pamph. 91.</note> but alwayes, with ſo much <hi>wit</hi> as might well become the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of an <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biers.</hi>
                  </note> which our Author miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrues, and calls <hi>[a Brothelry] to uſher in the New Favorite, and to out the Old One,</hi> (whoſe Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes with his Lady, brake out,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:169833:89"/>even now as we have told of before.</p>
               <p>And now indeed,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 124.</note> all the browſe boughs cut downe, or removed, to plain the <hi>Stemm;</hi> our <hi>Favorite</hi> appears, like a <hi>proper Palm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His firſt ſtep into honourable <hi>Office,</hi> was in the <hi>Admiralty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admiralls.</note> to ſucceed a good and gallant <hi>Old Lord</hi> of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> who being almoſt <hi>Bed ridd,</hi> made ſute to the King, That himſelf might diſpoſe his place, as a <hi>Legacy,</hi> in his life time upon <hi>Villiers:</hi> which was ſo done; and who, to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, went in <hi>Perſon</hi> to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the <hi>Kindneſſe,</hi> and preſented his <hi>Young Lady,</hi> with a very <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>valuable reward,</hi> which my <hi>Lord Compton paid for,</hi> and beſides a <hi>Penſion</hi> therefore, during his life. And all this was done with ſo much <hi>love</hi> and <hi>liking,</hi> that I have often obſerved <hi>Villiers</hi> his great
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:169833:90"/>Civility to him ever after, at each meeting to call him <hi>Father, and bend his knee,</hi> without the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of the <hi>Lord,</hi> that <hi>gained</hi> more than he loſt by the <hi>bargain,</hi> and did not coſt the <hi>King a penny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe Sir <hi>Robert Manſell</hi> (a dependant of <hi>Nottingham</hi>) had the place of <hi>Vice-Admirall</hi> at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure only; <hi>Villiers</hi> (for his Lords ſake) continued him by <hi>Patent, during life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which <hi>Courteſie,</hi> the good <hi>Old man</hi> came himſelf to give thanks, (as I remember) the laſt <hi>Complement his age gave him leave to offer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus was this <hi>Office</hi> of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Safety to the Kingdom, <hi>Ordered</hi> from the Command of a decrepid old Man to a proper young Lord, and ſtrengthned with the abilities of an experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Aſsiſtant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 124.</note> without deſerving the leaſt quarrelling <hi>Item,</hi> of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:169833:90"/>our <hi>Carping Pamphleter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next in our way,
<note place="margin">Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor <hi>Eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                  </note> is that of the Lord <hi>Egerton,</hi> He was <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of England,</hi> a man very aged, and now with ſickneſſe fallen on his <hi>aeath-bed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 125.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Term</hi> come, and the <hi>Scal to be diſpoſed,</hi> In order thereunto, the <hi>King</hi> ſent <hi>Secretary Winwood</hi> (not <hi>Bacon</hi>) for the <hi>Seal,</hi> with this <hi>Meſſage, That himſelf would be his under keeper,</hi> and <hi>not to diſpoſe it whilſt he lived, to bear the name of Chancellor.</hi> Nor did any receive the <hi>Seale,</hi> out of the Kings ſight, till <hi>Egerton</hi> was <hi>dead,</hi> which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſoon after.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> ſucceeded him in the <hi>Chancery.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor <hi>Bacon.</hi>
                  </note> He was <hi>Attorney Generall,</hi> and as others by that <hi>Place,</hi> and the uſuall way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment (time without memory) come to high <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> either in <hi>Chancery,</hi> or to the other <hi>Benches,</hi> ſo did he riſe.</p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:169833:91"/>
               <p>He was a man of Excellent parts, of all other learning, as of that of the <hi>Law;</hi> and as proper for that <hi>place</hi> as any man of the <hi>Gown.</hi> His <hi>merits</hi> made him ſo then, which in after time his <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> blemiſhed, and he juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to his private <hi>Studies,</hi> which <hi>render</hi> him to the world full of <hi>worth:</hi> and with the ſmall <hi>Charity</hi> of our <hi>Author,</hi> might merit the <hi>Bayes,</hi> before any <hi>Man of that age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we ſhall ſpare our labor, to obſerve his entrance into that Honor; <hi>by the idle Meſſage from Buckingham,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 127.</note> made up only by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors mouth. [Who tells us of his grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, heighth and pride. Particularly intimated afterwards to the King in Scotland,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 131.</note> by Letters from Winwood, which the King read unto our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.]</hi> At which [he ſayes, <hi>they were very merry.</hi>] Good God! The King opens his <hi>boſome</hi> to him, at
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:169833:91"/>that inſtant (not uſuall to any of the <hi>Green-cloth</hi>) when this <hi>Man,</hi> ſo vilely ſtudied, and plotted his <hi>Soveraigns,</hi> and that <hi>Kingdoms diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> for which he was turned out of the <hi>Court.</hi> Was the King ſo gracious to him, &amp; he ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, then, and ſince, in the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet to defame him, and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity? <hi>He that eats of his bread, lifts up his hand to deſtroy him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And afterwards we are told his downfall: <hi>which he ſays, at laſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him to a</hi> Horſe boy.</p>
               <p>He did (as became him to do to the Houſe of Peers) proſtrate <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> and <hi>ſins,</hi> which ingeniouſly he <hi>acknowledged,</hi> craving <hi>pardon</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Them,</hi> promiſing with <hi>Gods</hi> mercy to <hi>amend his life;</hi> which he made good to the <hi>worlds Eye.</hi> Thoſe excellent <hi>works</hi> contrived in his <hi>Retirements,</hi> dee manifeſt.</p>
               <p>And let me give this <hi>light</hi> to His <hi>better Character;</hi> from an <hi>obſervation</hi>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:169833:92"/>of the <hi>late King,</hi> then <hi>Prince;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from hunting, He eſpied a Coach, attended with a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Troop of <hi>Horſemen,</hi> who it ſeems were gathered together, to wait upon the <hi>Chancellour</hi> to his Houſe at <hi>Gorembury,</hi> at the time of his <hi>declenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At which, the <hi>Prince</hi> ſmiled; <hi>Well! do we what we can, ſaid He, This Man ſcornes to go out like a Snuffe.</hi> Commending his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>excellent parts;</hi> not without ſome regrett, that ſuch a <hi>Man</hi> ſhould be <hi>falling off.</hi> And all this, much differing from <hi>Our Authors Character of Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe times are complained of.
<note place="margin">Pamph. 129.</note> 
                  <hi>[What baſe courſes our Favourite took to raiſe moneys for advance of his beggerly Kindred.]</hi> Heretofore we are told, that the <hi>Great Men maſtered all:</hi> &amp; now, the affairs are <hi>Managed</hi> with <hi>beggerly fellows;</hi> &amp;
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:169833:92"/>concludes againſt himſelfe, that <hi>Riches make Men Cowards, and Poverty Valiant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis true, <hi>Plenty</hi> makes Men <hi>Proude,</hi> and <hi>Induſtry</hi> brings a <hi>Man</hi> to <hi>Honour.</hi> Had our <hi>Author</hi> lived to <hi>theſe</hi> our <hi>dayes,</hi> and obſerved as much now, as he pried into then; He muſt have ſpoke other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; unleſſe (as likely He could) hold with the <hi>Hare,</hi> and run with the <hi>Hounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We all know the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham</hi> had many <hi>Kindred,</hi> for his <hi>Family were Antient.</hi> And diſperſed by time, into ſeverall <hi>Matches with the Gentry;</hi> who no doubt, did addreſſe to the <hi>Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi> for preferment. And what ſtrange, or new device was it in Him, to raiſe them, that were neere in Blood, by <hi>Noble</hi> and worthy wayes, as he did; and if our Author had liked, to lick after the <hi>Kitchen-maid,</hi> had
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:169833:93"/>it been handſome for a <hi>Kinſman,</hi> to have <hi>kickt</hi> at his <hi>kindneſſe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 129, 130.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Good God, what a Summary Bead-roll of <hi>Penſioners</hi> are liſted in our <hi>Authors Account;</hi> Sure He became <hi>Regiſter,</hi> to the <hi>Revenue</hi> of that <hi>Rabble. Chancellour, Attorney, Deans, Biſhops, Treaſurers, Rich and Poore,</hi> raking upon the rates of <hi>Offices, Biſhopricks, Deaneries with Fines and Penſions.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſayes <hi>It had been impoſſible that three Kingdomes could have Maintained His Beggerly Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>but He muſt tell us,</hi> He made them all Lords, w<hi rend="sup">ch.</hi> got him much haued. He did ſo, and he did <hi>well.</hi> He made his two <hi>Brothers Peers,</hi> his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Siſter Counteſſes,</hi> the reſt of his kindred, by his Countenance, got means to live like their <hi>Birth-rights,</hi> being a <hi>Race Handſome and Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:169833:93"/>
               <p>And yet let me tell him, I have been often preſent, when it hath been urged <hi>as a Crime to this great Man, the neglect of his owne;</hi> when the diſcourſe hath been preſt, <hi>for preferment of his Freinds.</hi> And this I know, for I acted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. The Late <hi>King in honour of Buckinghams Memory</hi> ſupplied the neceſſities of his <hi>Kindred,</hi> which his untimely death left without ſupport.</p>
               <p>As for the baſe Obſervations, through and through the <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet,</hi> though I liv'd in the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of the <hi>Court reaſonable years,</hi> to ſee many <hi>turns</hi> of <hi>State;</hi> Yet I confeſſe, my time other wayes <hi>diverted,</hi> than to rake after ſo much <hi>Ribaldry,</hi> and <hi>beaſtly baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery,</hi> as now to queſtion this his <hi>peeping, pimping,</hi> into each <hi>Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat Placket;</hi> and for his ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency therein, he might have been made <hi>Master</hi> of the <hi>Game.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:169833:94"/>
               <p>In <hi>Bacons</hi> place,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 139. Doctor <hi>Williams</hi> Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> comes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment <hi>Doctor Williams</hi> (by the title of <hi>Keeper of the Seal,</hi> during pleaſure, which the <hi>Chancellor</hi> hath for life.) He was alſo <hi>Dean of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and <hi>Eiſhop of Lincolne;</hi> brought in (ſayes he) <hi>[to ſerve turns, to do that, which no Layman was ſound bad enough to undertake.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Former <hi>Ages,</hi> held it more <hi>conſonant to Reaſon,</hi> to truſt the <hi>Conſcience of the Clergy,</hi> with the <hi>Caſe of the Layman</hi> they beſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Caſe of Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And antiently, the <hi>Civill Law</hi> was allwayes judged by the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church:</hi> and the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> and <hi>Courts of Equity,</hi> in charge of a <hi>Divine Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ran that <hi>Channell,</hi> till <hi>Bacons Father had it from a Biſhop,</hi> and now a <hi>Biſhop</hi> has it again.</p>
               <p>And had <hi>King Iames</hi> lived to have effected his deſires, the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> had fixed firm footing in <hi>Courts
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:169833:94"/>of Iudicature,</hi> (out of the rode of the <hi>Common Law.</hi>)</p>
               <p>And this was the true <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Williams Initiation</hi> thither. How he fell from <hi>that,</hi> and other his wayes <hi>ſince,</hi> from <hi>worſe to worſt of all,</hi> we leave him, if he be <hi>living, to lead a better life, and make a Godly end, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis no new matter to tell us,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 143. <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Match. Fift Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</note> That the <hi>Spaniſh Ieſuit</hi> is more than our <hi>Match</hi> in the intricate way of <hi>Treaty,</hi> being enabled to <hi>Out-wit</hi> us and all the <hi>world</hi> beſides. Of which we made <hi>tryall,</hi> upon <hi>truſt</hi> of our <hi>Emiſſaries,</hi> and now the <hi>King</hi> was minded to put it to the <hi>touch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo reſolved, That the <hi>Prince,</hi> with <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington,</hi> and a domeſtick of the <hi>Dukes,</hi> ſhould hazard a <hi>Iourney</hi> into <hi>Spain;</hi> Being invited thither by <hi>ſecret Intimation of Sir Walter Aſton, Ambaſſador Extraordinary,</hi> with the <hi>Earl of Briſtow, Leiger.</hi> Which was
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:169833:95"/>to put period to that buſineſs of a <hi>Marriage,</hi> that had laſted long enough in <hi>Deſign,</hi> to weary both <hi>Parties.</hi> Nor was it held ſuch a <hi>Ranting journey</hi> by wiſe Men, that knew more perhaps, than our <hi>Author</hi> would make us beleeve he did.</p>
               <p>For the great buſines <hi>Incluſive</hi> with the <hi>Match,</hi> was to get <hi>Render</hi> of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> which this <hi>way,</hi> or <hi>none,</hi> was to be expected.</p>
               <p>And it appeared afterwards, That though the <hi>Spaniard</hi> did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, yet he had other <hi>Overtures</hi> with the <hi>Houſe of Auſtria,</hi> as a <hi>double bow-string.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which, we ſuſpected before; and therefore it was a <hi>Prince-like boldneſſe,</hi> to bring it to iſſue by <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> or to break the <hi>Bonds</hi> aſunder. Which at his being <hi>there,</hi> he ſoon <hi>diſcovered,</hi> and ſo retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>Wherein, <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> a ſuſpected
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:169833:95"/>
                  <hi>Penſioner</hi> to that <hi>State,</hi> did not ſo timely unmask the <hi>Spaniſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells,</hi> to the <hi>Princes advantage,</hi> as he might and ought to have done. For which neglect, it had like to have coſt him his <hi>life,</hi> when he came <hi>home</hi> to the true <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But evermore we muſt expect a <hi>bawdy tale</hi> in our <hi>Authors</hi> ſtories.
<note place="margin">Pamp. 146.</note> Which, to all <hi>Men</hi> that know the retired <hi>cuſtome</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh Wives</hi> (much more of the <hi>Grandees Ladies</hi>) from converſing, or ſight of <hi>their owne,</hi> either <hi>kindred,</hi> or <hi>friends,</hi> (much more of ſtrangers) muſt needs diſcredit this <hi>Tale</hi> of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> with <hi>Olyvares Counteſs,</hi> as abſurd and feigned.</p>
               <p>Nor hath our <hi>Author,</hi> either <hi>Courtſhip</hi> or <hi>Civill</hi> breeding other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to underſtand, what the <hi>Princes</hi> behaviour ſhould have been, towards ſo great a <hi>Perſon</hi> as the <hi>Infanta of Spain:</hi> but to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:169833:96"/>him, his <hi>cap cap on his head, and prevacy in her Cabinet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But above all the ſtrains of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency,</hi> Give me leave to marke out the <hi>Inſamy</hi> which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (oh horrid!) to caſt on <hi>King James;</hi> as of many other which he aſperts him, ſo this <hi>Sans-parell;</hi> intimating thus much, [<hi>That, not glutted with the blood of his dear,
<note place="margin">Pamph. 149.</note> and eldeſt Sen (that moſt incomparable) Prince Honry, for whoſe death he ſhould cunningly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with a feigned ſorrow. So now to adde to that, and for hatred to Buckingham</hi> (whom the world know he could have blaſted with his breath) <hi>He ſhould think it no ill bargain, to loſe this Prince, his only Son, and Succeſſor to all his Crowns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to illuſtrate the Kings wearineſſe of <hi>Buckingam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 150.</note> he tells us a <hi>Tale</hi> of the <hi>Lieger Spanish Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador Marqueſa d'Innocoſſa,</hi> and a
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:169833:96"/>Spaniſh Confeſſor, <hi>Padre Maieſtre,</hi> which he ſayes, <hi>was ſent to reveal to the King, what he had received under ſeal of Confeſsion, and on pain of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation never to utter) which was,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="153"/> That the King ſhould be Murthered by Buckingham, or ſome body elſe,</hi> (or no body at all.)</p>
               <p>Then, <hi>The Kings paſsion hereupon,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="154"/>(without any other proceeding, to ſecure his own life, that was ſo fearfull to loſe it.)</p>
               <p>And then, <hi>That the Duke being challenged with the truth, durſt not fight in his own defence;</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, had he bin ſo wicked to deſigne, the <hi>Devil</hi> might have aſſiſted him with <hi>courage to</hi> have <hi>countenanced</hi> it.</p>
               <p>Indeed,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>155</label> there was a Letter of <hi>Complaint</hi> ſent to <hi>Spain,</hi> by advice of the <hi>whole Councell</hi> here, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of that <hi>King,</hi> how far he had Commiſſioned his <hi>Ambaſſdor</hi> in an affair of <hi>Conſequence,</hi> which
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:169833:97"/>Letter was incloſed and returned to him, with peremptory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to give <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Duke:</hi> or to be ſubject to worſe <hi>Conſtruction.</hi> Which to my knowledge the Ambaſſador did recant, (for I copyed the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions;) and with much adoe, begg'd favour of the <hi>Prince,</hi> to be reconciled, upon <hi>ſulmiſsion;</hi> which the <hi>Prince</hi> in Honor was pleaſed to accept, or it might have coſt <hi>Innocoſſa</hi> his head, at his <hi>comming home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former ſtory is interlaced,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>151</label> with Obſervation; [<hi>How Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hamſhifted from truſting the King, as knowing his deſire to be rid of him. And ſo the Duke wrought himſelf into the Princes poor ſpirit, with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret of the old King, and every body elſe, Eſpecially, when he ſhould rather have call'd to mind, the bravery of his brother who hated the whole Family, although, he ſayes, none of them
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:169833:97"/>had ever offended him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly, <hi>Euckingham</hi> was not in <hi>beeing,</hi> when <hi>Prince Henry</hi> died; And if he were, he was more <hi>brave</hi> indeed, than to hate the Family that never did him hurt. But ſure our Author meant, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſets Ladies Family</hi> Howards; For he tells us before, <hi>That Prince Henry would not leave one of them to piſſe against the wall</hi> (the Male ones he means.)</p>
               <p>And taking occaſion before, to ſmell out ſomething of <hi>ſuſpition of Poyſon in Prince Henries death;</hi> we are promiſed in his <hi>page</hi> 84.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>84</label>
                  <hi>that his diſcourſe following will tell you the truth thereof,</hi> and yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeaks word of him, no more, nor otherwiſe than in this place.</p>
               <p>Our Author proceeds, and ſays,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>156</label>[<hi>Now that we have heard, what made the King hate Buckingham, wee ſhall know the reaſon of Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:169833:98"/>extreme hatred to the King, which is believed to be the cauſe of his ſo ſpeedy death.</hi>]</p>
               <p>More poyſon yet?</p>
               <p>But firſt we proceed to the ſtory <hi>of Yelverton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>H.
<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>156</label> Yelverton,</hi> was <hi>Attorney Generall;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir <hi>H. Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verton.</hi> Attorney Gener all.</note> and by his place of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,</hi> it was his duty to <hi>manage the charge of Impeachment againſt Somerſet,</hi> or any Subject whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, without diſpute: which he refuſed, as receiving that <hi>place</hi> by his <hi>Favour;</hi> and this <hi>contempt</hi> to the <hi>Kings ſervice,</hi> (not without ſuſpition of <hi>concealment</hi> of ſome paſſages concerning <hi>Overburies death</hi>) He was for thoſe <hi>Reaſons,</hi> (and deſervedly) by the <hi>whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> committed to the <hi>Tower, cloſe Priſoner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where (we are to be perſwaded [<hi>the Lieutenant Balfore, admits the Dake to treat with him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and then, to peece out a
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:169833:98"/>Peace between them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly <hi>Yelverton</hi> had Law to teach him, or any other <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that this was <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in <hi>Balfore,</hi> and in the Duke to attempt. And therefore to cleer it, <hi>Balfore</hi> himſelf hath vowed to a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> ſometime under his <hi>Guard,</hi> that there was never any ſuch <hi>act done</hi> by the Duke, or by his permiſſion to any body elſe.</p>
               <p>But afterwards, upon <hi>Yelvertons</hi> humble ſubmiſſion, for his former fault; and his Innocency cleared in the other <hi>ſuſpitions;</hi> he was ſet at liberty. And in truth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the merit of the <hi>Man,</hi> other wayes, he was afterwards truſted with the <hi>Judgement Seat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what was this ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, which we are told he ſhould tell the Duke, [<hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, That which the King ſpake in
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:169833:99"/>Parliament [not to ſpare any that was deareſt or lay in his boſome, by which he pointed to you; (meaning the Duke.)]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And muſt <hi>Buckingham</hi> adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his, and the Lieutenants head to learn this <hi>News,</hi> which no doubt the <hi>Duke</hi> heard before, being then at the KING's <hi>Elbow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>161</label> After this impertinent <hi>digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> (or great ſecret) he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers (which none ever dream'd of) a wonderfull [<hi>failing of the Spaniards both wiſdom and gravity</hi>] And why? gravity?) forſooth. [<hi>That</hi> (which had bin againſt all Humanity, Comerce and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Nations) <hi>the Spaniard miſt of the advantage, to impriſon the Prince</hi>] a ſure pledge (no doubt) for the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to have gotten the <hi>Heir-dome</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this he tells us for truth,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:169833:99"/>
                  <hi>[out of their own confeſſions]</hi> But they were caught with a trick <hi>[having the Princes faith, and his Proxy to boot, remaining with Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, which might coſen them into this kindnes, to let him come home again]</hi> Where at <hi>a Conference of both hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parlament, Briſtoll is blam'd,</hi> and (it being truth) <hi>the Prince owns</hi> it, and <hi>Briſtoll</hi> is ſent for by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (otherwiſe it had bin pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Treaſon in him to return home from his Commiſsion.)
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>163</label>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi> (he ſayes) <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades</hi> Briſtolls <hi>return,</hi> as <hi>doubting the ſucceſſe,</hi> (as well he might, knowing him to be his <hi>Penſioner</hi>) <hi>who for his ſake is like to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, he being come, and convented before the Parliament, endeavors to cleer himſelf, with a ſingle Copy of a Paper (and a bawdy tale to boot) againſt</hi> Buckingham, <hi>but forbore to tell it out, for offending their chaſt Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:169833:100"/>
               <p>In this,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>165</label> the Author is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious; as to be judged by the Reader, <hi>what a horrible wound,</hi> Briſtoll <hi>gave the Prince or</hi> Buckin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham? and yet by his Confelsion the wiſdome of the <hi>Houſe</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Briſtoll to the <hi>Tower, but ſome dayes after (not the next day) he was ſet at liberty, nor durſt any bring him to further tryall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was committed for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and might have lain there longer, Priſoner; But the Duke made means for his <hi>Releaſe,</hi> leſt it ſhould move a <hi>jealouſie,</hi> that it was his deſigne thereby to delay the Tryall. Which, to my knowledg, was earneſtly purſued, by the Duke, and had that Parliament laſted, might have been a dear bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for <hi>Briſtoll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Parliament,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>168</label> our Author obſerves [<hi>the Princes early hours to act by, where</hi> (he ſays) <hi>he diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo much juggling, to ſerve his
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:169833:100"/>own ends, that being afterwards come to be King, he could not affect them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A notable Note, he calls that Parliament <hi>Iugglers,</hi> and gives it a <hi>reaſon,</hi> why the late <hi>King</hi> muſt needs diſaffect all other <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> that ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>Then have we a diſcovery of our Authors owne making,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Pamph. </seg>169</label> which is intended (he ſays) <hi>as a caution to all States men,</hi> with a ſingular Commendation of the wiſdome of the late Earl of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury,</hi> (whom before through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Pamphlet he loads with ſingular diſgraces.)</p>
               <p>He tels us of a Treaty hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with <hi>Spain,</hi> for a <hi>Match</hi> with Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> where the jugling was diſcovered, that there was no ſuch <hi>intention.</hi> And that the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> the Favorite of <hi>Spain,</hi> leavs the Spaniſh <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> here in the lurch to anſwer for all; who
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:169833:101"/>in a great ſnuff, againſt thoſe that ſent him hither, proſtrates his Commiſsion and letters of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, (under the King his Maſters hand and ſeale) at the foot of our Councell Table; and ſo returnes home, (and yet was not hanged for his labour) but liv'd and died, <hi>bonus Legatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, our author having hunted the King hitherto; <hi>blowes</hi> his <hi>death</hi> at <hi>parting;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pam. 171. King <hi>James's</hi> Sickneſs.</note> which he ſayes <hi>[began with a Fever; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a poyſoned Plaiſter, applyed by</hi> Buckingham. <hi>For which being queſtiond the very next Parliament, it was haſtily diſſolved for his ſake, only to ſave his life.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the entrance of the <hi>Spring,</hi> the King was ſeized with a <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Ague;</hi> which to another <hi>Conſtitution</hi> might not prove <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilentiall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all Men then knew his
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:169833:101"/>Impatience in any pain, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes utter <hi>Enmity</hi> to any <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</hi> So that nothing was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, to give him <hi>eaſe</hi> in his <hi>ſits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which at length grew <hi>violent,</hi> and in thoſe <hi>Maladies,</hi> every one is apt to offer advice, with ſuch <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> as have been <hi>helpfull</hi> unto <hi>others;</hi> and in truth, <hi>thoſe</hi> as <hi>various,</hi> as the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> is <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So it was remembred (by a <hi>Noble, vertuous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> and <hi>untaint La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> for <hi>Honour and Honesty,</hi> yet living) of a preſent eaſe, by a <hi>Plaiſter</hi> approved upon ſeverall <hi>Perſons,</hi> which, becauſe the <hi>Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients</hi> were <hi>harmleſs</hi> and <hi>ordinary,</hi> it was forthwith compounded, andready for <hi>application;</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſerious <hi>reſolution,</hi> to preſent it to the <hi>Phyſicians conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>King,</hi> fallen into <hi>ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> about <hi>Noone</hi> the <hi>Phyſicians</hi>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:169833:102"/>took opportunity to retire, having <hi>watch'd</hi> all <hi>Night,</hi> till that Time.</p>
               <p>When in the interim of their abſence, the <hi>King</hi> wakes, and falls from a change of his Fit, to timelier effect, than heretofore it uſually happened; which to allay, this <hi>Playſter</hi> was offered, and put to his <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it wrought no <hi>mitigation,</hi> and therefore it was removed by the <hi>Doctors.</hi> Who being come, were much offended, that any <hi>One</hi> durſt aſſume this boldneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their <hi>conſents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by <hi>Examination,</hi> they were aſſured of the <hi>Compoſition,</hi> and a peece therof eaten downe by the <hi>Counteſſe</hi> that made it; and the <hi>Playſter</hi> it ſelfe then <hi>in being,</hi> for further <hi>tryall</hi> of any <hi>ſuſpition of poyſon.</hi> Which, if not <hi>ſatisfactory,</hi> it muſt, and ought to <hi>lodge</hi> upon their <hi>ſcore.</hi> Sir <hi>Mathew Liſter,</hi> Doctor <hi>Chambers,</hi> and others,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:169833:102"/>who were afterwards examined herein, with very great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to clear that calumny, and are yet living, to evince each <hi>ones ſuſpition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was, indeed, remembred the next <hi>Parliament</hi> following; and whereof the <hi>Duke</hi> was accuſed, as a <hi>Boldneſs unpardonable;</hi> But in the Charge, (which as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>Littleton Managed,</hi> at a <hi>Conference</hi> in the <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi>) it was not urg'd as <hi>poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous,</hi> but only <hi>criminous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But [<hi>ere the King dyed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pamph. 174.</note> it is told us, <hi>That Buckingham was accuſed to his face, by an honeſt ſervant of the Kings,</hi> (name him if you can) <hi>who valiantly tript up the Dukes heels</hi> (that his pate rung Noone) for which, <hi>he call'd upon the gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping King</hi> (no body being by) <hi>for Juſtice.</hi> And though ſpeechleſſe, we are told, <hi>what he would have ſaid,</hi> viz. <hi>Not wrongfully accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>]</p>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:169833:103"/>
               <p>And here obſerve;
<note place="margin">Pamph. 175.</note> he makes <hi>Archbiſhop Abott</hi> the <hi>Kings Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsor</hi> at his death; who before, he ſayes (pag. 78.) <hi>lived in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and excluded the Counſell Table. And dyed in diſgrace of this King on Earth,
<note place="margin">175.</note> but in favour of the King of Kings. [Biſhop Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams, then Lord Keeper, was the other Confeſsor]</hi> and in the mouths of two Witneſſes conſiſts the Truth. What regrett and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie remaines then in our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> heart? that ſome <hi>Miſchief</hi> ſhould lye hid in the ſecrets of the <hi>Sacrament of Confeſſion;</hi> which he could not learn, to out-live the Honour and Fame of his <hi>Sacred Soveraign?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How hath our <hi>Author</hi> patch'd up a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> of <hi>State Notions,</hi> pick'd up from the <hi>Gleanings</hi> of ſome <hi>Smell-feaſt Gueſts,</hi> at his <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diet,</hi> afforded him by the bounty of his <hi>Soveraign Master?</hi>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:169833:103"/>and which, this <hi>Man</hi> hath as a <hi>Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſodie,</hi> mingled with <hi>Miſconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Incertainties, Improbabilities, Impoſſibilities,</hi> In as much he can <hi>to poyſon the Memory of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> and blanch the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State, and Court. Wherein, his <hi>Fore-Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Himſelfe</hi> tooke <hi>Liſe and Livings,</hi> in the advance of his Family, with ſome repute and Fortune, to be what they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he is dead; Peace be upon his Grave.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion:</head>
               <p>ANd thus have we done, with our <hi>Pamphleter,</hi> and his <hi>Book,</hi> My pen being dull'd with diſdain, to deale with ſuch a ſubject, were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>good Men</hi> with the knowledg of a <hi>Truth;</hi> before that either
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:169833:104"/>
                  <hi>age,</hi> or longer time had <hi>waſted</hi> with too much <hi>Oblivion,</hi> or that the <hi>negligence of others,</hi> (of any) (more able I confeſſe) had given but too much way to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm</hi> the <hi>ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What I have don, may ſeem <hi>defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> in ſome part to ſome <hi>Perſons;</hi> whoſe <hi>Eminence</hi> in <hi>Court,</hi> and years of <hi>Experience,</hi> could have limm'd the <hi>Originalls</hi> with a bolder <hi>Pencill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, I have adventured upon this <hi>Copy;</hi> not to <hi>diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour Truth,</hi> by any <hi>Conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A hard Taske, I confeſſe; When <hi>Modeſty</hi> forbidds the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facement of Perſons, departed</hi> to their <hi>Graves of Reſt,</hi> whom <hi>living,</hi> we ſhould not dare to look in the <hi>Face;</hi> And whoſe <hi>Poſterities</hi> enjoy the <hi>merits</hi> of their <hi>Parents Vertues.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:169833:104"/>
               <p>To them I ſubmit; <hi>craving par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that without their leave, I have bin bold to ſpeak in their <hi>Cauſe;</hi> which might better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come greater <hi>Abilityes</hi> to <hi>plead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="200" facs="tcp:169833:105"/>
            <head>THE CHARACTER</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may merit diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether I ſhall Quarrell with the <hi>Character of King James,</hi> or let it alone, as the <hi>Pamphletter</hi> hath <hi>deſcrib'd</hi> Him, which (he ſays) <hi>Is eaſier to doe, than to take his Picture;</hi> and he gives the <hi>Reaſon</hi> for't, <hi>His Character was obvious to every eye,</hi> I am ſure His outward obſervations are ſo; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that His <hi>Picture was Inward;</hi> Tis true indeed, His beſt <hi>Peece</hi> was His <hi>Inſide,</hi> which wiſe <hi>men</hi> admir'd.</p>
            <p>Was ever <hi>Prince</hi> thus <hi>Limn'd</hi>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:169833:105"/>out to <hi>Poſterity,</hi> by His quilted <hi>Doublets,</hi> and full ſtuft <hi>Breeches?</hi> who reads His <hi>Court,</hi> needs none of this <hi>Character;</hi> ſo like they are in <hi>belying.</hi> But I ſpare the Author, and pitty the <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher.</hi> — The <hi>deficiency</hi> of the <hi>One,</hi> could not make out the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> For it becomes the <hi>Wit</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> in truth, to apprehend King <hi>James,</hi> whoſe <hi>wiſdome</hi> in His <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty,</hi> had eſteem beyond any Contemporary <hi>Potentate,</hi> with His <hi>Reign.</hi> Take Him in His turn, who had to do <hi>with all</hi> about Him. For at his entrance into His <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,</hi> He was engaged to go through with the <hi>difficulties,</hi> in <hi>Order as He found them,</hi> Or to make <hi>Bargain</hi> with <hi>All,</hi> the better to <hi>conſerve it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had He not done ſo, He might have ſound little leiſure, to live in <hi>Peace,</hi> and to enjoy His <hi>Realms</hi> as He did, with as much <hi>quiet</hi> as
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:169833:106"/>ever any King upon <hi>Earth,</hi> ſince the Story of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Who bent all his Counſells and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to promote that now exploded Motto of <hi>Beati Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifici.</hi>
               </note> and yet (in the like <hi>Example</hi> with us) fell to <hi>diſtraction</hi> in his Son that ſucceeded. Compare them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and find me a <hi>Parallell</hi> with more <hi>even concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know it were to be wiſhed, That in <hi>evill effects</hi> we could find out the true <hi>Cauſe;</hi> But like blind men, we grope, and catch hold of the neereſt; not looking up to Him who ballanceth <hi>Counſell</hi> with His <hi>Hand,</hi> and diſpoſeth the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi> in the <hi>future,</hi> not alwayes by the <hi>failings</hi> of the <hi>former.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Government of His <hi>Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place</hi> at home, what <hi>wiſdome</hi> was there not, to preſerve Himſelfe from <hi>jealouſie</hi> of His <hi>Predeceſſor,</hi> of being too haſty an <hi>Inheritour</hi> here? what <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> plots in the many againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Faith,</hi> which becauſe <hi>Providence</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:169833:106"/>Her to the laſt, was not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived</hi> with more cunning <hi>deſigns</hi> upon Him, who was to act over Her part, with diſadvantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt freſh <hi>plots</hi> to <hi>oppoſe</hi> Him?</p>
            <p>What <hi>Emiſſaries,</hi> and ſecret <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches</hi> by ſeverall <hi>Princes</hi> addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to prepare and gain Him, as an advance to eithers <hi>Intereſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVith what <hi>amaze</hi> to all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome?</hi> how He could ſo eaſily <hi>enter</hi> His <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> and then to <hi>amuze</hi> them all, how to <hi>deal</hi> with Him?</p>
            <p>How He was <hi>welcommed,</hi> and <hi>careſſed,</hi> by <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> of each <hi>Potentate,</hi> upon ſeverall <hi>deſigns</hi> of their <hi>Own?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat <hi>Contracts</hi> were made, and to be made, amongſt His <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> upon ſundry <hi>Overtures</hi> in <hi>Caſe</hi> He ſhould <hi>doe,</hi> even any thing but <hi>what He did,</hi> with what <hi>difficulty</hi> to any other, He main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Himſelfe in <hi>Peace</hi> againſt
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:169833:107"/>the <hi>Envy</hi> of them <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How was He by <hi>Conſanguinity imbroyl'd</hi> in His <hi>Son in Law's</hi> too haſty <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> when as a <hi>wiſe King</hi> He forewarn'd, and propheſied His <hi>deſtruction,</hi> and Chriſtendoms <hi>diſtraction?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat <hi>Ambaſſies</hi> publick, and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> priva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e He wiſely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for advantage of His and the Peoples <hi>Intereſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How he managed the <hi>Generall</hi> affairs of the <hi>Church Proteſtant,</hi> as a wiſe <hi>Patriarch,</hi> againſt the <hi>plots</hi> of the <hi>Pope?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far His <hi>Reputation,</hi> reacht out, to <hi>Forraign Princes</hi> far off?</p>
            <p>How from abroad and at home, He <hi>enriched</hi> His <hi>Subjects,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſ'd His own <hi>Revenue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat did he not doe without the <hi>Pike,</hi> if not with his <hi>Pen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How He preſerved <hi>Himſelf</hi> with friendſhip of <hi>all?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="205" facs="tcp:169833:107"/>
            <p>And thus in particular to put down in <hi>print,</hi> is the <hi>work</hi> of a <hi>weighty Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to take His true <hi>dimenſion,</hi> we have no <hi>Scale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can it be done without much <hi>diſhonor,</hi> to patch Him up in a petit <hi>Pamphlet:</hi> We ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to mature <hi>deliberation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the <hi>preſent,</hi> leave Him ſo great a King to His continued <hi>Memory,</hi> by His own excellent <hi>Impreſſions</hi> in <hi>Print,</hi> that ſame Him to <hi>Poſterity;</hi> whom we did not <hi>value,</hi> becauſe we could not <hi>comprehend.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
